Europe: A.D. 1801 to 1900

EUROPE

The population of Europe increased in this century from about 190 million to over 400 million. Industrialization of continental Europe followed England's examples and appeared early in the century basically in the regions of available coal, as in northern France, Belgium and the Ruhr Valley in Germany. Many of the industries and the necessary railway transportation systems were built and operated by governments, because of a lack of private capital. McNeill (Ref. 1) says that the industrialization of war began in the 1840s when railroads and semi-automated mass production together with Prussian breech-loaders and French naval steam efforts began to transform the previous military establishments. Western scientists (including Russians) tried to find the secret of damask steel (see pages 342, 348 and 643) and in so doing really initiated the field of metallography. (Ref. 2) The technology for using this metallurgy and other rapidly developing new fields in armaments actually started in the United States, by 1870. Russia, Spain, Sweden, Denmark and even Turkey and Egypt, were all following the original English example of importing American milling machinery for gun making. (Ref. 3)

The decline in oversea transportation costs made possible by the development of the steamship allowed an era of migration from Europe to the Americas, Oceania, Africa and Siberia. Railroads and steamships alike also extended the area from which bulky crops such as grains and minerals could be marketed and refrigeration allowed food and meat to be brought in from America, China, Australia and India. After 1871, although Europe was heavily armed, there were no wars for the remainder of the century. Ireland, England and all northern Europe, including Russia, had been badly hurt in mid-century, however, by the potato crop failure caused by the establishment of a Peruvian parasitic fungus, which implanted itself in European potatoes. The resulting famine in Irish, Belgian and German populations, along with typhus fever and other diseases, produced millions of deaths. (Ref. 4, 5)

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

By 1829 the Cyclades had become part of Greece, rather than Turkey. The Greek Cretans revolted against the Turks in the Greek-Turkish War at the end of the century and Crete became independent. (Ref. 6) The authorities then allowed Sir Arthur Evans to start excavations at Knossus. (Ref. 7) The Italian Frederico Halbherr had done some excavation work on the south shore of the island as early as 1884. Britain occupied Cyprus in 1877

GREECE

Led by Alexander Ypsilanti, the Greeks rose against the Muslim overlordship of the Turks in 1821 and in the following year declared their independence. The war was a savage one and also had elements of civil conf lict within Greek groups, themselves.

Great Britain, Russia and France finally helped Greece by def eating the Egyptian Muslim, Muhammad Ali, who had taken control of Greece, along with Crete and part of Syria. The victory came in a great naval battle of Navarino, in 1827 and an independent Greek kingdom was established in 1830 under Otto I, who had been a Bavarian prince. A constitution was forced upon the unwilling king in 1844 and by 1862 he was forced to abdicate in favor of Prince George of Denmark. After that Greece gradually gained more territory, acquiring the Ionian islands and Thessaly.

Early in the century Adamantois Korais created a new Greek literary medium, designed to emphasize connection with the classical tongue and to purify the language from heavy infiltration of Italian and Turkish words. (Ref. 8, 9)

UPPER BALKANS

From a material standpoint the Balkans lagged behind most of Europe. Panes of glass were not commonly seen in Serbia until this century and were still a rarity in Belgrade in 1808. (Ref. 10) In 1804 Serbian highlanders, under the rich peasant Kara-george, rose against the local Turks. The fierce fighting continued for several years and was finally put down by Turkish armies. Karageorge fled to Austria, but in 1815 Milos Obrenovic led a new revolt and that one succeeded so that Serbia proclaimed autonomy in 1830. In 1859 the areas of Moldavia and Wallachia became united as Romania, independent of Turkey. A native king was soon disposed and a Hohenzollern became Carol I, recognized in Europe as the sovereign of an independent Romania. Later in the century nationalist ideas spread rapidly throughout the entire Balkan area, but linguistic groups were so mixed up that a division on that basis became impossible. Languages included Romanian, Bulgarian, Turkish, Macedonian, Greek, Albanian, Serbian, Croatian, Slovenian and Hungarian with still some other minor ones, so that many conflicting national claims were made. Russia tried to intervene again in 1877, but the great powers again made her back down. Both Serbia and Romania became truly independent in 1878, although Romania had been united since 1859. Bosnia rebelled between 1875 and 1878, when Austria was permitted to proclaim a "protectorate" over it as Bosnia-Hercegovina. The Bulgarians rose up against Turkish rule in 1876 and after initial defeat were finally helped to independence by Russia in the Russo-Turkish War of 1877-78 and the subsequent Congress of Berlin. The Bulgarian state, however, was reduced to but a shadow of its former self. The remainder of Europe would not accept that situation immediately, so formal independence was not acknowledged until 1908. We have mentioned that Thessaly was added to Greece in 1881.

Greek merchant shippers constituted a limited area of transmission between the Orthdox Balkan Society and western Europe. On the cultural level, Karadjich and Obradovich used the peasant dialect of Herzegovina as the basis for literary Serbian, replacing the old standard, which was based on Church Slavonic. This allowed Serbian and Croatian languages to converge and made modern Yugoslavia a possibility. (Ref. 11, 12, 13)

ITALY

Napoleon transformed Italy into a kingdom, with himself as king, putting one of his family as viceroy of Italy and another as king of Naples. Pope Pius VII was kidnapped and held captive until Napoleon's downfall in 1814. Thereafter Italy became in part under Austria's control, part under the Bourbon Ferdinand and part under the House of Savoy. Minor revolts, which occurred in Naples and Piedmont in 1821 and in Parma, Modena and Romagna in 1830-31, had no national aims, but later uprisings were more forceful. In July, 1848 Charles Albert of Piedmont was decisively beaten by Austrians at Custozza in Venetia. This led to a closer union of Austria and Prussia, while Italy remained divided. Further war against Austria in 1858 and 1859, with French support, resulted in the union of Sicily, Naples, Umbria, Romagna and Marches with Piedmont-Sardinia under Camillo Benso di Cavour, prime minister of the Kingdom of Sardinia. He was one of the great European statesmen of those times. Victor Emmanuel II was king of Sardinia at the time and it was he, along with Cavour, who secured France's aid in throwing off the yoke of Austria.

Garibaldi had taken over control of Sicily and Naples, with his thousand volunteers, but these areas were annexed to Emmanuel's domain in 1860. In 1861 an Italian parliament met in Turin and declared Victor Emmanuel as King of all Italy. When Austria was defeated by Prussia in 1866, Italy acquired Venetia. Up until about that date Italians, like most Germans, were more attached to their provincial rulers and cultures (Tuscan, Emilian, etc.) than to a national idealism, although the middle class of people had objected to Austrian rule. By the last 2/3 of the century, the Italians extended the Piedmontese (Sardinian) constitution to the whole country and made Italy a centralized entity on the French model. (Ref. 14, 15, 16)

An interesting sidelight is the beginning of the control of malaria in the environs of Rome at the beginning of this century by Pope Pius Vll. Ever since the days of the late Roman Empire, when a shortage of manpower and the frequent barbarian invasions led to neglect of the drainage systems of the city and the surrounding areas, which had previously been irrigated, malaria had been a serious, endemic disease of the region. From a population of 750,000 in 70 B.C. Rome fell to 35,000 in A.D. 1050 and malaria has been indicted by some as the chief cause. But the draining of the marshes was started again by Pius VII and completed in the next century by Mussolini, when the population of Rome reached a million. (Ref. 17)

CENTRAL EUROPE

Northern Europe had one of the worst summers of all recorded time in 1816. There was frost in July and practically no harvest, so that famine resulted. (Ref. 18)

GERMANY

Between 1801 and 1803 Napoleon and his minister, Talleyrand, supervised the reorganization of the old Holy Roman Empire and this was done, not on German soil, but in Paris. The initial steps involved over 1/2 of the more than 300 political entities that had claimed sovereign status since the Treaty of Westphalia. Some 64 ecclesiastical principalities were secularized and 45 of the 51 free-cities were absorbed into larger units. Then the German princes confiscated all religious establishments and the lands of most of the "Knights". By October of 1806 Napoleon had delivered Prussia a telling blow at Jena and the French armies entered Berlin. In the same year Napoleon established the Confederation of the Rhine, with himself as its official protector. All states of the old empire joined this except Austria, Prussia, Brunswick and electoral Hesse. This definitely ended the Holy Roman Empire, forcing the abdication of the title of emperor by Francis II of Austria and then Germany began to draw itself together. At the same time Napoleon was rewarding Wuerttemburg, Saxony and Bavaria for their loyalties by elevating their dukes to kings and giving each a little more territory. Saxony got the Duchy of Warsaw from Prussia; Maximilian became king of Bavaria. But by 1813 Metternick got his Austria to declare war again on France and maneuvered to get Bavaria to desert Napoleon. In a 4 day battle near Leipzig, Napoleon was totally defeated and in the later Peace of Paris and the European Congress at Vienna, which lasted 10 months, Europe was divided among the 4 great powers of Prussia, Austria, Russia and England.

Prussia was re-made into a modern state by a group of enlightened legislators, chiefly Freiherr vom Stein, from a family of Rhineland Knights. The great General Staff was created between 1803 and 1809, utilizing intellectual, vigorous officers. (Ref. 19)

The serfs were freed, commerce and industry released from many restrictions and the army made more efficient and humane. On the total scene, however, Frederick William III of Prussia played a subsidiary role to both Metternich of Austria and Alexander of Russia. A German Confederation was formed of 35 sovereign principalities and 4 free-cities.

Map taken from Reference 97.

Frederick William hated that Confederation but Metternich utilized it to his advantage.

In the 1820s while many parts of Europe reverberated with liberal revolutions, Germany and Austria remained tranquil, although after 1830 some of the more liberal states of south and west Germany experienced mild disturbances. In Prussia, the widespread introduction of steam power in 1812 and an extensive net of railways produced an economic boom and eventually helped in the unification of Germany. Prussia further gained by a high tariff on goods transported across her territory and since she sat astride the most important trade routes between northern and southern Europe, this was a considerable boon. The Zollverein (Customs Union) derived out of that tariff was joined by 7 small neighboring states in 1828 and Prussian imperialism was already underway to some degree. By 1842 almost all German states except Austria, Hanover and a few free-cities had joined the Zollverein. This, along with railroads and the electric telegraph, bound the states together, acting as a unifier. By 1848 there were 3,000 miles of track in Germany. In spite of that, in some areas there were economic failures, unemployment and occasional uprisings.

The plague epidemic of 1846 was another problem and that was followed by world wide trade and financial crises, crop failures and inflation. In 1848 revolutions spread across Europe again, most of them essentially interrelated. In Germany there were three main aims: The unification of the country; the demand for basic civil rights and a measure of popular sovereignty; and freedom for serfs with better hours, wages and benefits for city workers. In the lesser states such as Wuerttembury and Hesse, there did result more liberal cabinets. In Baden there was much blood shed in many massacres.

In Bavaria things were different as King Maximilian I allowed a liberal constitution and promoted arts, science and architecture. When his successor Ludwig I gave his low-born Irish mistress, Lola Montez, a title, he was forced to abdicate and Maximilian II became king with a moderately liberal ministry. Both Ludwig II and son Otto I were brilliant but insane. The former was a friend of the composer, Wagner. In the meantime, Munich University had been transformed into an artistic and scholarly center.

By this time in Prussia there was revolution. The first disorders arose in the Rhineland, Silesia and East Prussia. Eventually crowds took over Berlin and the king placed himself at the mercy of his people and a meeting of the United Diet was called. Soon, however, royal power was re-assumed, the new liberal cabinet was dismissed and a new government formed under the conservative Count of Brandenburg.

In spite of all, many groups still worked for the unification of Germany. Some 600 delegates from various states met at Frankfurt in 1848, but the delegates got bogged down in too many problems of nationality, cross-purposes, etc. and this, as well as the revolutions, failed at that time. Because of the failure of the 1848 revolutions, Karl Marx was stimulated to write the Communist Manifesto, with the help of Engles. Actually the final unification of Germany involved three wars. The first was Prussia against Denmark. In 1861 King Wilhelm I came to the throne of Prussia and chose Count Otto von Bismarck-Schonhousen as his chief minister. In 1862 Bismarck dismissed the Prussian parliament, allied with Austria and attacked Denmark, taking Schleswig-Holstein in 1864. The "Seven Weeks War" followed in 2 years, with three theaters: (1) Italy, in which the Italians were defeated on both land and sea; (2) Germany, involving defeat of the Hanoverians; and (3) Bohemia, where the Austrians came to the Bohemians' aid. (Ref. 20) In that war Helmut von Moltke showed how the aristocratic General Staff planners could speed up and control deployment of vast numbers of men by carefully calculating everything ahead of time. In addition, the use of breech-loading rifles for the first time (after 26 years of transition) and the probable use of Alfred Krupp's breech-loading steel artillery must have played large roles. The Austrians, however, had 736 new rifled cannon and 58 smooth-bores to the Prussians' 492 rifled and 306 smooth-bores. The Austrians lost the Battle of Koenig-graetz because they had their infantry charge the foe in dense columnar formations. (Ref. 21) At the end of that conflict Prussia annexed Hanover and other German states, abolishing the Bund and forming a new North German Confederation. Bohemia, Austria, Bavaria, Wuerttemburg, Hohenzollern Baden, Palatinate and Alsace-Lorraine were not included in that confederation. Bismarck and Moltke shared the glory of that political reorganization of Germany with King Wilhelm. (Ref. 22)

The third war was the Franco-German War of 1870-71 which was easily won by Bismarck1 and resulted in the withdrawal of French forces from Italy and the acquisition of Alsace-Lorraine. Prussian planning defeated French elan as the French speed of supply and deployment fell far behind. A new German Empire grew out of that victory, along with a newly awakened German nationalism. All of the principalities mentioned above, except Bohemia and Austria, now joined this new empire, which was headed by the king of Prussia, who took the title of Deutscher Kaiser (Caesar). Perhaps unfortunately for the future of Germany, this empire contained a number of non-Germans, some Danes, many Poles and, of course, many Frenchmen in Alsace and Lorraine.

Otto von Bismarck-Schonhousen was a remarkable man, fluent in both English and French as well as German. As chancellor he placated England and Russia, obtained colonies in Africa and the Pacific and made many social reforms within Germany, itself. He promoted a good deal of social legislation which included: a health insurance law which gave financial and medical aid to workers off work with illness; an accident insurance law for workers' disability compensation; and an old age and invalidism insurance for all those disabled and/or over 70 years of age. The reader will have no trouble recognizing most of these features in present day American life. In 1890 Wilhelm II, known to the generation of the writer as simply "the Kaiser", dismissed Bismarck and turned to building up the army and navy, developing military industry and making enemies on all sides. He was not prepared for the task which he had inherited in 1888. Always immature, psychologically warped, perhaps in part because of his crippled left arm, sadly susceptible to flattery, he believed in "divine right" monarchy and at the same time loved all things modern - industry and engineering in particular. After he had deposed Bismarck he made Count Georg Leo von Caprivi his chancellor for 4 years, then followed with the once able but then aged Prince Chlodwig zu Hohenlohe-Schillingf uerst of Bavaria. In this man's senility, Wilhelm could, in truth, "railroad" through most of his own ideas, all of which resulted in extensive world involvement.

Map taken from Reference 97

By the last half of the century all of Germany west of the Elbe, but especially the area along the Rhine, had mechanized industry and eventually outstripped France and England. It had the raw materials and developed a great scientific, educational system and research facilities. After 1871 Germany set the pace for industrial supremacy with a lead in chemicals and electricity, with the latter industry dominated by Werner Siemens and Emil Rathenau. The German phase of the Industrial Revolution embraced a wider variety of materials (electrical, chemical, petroleum and light metals), but coal and iron remained primary. Coal was used for tars and derivatives as diverse as aspirin, dyes and explosives. Iron underwent potable chemical diversification after the invention of the Bessemer converter in 1856. Railroads were necessary to unlock mineral wealth previously cut off from exploration. The German contributions to industrial development included deliberate, planned invention, extensive credit through banks and cartels and human engineering, with the cultivation of an elite in both the military and industry. Even with the Industrial Revolution, Germany maintained an adequate food supply by putting an additional 2,000,000 acres under cultivation.

In the last decade of the l9th century the population of Germany increased 15% to 56,400,000. Forty percent of the people engaged in industry, twelve percent in trade and communication. Friedrich Siemens, with others, developed the open hearth method of making steel directly from ore. In one generation, 1840-1875, these north-central Europeans went from the Middle Ages to Modern Times. (Ref. 24) But there was inadequate urban housing, crowding, exorbitant rents and low wages. Germany's troubles and policies eventually resulting in World War I were not entirely the fault of Kaiser Wilhelm, but of Bismarckian government without a Bismarck. One of the important changes under the Kaiser was the rapid expansion of the German navy. New ships were launched and the Kiel Canal dug from the North Sea to the Baltic, bypassing any possible Danish blockade. In 1897 Admiral Tirpitz was put in charge and the naval program accelerated until well into the next century.

But Germany of this century was not all politics, industry, army and navy. F.W.A. Sertuerner isolated morphine as a pure alkaloid in 1806; Robert Koch established the bacterial cause of anthrax and tuberculosis; Rudolf Virchow (1821-1902) was called the "Pope" of medicine in Europe. He wrote on leukemia, thrombosis, embolism and phlebitis as well as delving into multiple scientific and social fields. At the end of the century German speaking countries (and we must include Austria in this) had the leadership in medicine. In the period of 1815 to 1840 alone, there were great men in literature, music, education, scholarship, philosophy and science, as well. The University of Berlin was founded in 1811. Some of the more famous names of the era include Beethoven, Schubert, Mendelssohn, Schumann, Goethe and Schopenhouer. (Ref. 25, 26, 27, 28, 29)

AUSTRIA (Part of the Austro-Hungarian Empire)

Austria was invaded by Napoleon while Great Britain, Russia, Austria and Sweden were forming an alliance, along with Prussia, to contain him. This alliance was the so-called "Third Coalition". The Austrians suffered a defeat at Ulm; Napoleon entered Vienna and then annihilated the Austrians and Russians together in the Battle of Austerlitz in Moravia in late 1805. In the Peace of Pressburg on December 26, 1805 Austria ceded all claims to her Italian and south German territories and dropped from her status as a world power2. Emperor Franz (Francis) had to give up his title of Holy Roman Emperor and thereafter the Habsburgs were emperors of Austria and Hungary only. Napoleon reentered Vienna, took up residence in Schoenbrunn Palace and continued to dismember Austria. It was in this desperate situation that Klemens Lothar Metternich, Austrian ambassador to Paris, returned to be imperial chancellor. To understand this complex, capable man, who has strong admirers and vicious detractors among the historians, will require some additional details.

Basically Metternich was probably the greatest diplomat of his time, the French Talleyrand not withstanding. He arranged a marriage of Princess Marie Louise to Napoleon, contributed a small Austrian contingent to Napoleon's disastrous Moscow expedition of 1812, thus gaining an armistice from the French emperor allowing some breathing room to reform his armies. He then offered to mediate peace proposals with France, Prussia and Russia. Bonaparte refused the terms, was defeated by Prussia and Russia at the Battle of Leipzig (1813) and abdicated. It was Metternich's diplomatic victory and the Treaty of Paris, which followed, called for no territorial concession or reparations, but merely arranged for the European Congress in Vienna to be held two months later. That Congress of Vienna of 1815, which included the "big four" of Russia, England, Prussia3, and Austria, promptly elected Metternich as president. Amid much pomp, entertainment and back-stage diplomacy, Metternich arranged for Austria to regain much of her old territory in return for giving up Belgium, part of the Netherlands and a few small holdings on the Rhine. Austria gained 4,500,000 people and the undisputed hegemony in Italy. After that Congress, Austria enjoyed her last great time as a prestigious power in Europe, with a period of thirty years of unbroken peace.

An interesting sidelight to the machinations of Metternich and his Austrian emperor has to do with the treatment of the only son of Napoleon. Born in March, 1811 to Marie Louis, daughter of Emperor Franz, Napoleon had his son christened "Napoleon Francis Joseph Charles Bonaparte, King of Rome". After his father 's banishment to Elba, the boy was tentatively to be given the title of Prince of Parma, with his mother as regent, but in the end Metternich and the emperor took him to Vienna for "protection" while his mother was given a small principality in Italy to rule. In Vienna, as a bright, handsome child, Napoleon II was raised virtually as a political prisoner until his death from tuberculosis at the age of 21 years. To the end he intermittently hoped for a throne and was actually considered at one time or another for the crowns of Greece, Poland and Belgium, as well as France. His mother took a lover by whom she had several illegitimate children and turned against her banished husband and essentially abandoned her French son. (Ref. 33)

Concerning Metternich, the other side of the coin shows that his domestic "system" led to revolution and his eventual downfall. To prevent the rise of nationalism in his multi- racial domain, he developed almost a police state, denying all freedoms. There was no free parliament, no free press, no free university, no intelligent civil service. All liberalism was suppressed. The revolution was led by the intellectuals in 1848, and the aims there were different than those in Germany, for in Austria the revolution was designed at securing autonomy for the component nationalities living under the Habsburg rule. In the turmoil, Metternich was forced to resign and he escaped to London, while Vienna was turned over to the National Guard. The Hungarians adopted their own constitution and other coalitions rose to demand self-rule. The Milanese forced the withdrawal of Austrian troops and the Venetians set up an independent republic again. The Czechs, Moravians and Galicians were all clamoring for autonomy. In the meantime (while Metternich was still there), the old emperor had died (1835) and the inadequate Ferdinand, hydrocephalic, epileptic and close to an idiot, reigned in name only. Prince Felix von Schwarzenberg assumed the post of chief minister and persuaded the weak Ferdinand to abdicate in favor of his 18 year old grandson Franz-Joseph I and between them, the Habsburg Empire was restored.

In a few years the new emperor took as his bride the beautiful Elizabeth, a Wittelsbach of Bavaria and then proceeded to complete his reign of "sixty-eight years of almost unbroken misfortune and disaster but he never swerved or flinched from his mission"4. By remaining neutral in the Crimean War he antagonized Russia and exposed Austria's weaknesses to the whole of Europe. His empire contained 50,000,000 subjects and after his able prime minister's death (Schwarzenberg), he attempted to rule alone as an autocrat. In the field as commander he soon lost Lombardy and other lesser territories and found that his Slav and Magyar troops were not very loyal. Elizabeth left him for all practical purposes, perhaps due in part to her mental health and in part because of very serious mother-in-law problems. Then Bismarck appeared on the scene from the north in Bohemia, with three separate armies. As Bohemia's ally, Austria sent Field Marshal Benedek north to attack. In the battle of Koeniggraetz (Sadowa) he eventually met def eat. (See page 1073). In the final peace of that 7 weeks war, Austria was excluded from the German League and Venetia was given up once again to Emmanuel's Italy (1864). Then there was peace for 40 years, until 1914.

Franz-Joseph had picked poor prime ministers after Schwarzenberg. There was no Bismarck, no Disraeli, no Gladstone nor Clemenceau. The one who came nearest to his liking and trust was Count Edward Taaf e, who lasted 14 years in the job and kept some peace by diplomacy only between the Poles, Czechs, Hungarians, Slovenes and the Austrians. But by 1886 there was great political strife between German and Bohemian subjects and Franz-Joseph did not well understand their feelings, but felt the only solution was continual adherence of both to Vienna. Georg von Schoenerer was an early leader of the Pan-Germanic movement, which was also anti-semitic. A program of state ownership of railroads, graduated income tax and the separation of church and school were proposals offered by Linz. Another "radical" was Viktor Adler, who founded the Social Democratic Party and organized demonstrations.

Austria's contributions to world knowledge and culture during this century were fantastic. In medicine alone the accomplishments were legion. Carl Rokitansky was the founder of pathological anatomy; Hermann Nothnagle first evaluated blood pressure in diagnosis; and Ernest Bruecke pioneered in physiology. There were multiple world famous psychiatrists - Freud, Krafft-Ebing, Joseph Brewer and others. Among the orthopedic surgeons were Adolf Lorenz and Lorenz Boehler, Jr. Bela Schick devised the diphtheria skin test, while Johannes Mueller is credited with establishing medicine as a true science. Von Helmholtz developed the ophthalmoscope; Koch worked out the bacteriology of tuberculosis and cholera; and Semmelweiss found the cause of puerperal fever, making one of the great advances in obstetrical care. Probably the greatest surgeon of the late century was Albert Theodor Billroth, born and educated in Germany, but working later in Zurich and especially Vienna, where he was the first to perform extensive operations on the pharynx, larynx and stomach. His students subsequently filled most of the prestigious surgical appointments in Europe. Incidentally, Billroth was also a musician and a great friend of Brahms.

Technological advances in Austria may be listed as follows:

1815 - Founding of Vienna Polytechnic
1829 - First trial of screw driven vessel, in Trieste Harbor
1839 - Invention of the sewing machine by Madersperger of Vienna, and also the time of Austria's first railway
1864 - First internal combustion engine invented by Siegried Marcus
1866 - Typewriter invented by Mitterhofer of the Tyrol

The great musicians of Austria included Johann Strauss, Joseph Haydn, Ludwig van Beethoven, Johann Brahms (originally from Hamburg, but settled in Vienna), Richard Wagner (from Bavaria) and Franz Schubert. In 1873 building was started on Vienna University, but in that same year a cholera epidemic broke out and a "Black Friday" occurred on the stock exchange, with a resulting financial crisis, which spread across Europe and even to the United States. By 1890 Vienna had 1,300,000 people.

The Empress Elizabeth was killed by an assassin in Geneva in 1898 and the heir to the throne, her son Rudolph, had committed suicide some 9 years previously. At the end of the century there were mass meetings of the Social Democrats in Vienna and the cry was "Young Czechs" against Germans. (Ref. 35, 36, 37, 38) Braudel (Ref. 39) quotes the historian of rural Austrian society, Otto Bruenner, as saying that the peasantry of Austria was the real foundation stone of European society and that regardless of changes in government, it had remained essentially -unchanged in structure from Neolithic times right down to the l9th century.

HUNGARY (Part of Austro-Hungarian Empire, and the previous paragraphs must also be read to get a complete picture of Hungary at this period)

After 1790 the chief demand of the Hungarian Diet, whenever the Austrian emperor allowed it to meet, was for wider use of the Magyar language in administration, courts and education. Lexicographers re-fashioned and enriched the native tongue and the cult of language was accompanied by similar dedication to national costumes, dances and the like. The Croats in the empire fought the switch to the Magyar language and began to develop their own tongue, along with a sense of Pan-Slavism. Count Istvan Szechenyi was a great Hungarian nationalist whose books Kitel and Vilag started the "Reform Era" in Hungary in 1830. He desired Magyarism and reform, but under the blessings of the emperor. His contemporary and eventual opponent, Lajos Kossuth, wanted progress and complete liberty from Austria. In 1840 the government passed a law making Magyar the official language of all institutions of Great Hungary. The Croats were given 6 years to conform. The reaction of the non-Magyars, including the immigrant Saxons and Slavs and the Romanians in Transylvania, was strong. Revolution broke out in Austria in 1848, along with that in much of Europe, and Kossuth took advantage to reform Hungary as a limited monarchy subject to the Austrian monarch, but in many internal respects, almost free. But the Serbs and Croats rebelled against Hungary under their leader, Jellacic.

At first he had Austrian help, but as further revolt occurred in Austria itself, this help soon dwindled and in the end Hungary triumphed, even temporarily breaking away from Austria. Franz-Joseph called on Russia for help and two Russian armies entered Hungary, forcing Kossuth to surrender and he personally fled to Turkey. By 1867 Hungary had re- covered her integrity under Deak, by the Ausgleich (compromise) of 1867, under which Hungarians won equal status with the German speaking population. The situation had in part been promoted by the Empress Elizabeth, who had a real and compassionate interest in Hungary. Thus began the "Age of Dualism" and one might then truly speak of "Austria-Hungary". Magyarization of all the people then followed, with changes of individual names and places to conform with the Magyar language.

By 1900 Hungary had over a million workers in mining and industry. There were two universities in Hungary proper, one in Croatia. There were a large number of colleges of law, theology, mining, etc. This was the time of the physicist Lorand Eotvds and the physician Semmelweiss, who was actually Hungarian, although part of his work was done in Vienna. Budapest was 79.8% Magyar speaking, but other ethnic frontiers remained on the east, north and west. Jews made up 4.9% of the overall population, 25% in Budapest and they had almost a monopoly in banking and finance. (Ref. 40, 41)

CZECHOSLOVAKIA

This area continued restlessly under the rule of the Austria-Hungarian Empire. Moravia was an important battle ground for Napoleon's rout of the Russian and Austrian forces, in the first decade of the century. After 1840 to 1850 the rapid growth of cities in the Habsburg domains, together with the ravages of cholera resulted in peasant migration into the towns of Bohemia and Hungary to such an extent that the previous pattern of those people learning to speak German and being "Germanized" was changed and a nationalistic ideal appeared. The result was that Prague became a Czech-speaking city within one-half century, just as Budapest had become a Magyar-speaking capital.

In the last of the century there was growing business prosperity, with particular emphasis on textiles, shoes, cheap china and glass, sugar refineries, breweries, coal and graphite mines and the great Skoda machine shop at Pilsen. Prague University had new vigor with Professor Thomas Masaryk becoming one of the greatest of Czech philosophers and patriots. He later became a member of the Austrian Parliament, promoting the Bohemian cause and in the next century was to become the first president of the Czechoslovakian Republic. In Moravia, there were riots in 1899 with the looting of Jewish and German houses so that troops had to be called out to restore order.

SWITZERLAND

We noted in the last chapter that Napoleon had conquered Switzerland. In 1803 he allowed a satisfactory federal constitution and with Bonaparte's fall, the Confederation was restored. In 1815 the Congress of Vienna guaranteed the perpetual neutrality of that land and this had never been violated to date. After a short civil war in 1847 a new close national union developed and a new federal constitution was written. All tariff barriers between the cantons were removed between 1848 and 1874. The International Red Cross was formed at the Geneva Convention of 1864, chiefly due to the efforts of Jean Henri Dunant, a Swiss banker, who had happened to see a battlefield in northern Italy littered with tens of thousands of wounded soldiers lying unattended on the ground. The Red Cross insignia is the Swiss flag, with colors reversed. (Ref. 42, 43)

WESTERN EUROPE

SPAIN

The Napoleonic Wars brought Spain to the edge of ruin. After war with France and then against England, as a French ally, Spain's sea power was destroyed and Napoleon put his brother Joseph on the Spanish throne in 1805. In 1812 Joseph, with his Cortes (Congress), abolished the Inquisition and limited the powers of the Catholic Church. Fighting continued, however, in the Peninsular War, with Great Britain entered on the side of the Spanish people and eventually driving out the French. The locals had never accepted Joseph and Napoleon's dominion was already collapsing, anyway, so after the Peninsular War, King Ferdinand VII resumed rule and revoked the new laws regarding the church. Spanish overseas colonies were revolting, however, and the people of Spain blamed the king, so he was taken prisoner and anarchy followed, with various temporary rulers, including Isabella II, who reigned from 1833 to 1868, at first with regents. The contesting of her succession by her uncle, Don Carlos led to the Carlist Wars. In these revolts most of the Basque provinces and much of Catalonia supported Carlos. Civil wars and insurrections followed one after another until 1876, over a year after Isabella's son Alfonso XII had been proclaimed king. The economy remained critical and Spain had industry in only a few small areas. Even in 1829 the trade was only 1/3 of what it had been in 1785. The last great European famine was in Andalusia in 1882. On the death of Alfonso XII, his posthumous son Alfonso XIII reigned during the remainder of the century with his mother as regent. (Ref. 44, 45)

The Spanish-American War developed in 1898, secondary to the long-standing insurrection in Cuba, with the American press sympathetic to the rebels. When a United States ship, the U.S.S. Maine, was mysteriously blown up in Havana Harbor, war was formally declared. When that war ended and the treaty signed in Paris, the last of Spanish America was lost. (Ref. 46, 47, 48) (Some additional information about Spain is to be found in the next section on PORTUGAL)

PORTUGAL

As the century opened Portugal was ruled by Pedro III, under the regency of his mother, Maria I. Trouble with the French led to a humiliating treaty in 1801 by which Portugal had to renounce treaties with England and pay heavy indemnities. Then when Spain temporarily allied with France, it was Manuel de Godoy, Spanish chief minister and lover of the Spanish Queen Maria Luisa, who invited Napoleon's aid in the dismemberment of Portugal. A French army under General Andoche Junot crossed into Spain and then a combined French and Spanish force took off for Portugal. The Portuguese royal family, including the Prince Regent Dom Joao, with 15,000 courtiers, took off for Brazil under protection of the British fleet. As Junot entered Lisbon he immediately imposed an indemnity of 100 million francs. (1807). In the meantime, however, the new Spanish King Joseph, put on the throne by Napoleon, had met with stiff local opposition and in 1808 two French divisions, mistakenly believing they were surrounded by greatly superior forces, had surrendered and 22,800 of them were interned on the island of Cabrera, where hundreds of them died of starvation or disease. The English government, now realizing that Junot's forces in Lisbon could not be reinforced from Spain, sent Sir Arthur Wellesley (the future Duke of Wellington) to Portugal with a fleet and army. He was soon joined by bands of Portuguese infantry and on August 21, 1808 he completely defeated Junot's army as it came out of Lisbon. This was the Peninsular War, which we have mentioned previously. The British forces were supplied by sea, using techniques developed during the American Revolution. In a crucial battle just outside Lisbon in 1810-11 the well-fed British troops pushed back some 250,000 starved French soldiers. All of this allowed Portugal to again be in alliance with England and by 1814 Wellington had even helped the Spanish push the French out of Spain, also.

But Portugal's troubles were not over. A liberal revolution against the regency broke out in 1820 and Joao VI returned from Brazil. His forces stopped the insurrection but he accepted a liberal constitution in 1822 in the same year that Brazil declared its independence under Pedro I, who was Joao's elder son. In spite of these things, Portugal made progress, with sanitary reforms, the building of railroads, telephone lines and schools and the abolition of slavery in her colonies. In the last half of the century under Pedro V and Louis I of the House of Coburg-Braganza, there was respite from civil strife, but there were political and financial troubles resulting from long civil wars which had raged during the middle years of this period. There were two opposing factions of professional politicians, the Regenerators and the Progressives and they developed a system of rotating power, with a resulting sterile, pseudo-parliamentary system. At Louis' death in 1889 sporadic revolts, strikes and conspiracies returned. Louis' son Carlos I (Charles) even tried in 1900 to support a dictatorship under Joao Franco, head of the Regenerator party, but this caused a violent reaction, and in 1908 Carlos and the heir apparent were shot in a public square in Lisbon. (Ref. 49, 50, 51, 52)

FRANCE

In the last chapter we noted that at the end of the 18th century Napoleon returned to France as consul after his escape from the British in his Egyptian fiasco.

We should add that on November 12, 1799 the Provisional Consuls - Napoleon, Sieyes and Roger Ducos - met in Luxembourg Palace to make plans to rebuild France, a nation in economic, political, religious and moral disarray. Some effects of the French Revolution had been positive, such as peasant proprietorship, capitalism, replacement of feudalism by a free peasantry, encouragement of science, a world view of theology and a national system of schools. But true democracy was given only a nod as all officials from local to national levels were made by appointment by the central government. In effect the central government was soon just Napoleon.

We must pause to give at least a thumb-nail sketch of this man, Napoleon Bonaparte, who has had some 200,000 books and pamphlets written about him and who has been labeled by some as a hero struggling to give unity and law to Europe and by others as an ogre, who drained the blood of France and ravaged Europe. He was born on Corsica in 1.769, only a few months after France had purchased that mountainous island f rom Genoa and Napoleon always remained basically an Italian Corsican of noble Tuscany pedigree. His brother Joseph was initially made King of Naples, then of Spain; his brother Louis married a de Beauharnais and became King of Holland; sister Maria Anna Elisa was the Grand Duchess of Tuscany; Pauline married Prince Camillo Borghese; Maria Caroline married Joachim Mural and became Queen of Naples; while brother Jerome rose to be King of Westphalia.

In his youth Napoleon did well in mathematics, geography, history, and Plutarch. He was selected from his French military school- to receive advanced instruction at the Ecole Militaire and then went on to rapid advancement in the French army. His first wife, Josephine de Beauharnais, widow of a vicomte murdered in the revolution, was older than Napoleon by 6 years and was the mother of 2 before her marriage to Bonaparte. Although devoted to her and yet at times tormented by her occasional- infidelities, Napoleon finally divorced Josephine because she remained childless by him. He then married the Austrian Archduchess, Maria Louise, who did present him with an heir, only about 3 years before his final military defeats5.

To summarize in advance the information to follow, Bonaparte ruled France for 15 years as First Consul of the First Republic (1799-1804) and as emperor from 1804 to 1814 and during that time conquered almost the whole of Europe, finally being defeated by a coalition of Austria, Prussia and Russia at the Battle of Leipzig in Germany in October 1813 and subsequently again by the British at Waterloo, Belgium in 1814. Louis XVIII was then called to be king. Napoleon himself estimated that his campaigns resulted in the deaths of 1,700,000 Frenchmen, more than were killed in both subsequent World Wars. It is interesting, however, that more soldiers died of typhus f ever in the Napoleonic Wars than in battle. Small-pox was not a problem in his own armies as he had had all his troops vaccinated in 1805, introducing this to Europe. He also pioneered the large scale use of canned food for his troops. The road to defeat was a long one. Napoleon abandoned the idea of siege warfare early and aimed at defeating an enemy by out-maneuvering him.

Crushing defeats were given to Austria at Austerlitz (1805), to Prussia at Jena (1806) and to Russia at Friedland (1807). In 1808 in a rapid invasion of Spain a British expedition force was forced back to the sea6. Switzerland came under French protection, Spain, northeast Italy, Naples and Westphalia became satellite kingdoms under the Bonaparte family. Only reduced kingdoms of Austria and Prussia preserved some semblance of independence. Napoleon's great international frustration was England and his attempt to avenge that enemy was probably the cause of his downfall. Sitting in conquered Berlin in late 1806, as the son of Maria Louise and the grandson of Emperor Franz, he was held virtually as a prisoner of Austria from childhood until his death. More details are given on page 1077. The last thoughts of Napoleon I on his death bed were of this boy. (Ref. 53)

He decreed that all ports and coasts of the European continent were closed to the entry of British goods. The blockade worked at first and by 1810 England was in a severe economic depression while France prospered with an accelerated Industrial Revolution. Then suddenly the situation reversed. The French textile industry was unable to get raw material and capital, a banking firm in Lubeck failed and in 1811 France had a great depression, with bank failures, factory closings, strikes, poverty, riots and areas of starvation. The blockade had been particularly damaging to Russia also and after Czar Alexander had made peace with Turkey, he signed a mutual aid pact with Sweden and offered an alliance with England, while he opened his ports to ships of all nations. Then he declared war on France.

The mobilizations of both the Russians and French were massive. Napoleon had some difficulty conscripting the now somewhat satiated French, but annexations to France almost doubled the number of "Frenchmen" to about 44,000,000 by 1810 so that eventually he had an army of 680,000 fighting men, less than 1/2 of which were actually French. Only a minority even spoke French. (Ref. 54) Relentlessly he churned on to Vilna, Smolensk and Moscow, with the Russian armies retreating in an orderly f ashion ahead of him and burning and destroying all possible provisions. As he arrived in Moscow he found the city almost deserted and then mysteriously 2/3 of the city was burned, whether by the French, Russian soldiers or by order of Count Rostopchin, governor of Moscow, no one knows for certain. Finding no one to fight and with winter approaching, Napoleon decided to return to central Europe. Winter caught him and Russian troops harassed him from the flanks and the rear. The loss of men was unbelievable and only 30,000 men re-crossed the Nieman River into East Prussia in December, 1812. Dominique-Jean Larrey, Napoleon's chief surgeon is said to have performed over 200 amputations during one 24 hour period during that Russian campaign. (Ref. 55)

Czar Alexander had followed the retreating French armies as they approached East Prussia and he urged the king and people of Prussia to join him against Napoleon. In the meantime the latter was trying to recoup his financial losses, conscript still another army, defend his Italian possessions against Austria and console the French people for his defeat in Russia. He arranged a temporary truce through the help of Metternich, but all nations simply used that time for more war preparation. Napoleon received a contingent of men from Denmark and returned to the battles, but Bernadotte of Sweden brought an army to join the allles of Prussia, Russia, Bohemia and Austria and finally after Napoleon's Saxor and Bavarian troops deserted him, he was soundly defeated at Leipzig in 3 days of terrible carnage in October of 1813.

The Netherlands then overthrew French rule (with Prussian help), parts of Italy were lost again to Austria, English troops took the Scheldt and Wellington crossed from Spain into France (see page 1083). Unemployment and poverty was all over France and the stock market fell almost 50% in the year. The senate and legislature were in open revolt against the emperor and after a few more military set-backs with the allied armies driving westward and entering Paris on March 31, 1814, the senate deposed Napoleon and chose Talleyrand as President of a new republic. The Russian czar prevented the invading armies from pillaging Paris and arranged for Napoleon's exile on the island of Elba, with an annual stipend of 2,000,000 francs, which the French government failed to pay.

Louis XVIII, grandson of Louis XV, "59 years of age, genial and courteous, lazy and slow, fat and gouty"7 was called to rule France. He had the good sense to leave alone the Napoleonic Code, the judiciary and the structure of the economy, but he soon sided with the Church, which was demanding that all ecclesiastical property confiscated during the Revolution should be returned. Meanwhile the Congress of Vienna had stripped France of her recent territorial expansions, with both Prussia and Austria gaining much land and power.

On the island of Elba, Napoleon, with 400 of his old Imperial Guard and 800 volunteer grenadiers, continued to receive information about discontent in the French army, the fears of the peasantry about losing their land, the enforcement of Catholic worship and the continued Jacobin activity. On February 26, 1815 he loaded his men on 6 ships and sailed for the south shore of France. By March 20th he entered Paris again, never having fired a shot and having gained additional troops all along the long journey. Even General Michael Ney, sent by King Louis XVIII with 6,000 troops to stop Bonaparte, reversed his loyalties, turned and joined Napoleon's march and was with him as he resumed the exercise of power as Emperor of France. Ney was later to face a firing squad for this action.

But Napoleon's foreign enemies were now more firmly united against him than ever and their armies pressed in on him from all sides, even as he found that France was not truly all united behind him. The most immediate external danger was from Belgium, where Marchal Blucher had a Prussian army of 120,000 and the British Duke of Wellington had an army of British, Dutch, Belgium and German recruits totaling 93,000. In the hope of challenging these foes one at a time, Napoleon crossed into Belgium with 126,000 men. There were many battles on the flanks and the center, but the decisive defeat at Waterloo ended Napoleon's dreams, even as urinary tract stones and-gastric cancer were already beginning to end his life. One hundred days after his resumption of rule he again abdicated under force and was banished to St. Helena, 1,200 miles off the coast of Africa. There he lived, still surrounded by many of his faithful aides, reading many hours a day from some 400 books (70 by Voltaire) and eventually dictating his memoirs, until his death supposedly from cancer on May 5, 1821, at the age of 51 years. Recently one researcher has written that he believes he has positive evidence that Napoleon died of chronic arsenic poisoning8, administered by Charles Tristan de Montholon, a count of the French aristocracy. (Ref. 57) In answer, however, the editors of "Science" (Ref. 58) have denied this, with "proof" that any arsenic present in the hair of Napoleon came from the green wallpaper of that time and that non-fatal doses of antimony used in medicines could also have given false readings of arsenic in the previous tests.

Overall, the French Revolution led not to popular and republican government, but to military dictatorship, followed by monarchial restoration. It did not result in universal suffrage. Property was necessary and in 1815 only 1% to 3% of the population was qualified to vote. Even as late as 1846 the total French electorate was estimated at 241,000 or 2.8% of the total male population over 21 years of age. Yet much was accomplished in that there was wholesale cancellation of seigneurial rights and f airly extensive dispersal of land ownership through conf iscation and sale of church and noble properties, making 19th century France a nation of peasant farmers. Out of 12,000,000 families in the nation, perhaps 200 to 300 could be called opulent. (Ref. 60) But the canny peasants, unwilling to divide their land among large numbers of children according to the Napoleonic Code, restricted the size of their families. The resulting slow population increase inhibited a really rapid rate of industrialization so that even at the end of the century industry was still relatively small. A fundamental French weakness was the dependence on costly overland transport. A great effect of the war years was to choke off the Atlantic face of France and build up the Rhine-Rhone valleys' industries. (Ref. 61) The government did overcome the old church condemnation of interest with an 1807 law which fixed the interest rate at 5% on loans and 6% on commercial paper, while anything above that was considered usury. (Ref. 62) There were a few industrial advancements. Having been cut off from imported sugar by the British counter-blockade early in the century, by 1840 France had built 58 sugar-beet factories. The population control was helped in 1830 when cholera killed 1,000 people a day. After that the population of Paris did increase rapidly, however, from 1,242,000 in 1851 to 2,212,000 in 1872. Alfred Sauvy, French sociologist, calculated that between 1810 and 1900 the purchasing power of the average worker in that nation increased by 80%. Napoleon's administrative reforms in the Code Civil contained 2,281 articles and countless amendments and still constitute the basic French legal text.

Second only to Napoleon in interest and influence in Europe in this century was Charles Maurice de Talleyrand-Perigord. Born with a clubfoot, he over-compensated in his young adult days by becoming both a bishop in the Roman Catholic Church and at the same time a gambling, wenching, rogue. As one of the leaders of the Revolution, he had written a good part of its Declaration of the Rights of Man, but by 1794 even he had to escape the "Terror" by going to America. Back in Paris as foreign minister in 1796, he had soon insulted an American delegation and accumulated an enormous private fortune from the bribes of various other foreign delegations and from "percentages" of such transactions as the Louisiana Purchase, which he helped to negotiate for Napoleon. In 1808, however, when Napoleon kidnapped the Spanish royal family so that his brother Joseph could have the throne and then made Talleyrand the family's jailer, in effect, the aristocratic French- man suddenly turned from faithful servant to the emperor's foe. He started correspondence with the Russian czar, setting in motion the alliances which eventually led to Napoleon's downfall. When the little emperor was out of power in 1816, a new provisional government, headed by Talleyrand, called a Bourbon king back to power and extracted France from its damaging wars. Throughout all that time, that indefatigable man continued his elegant living - fulfilling his desires with multiple women, young and old. It is said that the painter Eugene Delacroix was his natural son. After the Revolution of 1830, Talleyrand survived and remained in favor with the victorious Duke of Orleans. He served as ambassador to England from 1830-34, helping to avert another general European War. Just before his death in 1838, he signed an agreement with Rome, repenting his multiple sins and re-entering the folds of the Catholic Church. (Ref. 63)

The end of the Napoleonic era did not terminate internal strife in France. The successor of Louis XVIII, Charles XI, an ultra-royalist, was overthrown by revolution in 1830 to be replaced by Louis Philippe, who reigned only until 1848 when he too was disposed of by revolt. Actually these "revolutions" were in reality only Paris disorders, which in some other countries could have been kept under manageable proportions by political processes, but not in France. After Louis Philippe, the Second Republic was proclaimed and Louis Napoleon, nephew of Bonaparte, was elected president. He immediately made himself dictator and emperor, so that the Second Empire was thus launched in 1852. As Napoleon III, he tried to follow in his uncle's footsteps, but had not the ability. He wanted a strong Prussia, a powerful Sardinia-Piedmont, with an Italian Federation, which he hoped would be favorable to France. As Napoleon I had sold Louisiana to the United States in 1803 when he desperately needed money, so Napoleon 111 decided on a new venture in America by sending French troops into Mexico to make the Archduke Maximilian of Austria Emperor of Mexico. But the French troops were always somewhat anxious there and when the United States emphasized the Monroe Doctrine after its Civil War, Napoleon III abandoned Maximilian to his fate at the hands of the Mexicans. The second French emperor, himself, ended his career as a prisoner of the Germans in the Franco-German War of 1870, in which France lost Alsace9, a part of Lorraine and had to pay heavy indemnities. After a period of German occupation of Paris and another civil war, a stable French government was finally established as the Third Republic in 1871. Adolphe Thiers headed the provisional Commune of Paris and by 1873 Marshal MacMahon, a royalist sympathizer, was elected president.

French imperialism in Africa and the Far East followed, perhaps as an antidote for the loss of Alsace and Lorraine. The French also had a persistent dream of overturning British naval supremacy. Before the War of 1870 they had developed a good start with the development of their mobile, high f ire-power gun and torpedo boats, but then they had to turn their money and energies to the land war with Germany. In 1887 Gustave Zede designed the first practical submarine, although the periscope, which allowed the aiming of torpedoes while submerged, was not developed until after the turn of the century.

In 1893 Schneider-Creusot introduced the famous French 75 millimeter field gun, which revolutionized artillery design. Russia, as France's ally of the moment, purchased many of those guns. (Ref. 65, 66, 67, 68, 69, 70, 71)

In this century Louis Pasteur made great discoveries in chemistry, biology and medicine and Francois Magendie and his pupil Claude Bernard made great advances in human physiology. Charles Brown-Sequard is sometimes considered the founder of endocrinology and Rene' Laennec, working early in the century is considered one of the great clinicians of all time, best remembered for his invention of the stethoscope. But still French medicine was crude in many ways. Blood letting was still a major treatment, but rather than opening veins, the French started using leeches, importing over 40,000,000 of them in a single year.

This practice was continued until late in the century. The principle of canning with heat was developed by Nicholas Appert in 1810. Francois Arago (and Humphrey Davy, independently) discovered that an electric current could be made to magnetize iron. (Ref. 72, 73, 74) Work was done in mathematics by Lagrange and Legendre and in histology by Bichat.

THE NETHERLANDS AND BELGIUM

Napoleon's take-over of Belgium caused Britain to enter the war against him and we have seen above how the final battles and French defeat occurred on Belgian soil. At the termination of the initial Napoleonic Wars, the Congress of Vienna created the Kingdom of the Netherlands and gave William of Holland the Austrian Netherlands as compensation for some Dutch colonial losses. Since this was the first time that the northern and southern parts of the Netherlands had been united since the 1 6th century, there were now many differences in religion and in the economics of the two sections. The Belgians felt themselves conquered subjects rather than equals and as part of a July revolution in Paris in 1830, the Belgians rose up in Brussels and by October had declared their independence from King William and had separated themselves from the Dutch and the Dutch language. But there were still two peoples and two languages in the liberated Belgium.

56% of the people were Flemings in the north, while 32% were Walloons, speaking French in the south. They elected Leopold as a Belgian king. By 1850 their railroad network was virtually complete and by the last of the century there was mechanized industry in a great part of Belgium, spreading out from the Walloon district. Mechanization, however, ruined the old artisan trade of making guns by hand at Liege, so that city shrank in world importance. (Ref. 75, 76, 77, 78, 79)

BRITISH ISLES

All four of the countries of the British Isles were now united under the government of Great Britain. The nation went to war with Napoleon when France took Belgium and Admiral Nelson won a great victory over the French fleet at Trafalgar in 1805. As we have previously noted, when Napoleon had control of the continent he established a port and coast blockade to exclude British goods and this was so effective that England came close to starvation in the years 1810 and 1811. Within half a century, however, with the help of great British seamen, the nation overcame that to build a powerful and civilizing empire, in spite of the fact that at the same time their King George III had become completely insane. The English, although socially and economically divided into classes, were in another sense surprisingly homogenous. They were almost all Protestant, with only some 60,000 Catholics (chief Iy of Irish origin) and some 26,000 Jews, almost all of whom lived in London and who were still without civil liberties. Nevertheless, it was the Jewish banker, Nathan Rothschild who established a branch bank in London in 1810 and transmitted the subsidies from England to Austria and Prussia that enabled them to fight and def eat Napoleon. Thereafter he played a leading role in the industrial and commercial expansion of England.

Actually England recovered from Napoleon's blockaded ports by establishing a naval blockade of her own and carried it to the extent of searching neutral ships, a feature which led to the War of 1812 with the United States10. At the peak of mobilization in 1814, some 500,000 men, representing 4% of the active work force of Britain, were in the armed services. Just as in France, this helped the unemployment situation. After the Congress of Vienna had restored a balance of power in Europe, however, England was left loaded with debt and an economic depression which threatened revolution at the time that William IV came to the throne in 1830. He helped to pass the Reform Bill, which gave a vote to the middle classes and enlarged the House of Commons. In the last of the century England recovered in all ways, economically and politically in particular, helped in large part by the great ministers - Sir Robert Peel, Benjamin Disraeli and William F. Gladstone. For nearly 20 years the last two alternated as prime minister and no one disputed their leadership under the great Queen Victoria. A number of far reaching social changes occurred, such as the enfranchisement of urban working men in 1867, the secret ballot in 1872 and a nearly universal male suffrage in 1884.

After 1870, European alignments began to shape up in preparation for the great World War of 1912. In England, Gladstone was pursuing a foreign policy later carried on by Disraeli, which was designed to antagonize the European continent. In the last decade of the century even the British public was made aware that the country was being flooded with German goods and by 1900 the armaments race made it obvious that the real threat lay in Berlin. Britain had occupied Egyptian soil in 1882 and the unseated French retaliated by concluding an alliance with Russia, which was already growing rapidly, with French investment capital. After Britain was firmly established in the Mediterranean (she also occupied Cyprus in 1877) the old need to prop up Turkey was gone and that country was left open for German penetration. In the Boer War of 1899-1902 Britain gained additional territory in South Africa.

In spite of the apparent political advancements in this century, the common people of Britain had many problems. Education in England was poor, overall, with an estimated 2,000,000 children in England and Wales receiving no education at all in 1806. Women were used to carry coal up from the mines as much as 100 feet. In Scotland the coal and salt miners were still legally serfs, bound to the mines for life and even wearing collars as visible signs of their slavery. (Ref. 80) Other strange things were occurring in that far northern country. With the idea of clearing the inland valleys for the raising of sheep, the inhabitants of those areas were forcibly evicted and sent to the coast where they were supposed to work in fisheries, but the latter had not yet been built. There was much brutality among the frightened and weeping people and a few died. The fisheries were never very successful and again many people left for Canada. A large number of impoverished highlanders joined the British army. There were frequent famines, with the worst following the potato blight in 1846. There were also epidemics of cholera and food riots. Eventually economic recovery and the Industrial Revolution arrived in Scotland with the establishment of new coke-fired blast furnaces in some of the desolate regions of the country. The short-barreled, extra large gun used on Nelson's ships at Trafalgar, the "carronade", was named for the Carron works in Scotland. (Ref. 81, 82)

By 1810 still some 3/4 of the agricultural laborers in Great Britain were illiterate, but then there were more people working in trade, manufacturing and handicrafts than on the farms. In 1812 there was an insurrection in Yorkshire over the cotton loom. Thomas (Ref. 83) says that if the government had taken labor's side there would have been no Industrial Revolution. It was not until 1870 that a national system of elementary schools, separate from the church, was established in England, although Scotland had initiated this earlier. In general the British commoners were still quite coarse in their daily living. Even in 1820 the sewers in London were inferior to those of Rome in the first century of the Christian era. As late as 1897 sailors in the British navy were forbidden to use knives and forks, as this was felt to be unmanly and apt to compromise discipline.

Great Britain, France and Germany all faced agricultural crises in this century. Railroads, steamships and refrigeration had made it possible for the vast new areas in Russia, North America, and Australia to sell their grain and meat in European markets at relatively low prices and the economy became displaced. In Britain, the fall of wheat and meat prices speeded the break-up of rural society and undermined the economic foundations of the landed oligarchy. A disastrous cattle epidemic between 1863 and 1867 added to the agricultural problems so that initially local meat prices soared and imports rose from 16,000 pounds in 1866 to 22,000,000 pounds by 1871. Later the manufacture of ice led to the fish and chips industry. Between 1870 and 1900 land devoted to grain diminished by 1/4 as dairy farming, fruits and vegetables became more common. But even in 1890 83% of children had no solid food except bread and all people tended to get scurvy, rickets and tuberculosis.

As we noted in the last chapter, modern industrialism began in England and involved coal and iron, with a technology which f lowered about the midpoint of this 1 9th century. 30,000,000 tons of coal were mined in 1840 and by 1850 Great Britain owned more net tons of commercial shipping than France, the United States and the German states all put together. The importance of military procurement in the promotion of the Industrial Revolution is of ten overlooked. Mass production of small-arms and a decisive stimulus to new techniques in artillery were by-products of the Crimean War, in which deficiencies of the British and French forces became the source of public scorn. A further byproduct was the discovery of the Bessemer process for making steel, as Henry Bessemer experimented with artillery design11 (Ref. 84) In 1870 Britain already produced more steel than the combined output of France and Germany and then, using the Bessemer converter and the Gilchrist-Thomas steel process, England boosted the world output from 540,000 tons in 1870 to 14,600,000 tons in 1895. The British population grew by 10 million in this century. In the 59 years up to 1815 the nation had been at war (chiefly with France) for 37 years and in the year 1814 had 1,062,000 men under arms out of a total of 12,000,000 on the islands and yet the industrial changes went on. A certain looseness in the texture of British society perhaps stimulated inventiveness and the strains of war, changes in overseas trading patterns and fluctuations in the supply of money and the price levels may all have contributed to weakening traditional resistances to economic changes. From the first Liverpool-to-Manchester Railway in 1830, a modern railroad system was completed by 1870. By that time Britain had 60% of the world's steam tonnage on the seas, but there was still more tonnage registered under sail than steam. (Ref. 85)

Late in the century British captains of industry tended to rest on their laurels and the new generation became attracted to the cultivated life of a leisure class. There was also a definite and deliberate lack of interest among the industrialists in any pure science and research. Although the aniline dye industry was started in Britain it was soon taken over by the German chemists in the 1860s. Still another liability was a law against the modern joint-stock companies, on the books until 1855, and the prohibition of limited liability until 1855. Still another British government decision had world-wide consequences. In 1864 the production of all artillery for the British services was entrusted to the Woolwich arsenal. Other firms, including the large Armstrong armament manufacturer, were forced to rely on foreign sales and this soon resulted in some danger to British security. Armstrong built a cruiser for Chile in 1882 that could outrun all existing capital ships, while still maintaining excellent firepower12. Such cruisers in foreign hands, plus the new French concentrations on relatively inexpensive gun-boats and fast torpedo boats, all tended to nullify Britain's naval preeminence and put her trans-Atlantic supply lines in jeopardy. It was about 1886 before the government realized that William Armstrong's private plants would have to be used for naval armaments and ships to keep England abreast of the rest of the European world. Under a bill passed in 1889 the Royal Navy received even greater appropriations than it had requested and new ships were built using nickel steel armor and full steam propulsion. Older ships were re-built and masts removed. Significant changes in production and technology of land armaments did not occur until the time of the Boer War in 1899. (Ref. 87)

In spite of industry's lack of interest, some pure science achievements were made in this period. John Dalton revolutionized theoretical chemistry with his Atomic Theory, as early as 1804. Humphrey Davy used electrolysis to discover and isolate sodium, potassium, barium, boron, strontium, calcium and magnesium and he demonstrated the potentials of producing both heat and light from electric current. There was public electric lighting in London in the 1880s. In other fields, there were researches on the nervous system and brain by Charles Bell and Lister first used antiseptic surgery in 1865, along with some anesthesia. Simpson of Edinburgh had used chloroform as early as 1847. As late as 1854 there were still 14,000 cholera victims with 618 deaths in London, even though the city had such great clinicians as Astley Cooper, Richard Bright, Thomas Addison and Thomas Hodgkin, all of whom have had diseases named after them and all of whom worked at the famous Guy's Hospital and Medical School. Noteworthy surgeons of the era were Benjamin Brodie and James Paget. Dental caries was rampant, apparently secondary to excess use of sugar and cheap, canned milk.

Early 19th century philosophy was little influenced by science but spawned some famous doubters such as Tom Paine, who wrote on the fallacies of the Christian legend; William Godwin, who felt that morality is nothing but a calculation of consequences and Malthus, who foretold the starvation of man resulting from his fertility. Britain led the world in literature. It was the time of the prolific novelist, Sir Walter Scott of Scotland, born in the preceding century, who wrote such favorites as The Lady of the Lake and Waverly. In England proper, women led among the novelists, with Jane Austen, Ann Radcliffe, unhappy Frances Burney and Maria Edgeworth, but the men dominated poetry. In the Lake District of northwest England, early in the century, there lived three of England's great poets - William Wadsworth, Samuel Taylor Coleridge and the worst poet but the greatest gentlemen. Robert Southey. And then there were the "rebel poets" - Byron and Shelley - friends, philanderers, travelers and geniuses. Lord George Gordon Byron of noble heritage was born with a right club-foot, but this did not prevent him from living and loving extravagantly, in and out of marriage and in and out of many European countries. He died in Greece in 1824 as the leader of a squad of 600 Suliotes (part Greek, part Albanian barbarians) in the Greek Revolution. His partner in much of his sin and fun, Percy Bysshe Shelley, also of lesser nobility parents, was expelled from Oxford for favoring atheism and then became a renegade poet and lover, joining Byron in Switzerland and later in Italy. Not yet 30 years of age, he suffered a nervous breakdown, contemplated suicide and then was drowned off the coast of Italy in a storm and shipwreck in 1822. He had just written his last poem, entitled "The Triumph of Life". Last but not least of the poets was John Keats, who died of acute tuberculosis at the early age of 26 years.

Charles Darwin's Origin of Species in mid-century precipitated a whole series of profound re-evaluations in philosophy and social thought as well as another crisis in religious circles. His work, however, was only the end result of many previous studies. For example, Charles Lyell's Principles of Geology, published in 1830, had emphasized the theory of uniformitarianism, that geological history was one of slow, uniform orderly development brought about by accumulation of constant, small changes. This was at odds with the Biblical creation. Darwin, himself, refrained from attacking the Bible, but others, like his friend and publicist, Thomas Huxley, were not so reticent. Darwinism was even used as an endorsement of industrial capitalism and laissez-f aire and conversely on the continent, particularly, as a racist-militarist endorsement that "the strong must rule". (Ref. [for all of ENGLAND] 89, 90, 91, 92, 93, 94, 95)

Ireland deserves an additional paragraph or two in the tale of this century. After the Act of Union of 1800, which joined Ireland to England, Daniel O'Connell had won the right for Catholics to sit in Parliament and hold office, by 1829. Then he immediately began to agitate for repeal of the Union, to free Ireland again. By the 1840s Ireland's population had reached 8,500,000 (almost 3 times its 1973 level) and 4,000,000 of those people lived almost entirely on potatoes. The American potato had been introduced in the 1580s and the Irish had become very dependent on that food. When a parasitic fungus initiated the great potato blight in 1845, there were soon not only no potatoes to eat but none for seed for the next season and livestock had to be slaughtered, because they were also without food. Hunger was soon accompanied by scurvy (because no vitamin C) and then failing eyesight, acute nervous debilities and sometimes even dementia, apparently from the lack of vitamins A and B7, which had previously been obtained from milk. There was a tremendous emigration of the Irish, some to England, but most to the United States, so that by 1851 some 250,000 were arriving at Ellis Island each year. The famine only increased Irish bitterness with England and in the 1860s and 70s there was new agitation for independence, fanned by the Fenians, who acted secretly and violently. In opposition to that extremism, Charles Stewart Parnell- fought in Parliament for simple autonomy in internal matters. Some land reforms were obtained through the help of Gladstone, but to the English the idea of real separation was unthinkable.

Simultaneous with the great medical tradition that developed in Paris in the first half of the century, a clinical investigation center arose in Dublin at Meath Hospital. Three men in particular should be named and, although trained in Scotland, they became famous as the "Irish School". They were John Cheyne, William Stokes13, and perhaps the most famous of all, Robert James Graves, known for his description of toxic goiter (Graves' Disease) and his bedside teaching. Abraham Colles and Robert William Smith described the mechanics and treatment of various wrist fractures and the latter wrote about neurofibromatosis before Von Recklinghausen described it in 1882, even though the disease bears the latter's name. (Ref. 96, 97, 98, 99, 100)

SCANDINAVIA

Two completely unrelated facts about Scandinavia, as a whole, are mentioned here. First it should be noted that the Lapps, living across the north of all Scandinavia, are the sole European survivors of the old Arctic reindeer hunting cultures. They call themselves "Saami" and they pursue fishing, whaling and limited farming in some areas where there is a warming influence from the Gulf Stream system. They travel on skis, following the migrating reindeer herds. There are North, South and East Lappish people, each distinguished by the types of hats they wear. (Ref. 101) The second factor of note is that by mid-century there were railroad lines in all Scandinavian countries. (Ref. 102)

NORWAY

At the close of the Napoleonic Wars, Great Britain forced Denmark to cede Norway to Sweden, but the Norwegians ref used to accept the Treaty of Kiel, proclaimed themselves an independent nation, adopted a constitution and elected the former Danish governor, Christian Frederick, as their king. May 17, 1814 became their Independence Day. The Swedes retaliated with warfare, but in 2 weeks a settlement was made, with the king of Sweden becoming also the king of Norway, but respecting the Norwegian constitution and giving, in effect, an autonomous government. The first king of the two countries under that arrangement was Karl Johann (Charles John) Bernadotte. In 1884 true parliamentary government came into effect, although there was still much mutual irritation with Sweden. Near the end of the century, with industries and shipping growing, the desire for complete independence again became very strong and just after the turn of the century (1905) the parliament deposed the Swedish king and elected again a Danish prince to rule them as Haakon VII. Some Norwegian merchants became rich using ice for a fresh-fish industry, which replaced the old salted herring. This was the period of Henrik Ibsen, one of Norway's literary greats. (Ref. 103, 104, 105)

SWEDEN

In the reign of Gustavus IV (1792-1809) Sweden joined the Third Coalition against France, thus giving Napoleon an excuse for seizing Pomerania and Stralsund, which were Sweden's last possessions on the mainland. (Ref. 106) Then in 1808 a Russian army crossed the Gulf of Bothnia on the ice and eventually compelled Sweden to cede Finland. The Riksdag deposed Gustavus IV and chose the king's old uncle, Karl (Charles) XIII to rule. Some radicals, feeling that new blood was needed in the royal house, then supplied the childless Karl XIII with an adopted crown prince, one Jean-Baptiste Bernadotte, formerly one of Napoleon's marshals. As a concession from Napoleon, it was agreed that Norway should be associated with Sweden under the Bernadotte rule. We have seen above that Norway resisted this arrangement. In 1810 Bernadotte, whose wife was once Napoleon's fiancé and was a sister-in-law to Joseph Bonaparte, became Crown Prince, changing his name to Karl Johann (Charles John). Upon the old king's death in 1818 Bernadotte then became King Karl (Charles) XIV, Johann. In the interim he had had time to renounce his old emperor, join with Russia and Prussia, lead a Swedish army back on to the continent and help in the final battles against Napoleon. Five Bernadotte kings followed, all notably able, healthy and democratic. During the century the Riksdag became a two-chamber congress, industry developed and the middle and working classes became more important.

Education, science and literature advanced rapidly in Sweden. The universities of Uppsala, Abo and Lund were among the best in Europe. Jons Jakob Berzelius was one of the founders of modern chemistry, developing a table of atomic weights far more accurate than Dalton's and isolating many chemical e-lements for the first time. Alfred Nobel perfected nitroglycerine and dynamite. Poets abounded, with perhaps the most famous being Esaias Tegner, who wrote the "Frithjofs Saga", a series of legends taken from an old Norse cycle of lays. By 1888 there were 21 translations into English and 19 into German. (Ref. 107)

DENMARK

At the close of the last century in August of 1800, Denmark had joined Russia. Prussia and Sweden in the Second League of Armed Neutrality, pledged to resist British search of neutral vessels. Fearing that the combined naval power of those nations might put an end to her mastery of the seas, Britain decided that one of those fleets had to be destroyed. Denmark's, being close at hand, was chosen and attacked in a vicious sea battle off Copenhagen and most of the Danish ships were disabled or sunk. But Denmark survived and attempted to continue neutral for another 6 years, while she rebuilt her seagoing fleet. In 1807 Britain demanded the use of the entire Danish navy to use against the French and when the Danes ref used war broke out again. General Wellesley (Duke of Wellington) landed 30,000 English troops on Zealand and after bombarding Copenhagen he finally seized the naval harbor and all ships in it. This forced the angry Danish Crown Prince Frederick VII to join up with Napoleon and his country was sucked up in the European whirlpool, once again ending up on the losing side.

In the middle of the century, a number of citizens went to the king and demanded a free constitution and got it. But in both Schleswig and Holstein there were many German people who wanted German rather than Danish rule and the Danish king soon had to go to war against the Holstein rebels, with the unfortunate result that that drew Bismarck into the scene and those provinces were soon lost to Germany (1866). We have detailed above the loss of Norway early in the century, but the old Norwegian dependencies of Greenland, Iceland, the Faroe and Virgin Islands were kept by Denmark.

Between wars the Danes made significant contributions to science, literature and art. Hans Christian Oersted (1777-1851) founded the science of electromagnetism through 38 years of experimentation. Bertel Thorwaldsen (1770-1844) was one of the two greatest sculptors of Europe of his time. After a Dane invented an improved cream separator, Denmark developed a large butter industry to go along with bacon production. (Ref. 108, 109, 110)

FINLAND

Finland proper now began to have a denser congregation of true Finns, displacing a sparse and probably related Lapp population. Russia took control of the land in 1809 with a sudden, surprise defeat of the Swedish forces. The Diet was abolished and there was severe oppression by the conquerors. Late in the century, however, when Czar Nicholas II wanted to blend the Finns into the Russian Empire, a struggle resulted and led to a revolution just after the turn of the century in 1905. Actually in essence this was a great national strike that has seldom been equaled anywhere. It did force some changes and a new one-chamber Diet was formed with some political advancements such as freedom of the press and universal suffrage. The Finns did not obtain their final independence until the Boleshevik Revolution in Russia in 1917.

The establishment of the modern Finnish language is credited to Johan Snellman (1806- 1881). Carl Ludwig Engel (1778-1840) was the architect of the great square of Helsinki. Jean Sibelius (1875-1957) began his symphony work as the century closed. (Ref. 111, 112)

EASTERN EUROPE

Even as today, in the l9th century most of east Europe belonged politically to Russia, although there were multiple language groups such as Finnish, Estonian, Latvian, Polish and some Swedish and German along the coast, while Great Russian, White Russian and Ukrainian were separate language groups farther east. Agricultural yields throughout eastern Europe remained low and, in fact, had changed little from the 16th century. There was no significant rural surplus and therefore no really prosperous towns. The dread cholera, coming out of Bengal in 1826, reached south Russia, then Poland and the Baltic by 1830, before going on to Western Europe. (Ref. 113, 114, 115)

SOUTHERN BALTIC AREA

The southern shore of the Baltic remained throughout this period basically divided between Russia and Germany. Poland remained dispersed within the three great empires of Europe, but life went on. The world's first sugar-beet factory was built in Silesia in 1801. Some quivers of hope appeared when Napoleon marched into Warsaw at the end of 1806 and the people at first felt that he was a savior and about to free their country. The Russian troops had fallen back to their own border after several battles with the French, but Poland did not survive the Vienna Congress. Once again the Poles revolted in 1830 and declared their independence in Warsaw in 1831, but Czar Nicholas' army quickly crushed them in the battle of Ostroleka, each side suffering some 6,000 casualties. Under Nicholas' orders an internal campaign attempted to eliminate all traces of dissidence. Polish universities were suppressed and the Polish army disbanded. Prussia gave Russia moral support in these activities. (Ref. 116, 117, 118)

Nicholas' successor, Alexander II, at first tried some reconciliation, allowing exiles to return, the Catholic Church to function and created a new Warsaw University. But those attempts at reform did not placate the Polish people and religious ceremonies were used as political demonstrations. When an attempt was made to conscript dissident Polish youths into the Russian army, hundreds of young men fled to to the forests and in January, 1863 a revolutionary committee called for an insurrection. It began with an attack on a Russian soldiers' barracks and the Poles were actually joined by White Russians and some Ukrainians who wanted agrarian reform. But the political and social diversity involved allowed General Muraviev and Field Marshal Paskenvich to put peasant against landlord and in spite of two years of guerilla warfare against the Russian army, then the largest in Europe, the Poles lost again. There followed wholesale executions, confiscations and deportations. Subsequently Poland became the most industrialized province of the Russian Empire, producing large amounts of textiles, coal and iron. In the last third of the century, the Russian imprint on Poland became ever more evident. (Ref. 119)

RUSSIA

Czar Alexander I (1801-1825), although implicated in the murder of his father Paul, started rule with a true humanitarian ideology and a desire to liberate his serfs and establish a constitutional government, but the mechanics of that were difficult and blocked by his ministers and senate. Before anything could be initiated, he became entangled in European politics and diplomacy, first as an all y of France and then as an enemy. As Napoleon invaded Poland, Russia retreated but then hostilities ceased temporarily with the Treaty of Tilsit, where there was much exchange of territory and Russia gained Finland from Sweden. Of course, the Russian army in Finland had helped to promote that. Napoleon sought to keep Russia happy and thus free his hand in the west against England. But apparently changing his mind by June, 1812, Napoleon again started for Russia with 600,000 men. As we have noted in an earlier section, Bonaparte's army reached an evacuated Moscow, started to freeze and starve and finally retreated. The Russians cut them down until only 1/5 of the French army remained alive. McNeill (279) surmises that the Russian troops were supplied by barge and river boats in summer and sleighs in winter, allowing great weights to be moved easily and relatively rapidly, in contrast to the French land carts. It has been estimated that there were about 400,000 burlake, or hauliers, who pulled or propelled boats along the Volga in about 1815. (Ref. 120) Czar Alexander I followed his troops into central Europe and then Paris, as Napoleon abdicated. The czar was then influential in the final peace at Vienna and the subsequent formation of the Holy Alliance of European monarchs.

Under Czar Nicholas I (1825-55) Russia aggressively added Persian Armenia to its empire and tried to take over the Balkans, but was thwarted there by the British. The great Russian army was used during Nicholas' reign on many diverse fronts; in central Asia (1839-43 and 1847-53); in the Caucasus (1829-64); against Persia and Turkey (1826-29); against Polish rebels 1830-311 and 1863); and against Magyar revolts in 1849. It is of interest that as early as the 1830s the astute Alexis de Tocqueville (Ref. 121) recognized that even then the two greatest nations in the world were Russia and the United States, although the former centered all the authority of society in a single arm while the latter relied on the strength and common sense of the people. The population of Russia increased proportionately more rapidly in the early century than any other country in the world.

Britain felt that Turkey must be kept independent of Russia and in 1841 an International Straits Convention closed the Bosphorus to Russian warships. In spite of that, in 1851 Russians invaded Turkey's Danubian provinces and in 1853 sank the Turkish fleet, gaining control of the Black Sea. In reprisal, France and Britain declared war on Russia in 1854 and invaded the Crimea. In this Crimean War the greatest battle took place at Sevastopol, where Russia sank her antiquated navy to block the bay, putting the ships' guns on the shore. But the western powers finally took the great naval base, anyway, humiliating Russia. Long supply lines14, poor administration, and obsolete ammunition, along with typhus fever and other diseases contributed to the eventual f all of the Russians, although the strategy of the British had also been appalling. This war ended the dominant role of Russia in southeast Europe. The scandalous condition of the troops and the dead, sick and wounded of both sides, as depicted by the first war correspondents, led to the work of Florence Nightingale and this was perhaps the most positive result of the war. (Ref. 122) The Peace of Paris of 1856 let Sevastopol stay in Russian hands, but the mouth of the Danube became international and Russia was barred from having a Black Sea navy. The treaty was a futile effort to settle the "Near Eastern Question". During the same period, Russia attempted periodically to take the Caucasus and was opposed with great fanaticism by the Islamic leader Shamil. Nevertheless, that area was under complete Russian control by 1864.

Some of the reforms which had been attempted by Czar Alexander I were actually accomplished by Alexander II as he emancipated the serfs and established councils for local self-government in the years after 1855. He refused a national constitution, however, and retained absolute rule, so that while the serfs were freed from the authority of the gentry, that authority was simply transferred to the local commune or "mir", which in turn distributed the land and levied taxes. The Act of Emancipation also divided the nation into two great classes: (1) gentry and urban classes, and (2) peasantry. In 1864 there was decreed a Local Government Law or "Zemstvo" under which each province and each country was authorized to elect its own assembly. This promoted better education and public health and through other provisions there was established trial by jury with an ordinary system of defense and prosecution. Still, many revolutionary ideas developed in many groups and many sectors in the 1860s and between then and the end of the century over 500,000 people emigrated to Siberia. The Nenets, living along the tree-line and north of the Arctic circle were under the czar's jurisdiction and in 1870 he moved many of them to Novaya Zemlya to end Norway's claim to that island. (Ref. 124) Anti-semitism was stronger in Russia than in Germany. Baltic Germans were responsible for much of this in the Nazi party of the 20th century. (Ref. 125)

Chernyshevsky preached materialism and intellectualism, stating that man's creative thinking was superior to any spiritual power from above. He was also a socialist. Pisarev wrote about nihilism, with an intellectual attitude of extreme individualism. Karakozov promoted the philosophy of terror and prophesised that all of Europe, including Russia, would soon be in the flames of revolution. He was executed in 1866. Nechaev formed a society called "The Peoples' Justice" and sowed the seeds of anarchism. In P. Tkachev one finds the forerunner of Bolshevism with such statements as: "The Russian Revolution, like any other revolution cannot escape hanging and shooting gendarmes, public prosecutors, ministers, merchants and priests."15 He said that the goal was a new social order and that in the original state the revolution might assume the form of a dictatorship of a minority, but representing in essence the will of the people. Plekhanov founded the Land Freedom Party, later split into the Populists and the Terrorists.

In 1877 Russia again tried to intervene in the Balkan revolutions, but once more backed down as the great powers of Western Europe complained and in the resulting Congress of Berlin of 1878 all non-independent areas in the Balkans were given either to Austria or back to Turkey. After an attempt on the life of Czar Alexander II in 1880, Loris Melikov was appointed virtual dictator to combat revolution and develop means of stopping revolts. A type of constitution was devised, but before it became effective Alexander was killed by a terrorist bomb.

Alexander III began his reign as czar in 1881 and died in 1894, but lived long enough to resume some diplomatic relations with Europe, while economic and social problems increased at home. Matters were not helped by a famine in 1891. Nevertheless, there was continued relentless expansion into central Asia, with the British becoming alarmed regarding their claims in India. A great industrial region developed where the Don River empties into the Sea of Azov around the Donets coalfield. A railroad connecting that area to the iron-ore fields of Drivoy Rog to the west helped industrialization. As in the United States, the railroads were fundamental in creating a modern nation. (Ref. 127)

After 1870 the steel industry grew 500 times faster than in any other country. Swedish entrepreneurs found oil near the Caspian Sea about 1860 and by 1900 some 10 million tons of oil a year were produced, about half of that of the world. Although carried out by foreigners, such industrialization was inspired by the state. Marx, who knew little about Russia, did not realize that the chief political problem was one of nationalities. Russia, in 1900, had 120,000,000 people dominated by 56,000,000 Greater Russians, with 22,000,000 Ukrainians and then varying numbers of White Russians, Poles, Jews, Tartars, Lithuanians, Letts, Germans, Armenians, Estonians, Finns, Bashkins, Georgians and Circassians. (Ref. 128)

Russian literature was dominated by Alexander Pushkin and Fedor Dostoevsky, who anticipated much of the 20th century. Russian scientists excelled in many fields. In mathematics Lobachevsky developed a non-Euclidean geometry and Sophia Kovalevskava did much work with calculus, although she was foreign educated and did much of her work in Sweden. In biology I.I. Mechnikov was a co-worker of Pasteur and Kovalevsky founded comparative embryology and experimental histology. In chemistry D.I. Mendeleyev became world famous for his Periodic Table of the Elements. Physiologists included the well known Ivan Pavlov, who worked with digestive glands and conditioned reflexes and Timiryazev, who found the role and significance of chlorophyll. A.S. Popov was a pioneer in electromagnetic waves and predicted the development of radio. Tsiolkovsky, who was the father of jet-propulsion and cosmic rocketry did his work at the end of this century, although it was not published until early in the 20th. After 1864 local governmental organizations, the "Zemstrovs" were responsible for medical service to the poor and mentally ill, acting through the "feldshav", a combined male nurse and pharmacist. Regular physicians were trained in the large universities. (Ref. 129, 130, 131, 132).

1 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

2 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

3 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

4 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

5 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

6 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

7 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

8 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

9 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

10 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

11 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

12 [206] STILLMAN EDMUND ANDEDITORS OF LIFE, The Balkans. (Time, Inc., New York, 1964).

13 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

14 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

15 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

16 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

17 [213] Thomas, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

18 [213] Thomas, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

19 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

20 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

21 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

22 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

23 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

24 [213] Thomas, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

25 [177] REINHARDT. Kurt f., Germany: 2000 Years. (Frederick ~ngar Publishing Co., New York, 1960).

26 [184] Rodes, John e., Germany: A History. (Holt, Rinehart & Wilson, New York 1964).

27 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

28 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

29 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

30 [177] REINHARDT. Kurt f., Germany: 2000 Years. (Frederick ~ngar Publishing Co., New York, 1960).

31 [181] RICKETT, RICHARD, A Brief Survey of Austrian History. (Georg Prachner Verlag, Wien, Third Edition, 1970).

32 [213] Thomas, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

33 [23] CASTELOT, ANDRE, King of Rome, (Translated from French by Robert Baldick), (Harper and Bros. Publishers, New York, 1960).

34 [181] RICKETT, RICHARD, A Brief Survey of Austrian History. (Georg Prachner Verlag, Wien, Third Edition, 1970).

35 [177] REINHARDT. Kurt f., Germany: 2000 Years. (Frederick ~ngar Publishing Co., New York, 1960).

36 [184] Rodes, John e., Germany: A History. (Holt, Rinehart & Wilson, New York 1964).

37 [128] MAREK, GEORGE R., The Eagles Die. (Harper & Row, New York, 1974).

38 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

39 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

40 [126]  MACARTNEY, C.S., Hungary. A Short History. (Aldine Publishing Co., Chicago 1962).

41 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

42 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

43 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

44 [213] Thomas, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

45 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

46 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

47 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

48 [55] DURANT, Will and Ariel, Ibid. Part XI - The Age of Napoleon. (1975).

49 [55] DURANT, Will and Ariel, Ibid. Part XI - The Age of Napoleon. (1975).

50 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

51 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

52 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

53 [23] CASTELOT, ANDRE, King of Rome, (Translated from French by Robert Baldick), (Harper and Bros. Publishers, New York, 1960).

54 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

55 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

56 [55] DURANT, Will and Ariel, Ibid. Part XI - The Age of Napoleon. (1975).

57 [248] CHELMINSKI, RUDOLF, "The plot to murder Napoleon:, Smithsonian 13: No. 1, pp. 76-87, Apr. 1982.

58 [287] "NAPOLEON'S DEATH: ARSENIC & old WALLPAPER", Currents section, page 6, Science 83, Jan./Feb. 1983.

59 [248] CHELMINSKI, RUDOLF, "The plot to murder Napoleon:, Smithsonian 13: No. 1, pp. 76-87, Apr. 1982.

60 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

61 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

62 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

63 [232] WERNICK, ROBERT, "M. de Tallyrand, a controversial Prince of Politics", Smithsonian Nov. 1981, pp. 74-83.

64 [213] Thomas, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

65 [55] DURANT, Will and Ariel, Ibid. Part XI - The Age of Napoleon. (1975).

66 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

67 [74] GRAMONT, SANCHE DE, The French, Portrait of a People. (G.E. Putnam 's Sons~ New York, 1969).

68 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

69 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

70 [23] CASTELOT, ANDRE, King of Rome, (Translated from French by Robert Baldick), (Harper and Bros. Publishers, New York, 1960).

71 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

72 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

73 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

74 [213] Thomas, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

75 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

76 [24] CERRUTE, James, "Belgium, One Nation Divisible", National Geographic 155:314, March, 1979.

77 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

78 [55] DURANT, Will and Ariel, Ibid. Part XI - The Age of Napoleon. (1975).

79 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

80 [213] Thomas, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

81 [170] PREBBEL, JOHN, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

82 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

83 [213] Thomas, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

84 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

85 [213] Thomas, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

86 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

87 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

88 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

89 [55] DURANT, Will and Ariel, Ibid. Part XI - The Age of Napoleon. (1975).

90 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

91 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

92 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

93 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

94 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

95 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

96 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

97 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

98 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

99 [174] RANG, MERCER, Anthology of Orthopedics. (Chas. Livingtone, Edinburgh, London & New York, 1966).

100 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

101 [288] "PEOPLES OF THE ARCTIC", Cartographic Division, National Geographic, Feb. 1983.

102 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

103 [117] La Fay, HOWARD, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

104 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

105 [213] Thomas, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

106 [55] DURANT, Will and Ariel, Ibid. Part XI - The Age of Napoleon. (1975).

107 [55] DURANT, Will and Ariel, Ibid. Part XI - The Age of Napoleon. (1975).

108 [117] La Fay, HOWARD, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

109 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

110 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

111 [34] CLARK, SIDNEY, All the Best in Scandinavia. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1968).

112 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

113 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

114 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

115 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

116 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

117 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

118 [135] MAZOUR, ANATOLE G., Russia, Tsarist and Communist. (D. Van Nostrand Co., Inc. Princeton, New Jersey 1963).

119 [56] DYSON, FREEMAN, Disturbing the Universe. (Harper and Row, N.Y., 1979).

120 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

121 [217] De TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

122 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

123 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

124 [288] "PEOPLES OF THE ARCTIC", Cartographic Division, National Geographic, Feb. 1983.

125 [213] Thomas, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

126 [135] MAZOUR, ANATOLE G., Russia, Tsarist and Communist. (D. Van Nostrand Co., Inc. Princeton, New Jersey 1963).

127 [135] MAZOUR, ANATOLE G., Russia, Tsarist and Communist. (D. Van Nostrand Co., Inc. Princeton, New Jersey 1963).

128 [213] Thomas, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

129 [135] MAZOUR, ANATOLE G., Russia, Tsarist and Communist. (D. Van Nostrand Co., Inc. Princeton, New Jersey 1963).

130 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

131 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

132 [55] DURANT, Will and Ariel, Ibid. Part XI - The Age of Napoleon. (1975).

1.  The French stopped compulsory military small-pox vaccination after the Napoleonic Wars, but the Prussians continued. Thus, small-pox put 20,000 French soldiers out of action in the Franco-Prussian War, while the Germans went unscathed. (Ref. 23)

2.  This comment was taken from the German historian, Reinhart (Ref. 30, but according to the Austrian historian, Rickett (Ref. 31), the true glory of Austria was yet to unfold, as we shall see

3.  The Prussians, who are genetically about half Slavic, registered as a Slav Monarchy. (Ref. 32)

4.  Quotation from Rickett (Ref. 34), page 93

5.  At the time of his birth this baby, Napoleon II, was declared King of Rome, but he never ruled anyplace

6.  See page 1083 for the British resurgence

7.  Quotation from Durant (Ref. 56), page 730

8.  The evidence is basically that arsenic has been identified from hair which was allegedly that of Napoleon (Ref. 59)

9.  This ended the cotton industry for France. (Ref. 64)

10.  This War of 1812 will be discussed in a little more detail in the section on THE UNITED STATES

11.  A Patent Office in Great Britain issued 600 patents between 1850 and 1860 pertaining to firearms. (Ref. 86), page 237n

12.  Altogether Armstrong built 84 warships for 12 different foreign governments 1884-1914. (Ref. 88)

13.  Cheyne-Stokes syndrome is a well known respiratory arrythmia

14.  About 125,000 peasant carts were requisitioned but forage was almost non-existent for the draft animals and the ulimate payloads for the army were far from adequate. (Ref. 123)

15.  As quoted by Mazour (Ref. 126), page 285

The Indian Subcontinent: Beginning to 8,000 B.C.

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

The Indian subcontinent has produced almost no fossil men with the exception of Ramapithecus from the Siwalik beds and a similar jaw from Gandakas in Pakistan. These have just recently been put into the human "line". But men have lived in India since the second interglacial period, from 400,000 to 200,000 B.C. The hand-axes, chopping tools and flakes of the early Stone Age are found in the Punjab foothills, the Soan and Beas valleys, Rajasthan, Malwa and as far south as Madras. Some of these are reminiscent of the Clactonian of Europe and the Olduvan of Africa. At the close of the Paleolithic, tiny bladelet tools likethose of the European Mesolithic Age were being used. From then until about 10,000 B.C. there was a mixture of archaic and gradually more modern societies, of ten side by side.

After 10,000 B.C., except for the high mountains, India was covered by woodland and the modern barren landscape is man-made, due to millennia of woodland clearance for various reasons. (Ref. 1, 2, 3, 4) (Continue on page 36)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

3 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

4 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

The Indian Subcontinent: 3000 to 1500 B.C.

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

In addition to the Brachycephals discussed in the last chapter, other ethnic groups were well established by the 3rd millennium B.C. Negritos, Proto-Australoids and a Mediterranean people now mainly associated with the Dravidian Culture and finally the Mongoloids of the northeast and northern fringes, were all present. The latter were serpent worshiping Nagas, while the Dravidians were adventurous sailing merchants with cities of refinement and luxuries. Today the Deccan, in southern India, is essentially Dravidian in stock, customs and language.

The Brachycephal1 development came to flower in the Indus Valley cities of Harappa and Mohenjo-daro (now all in Pakistan) with a civilization which survived for almost a thousand years (2,550 to 1,550 B.C.) with excellent houses, elaborate drainage systems, bathrooms, etc. - all equal to Sumerian accomplishments and probably superior to Babylonian and Egyptian cultures. At its height this society extended far beyond the Indus Valley, itself, (see map on next page) and covered an area far greater than the contemporary states of Mesopotamia or the Kingdom of Egypt. Of this, only high citadels, solid buildings, uniform grids of streets and the elaborate drainage system remain. It was a society of priests, merchants and peasant farmers with extensive sea trade with Sumer and Babylonia. There was local script writing by 2,400 B.C. but unfortunately it has not yet been convincingly deciphered. No one knows even the language family to which it belongs, although there are thousands of short examples on stone seals, metal objects and pottery. This civilized area not only extended all along the Indus and its tributaries but ran for five hundred miles along the coast of the Arabian Sea, and French archeologists have also discovered remains of a mature Harappan settlement up in northeastern Afghanistan close to the Russian border, a thousand miles northeast of the Indus mouth. The Harappans domesticated the Indian jungle fowl, later to become the world's "chicken". The women apparently all wore at least loin cloths, but the men are often shown naked, in the discovered figurines. (Ref. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5)

The disappearance of this as a living civilization has been traditionally blamed on the destruction wrought by the Aryan invaders from Bactria and northern Iran who descended into this area between 1,600 and 1,500 B.C.. Although they came primarily as immigrants to find pasture land for their cattle, they were also strong fighters when combat was necessary, and gradually all Hindustan (the land north of the Narbada River) was under control of these people, now called "Vedics". They prohibited intermarriage with native groups and thus initiated the Caste System in India. Their Aryan tongue was ancestral to Sanskrit and Sanskrit was a well differentiated language by 2,000 B.C.. They had a sophisticated theology and well organized priesthood, both indicating influences of Sumerian and Babylonian religious ideas. Some authorities put the collapse of the Harappan civilization somewhat earlier, between 1,800 and 1,700 B.C. and mention that the streets of Mohenjo-daro when first excavated were lined with corpses. If the invading Aryans were not responsible, other possibilities included a change in the course of the Indus, or a terrible drought. It is of interest that many Indus settlements were in areas where today there is nothing but dry sand and agriculture would be impossible. Apparently in those ancient days rainfall and river water had been more plentiful and this has been confirmed by archeological pollen counts, These pollens, which were in great numbers in the lowermost layers later dropped in the upper layers of excavation and were then chiefly of desert plants, indicating an obvious drought. One theory of the cause of this has been put forward by Reid Bryson of the University of Wisconsin, who feels that with increasing population of the Indus civilization the forests were destroyed for fuel and timbers, and the resulting deforestation accelerated the run-off of rain, decreasing soil moisture and lowering the fertility from erosion and top-soil loss. Then with overgrazing, a man-made desert appeared, with rising dust which, in turn, clouded and cooled the upper atmosphere, with the resulting heavier, cool air sinking downward and preventing rain. Thus it is possible that the Indus people, pushing their environment to the limit, caused their own downfall and near extinction. In any event, life did continue in the valley but without the highly organized culture previously known. (Ref. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11)

Image not Finished

Map xx Indus Civilization

By 2,000 B.C. Pan chewing was a well established practice in India. Pan is the Betel nut, and like cocaine it is part narcotic and part stimulant. We have mentioned that the Aryans brought live stock with them, particularly cattle. They ate beef, mutton, milk, and curds and used the cooking medium "ghi", a clarified butter, which can be kept for months. They introduced this heavy dependence on dairy products, reinforced by precepts from the Vedas, which led slowly to a belief in the sacredness of the cow, a precept still existing today. (Ref. 12)

Very recent excavations at Balakot on the Arabian Sea coast of southern Pakistan indicate the possibility of a civilization even earlier than the Harappan, with well developed ceramics and the use of copper. In the far south in Sri Lanka, the first inhabitants were the Veddas, who emerged there about 3,000 B.C. Only a few of the descendents of these aborigines still live in the mountainous area. (Ref. 13, 14)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

3 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

4 [44] Dales, George f., "Strange Relics of the Crumbling, Still-puzzling Indus Culture", Smithsonian 89:56-65, July, 1977.

5 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

6 [175] READERS Digest, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

7 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

8 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

9 [176] READERS Digest, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

10 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

11 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

12 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

13 [44] Dales, George f., "Strange Relics of the Crumbling, Still-puzzling Indus Culture", Smithsonian 89:56-65, July, 1977.

14 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

1. There is some evidence to suggest that the Brachycephals were themselves Dravidians. (Ref. 6)

The Indian Subcontinent: 1500 to 1000 B.C.

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

Between about 1,500 and 1,200 B.C. there were successive waves of Aryan charioteers and bowmen moving south from eastern Iran to the Indus Valley. By 1,050 these Rig-Vedic Aryans, with their vigorous, objective and warlike attitude toward life, had extended their domain from the Swat Valley of Afghanistan to the land of the "Seven Induses", and then they moved eastward toward the Ganges. In the Rig-Veda, or first period of the Aryans, goat, horse, sheep and buffalo could be eaten but only barren cows, but by 1,000 B.C. the Atharva-Veda forbade eating even barren cows. The Vedic civilization accumulated a great literature transmitted verbally in the Sanskrit language as the "Vedas" (Books of Knowledge). These were later written down, but probably after 1,000 B.C. Hinduism1  developed from the ancient Sanskrit chants with the concept of Brahman, the Supreme Being, ruling over man and all of a multitude of deities, many of them animistic. The soul of each man (Atman) through many incarnations eventually wins liberation from worldly existence to achieve union with Brahman. Below the level of Brahman in the Hindu pantheon is the trinity of Brahma the creator, Vishnu the preserver and Shiva the destroyer. Brahma is held too sacred for popular rites, but Vishnu and Shiva are worshiped in hundreds of guises and forms and customs. Vishnu has ten chief avatars or forms in which he descends to earth, including Rama of the Ramayana legend, Krishna, hero of the Mahabharata epic, and Buddha, of historical significance. (Ref. 1, 2, 3)

Although ancient Indian society was divided into colors or "varnas", later the last term stood for a grouping according to vocation: Brahmins as priests and scholars; Kshatriyas as rulers and soldiers; Vaishyas, the merchants and farmers; Sudras, the peasants and serfs. All of this developed into the hereditary caste system with eventual emergence of some 3,000 sub-castes. As early as 1,000 B.C. steel was made in India, by melting iron at 1,500 degrees Centigrade and adding less than one percent carbon. (For contrast, copper melts at 500 degrees). Agriculture, as in ancient Iraq and China, depended on irrigation, and this was the most time consuming part of the farmers' work. (Ref. 4, 5, 6) (Continue on page 146)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

3 [25] CHAKRAVARTY, AMIYA, "Hinduism". Great Religions of the World, (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

4 [25] CHAKRAVARTY, AMIYA, "Hinduism". Great Religions of the World, (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

5 [21] BRONOWSKI, J., The Ascent of Man. (Little, Brown & Co. Boston, Toronto, 1973).

6 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

1.  The name "Hinduism" is derived from the name of the Indus River

The Indian Subcontinent: 1000 to 700 B.C.

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

In the last chapter we discussed the southern and eastern expansion of the invading Aryans. Their migration soon became sharply limited because the "forest people" they encountered had endemic tropical and parasitical infestations flourishing in the moist, warm climate which meant death and destruction to the invaders. The aboriginal forest people were only gradually incorporated in special castes, thru in effect isolating them from the conquerors, and this was another element in the development of the caste system. It was only after some adaptation to disease and the advent of iron, in about 800 B.C., that the Aryan Vedics began to actually clear the forest of northern India preparatory for farming and large scale agriculture. (Ref. 1, 2)

In the south, tiny communities developed in the fragmented land, each with its own religious, political and economic life. Distinctive megalithic cultures grew up around Madres, Kerala and Mysore. Sea-faring peoples at the tip of the peninsula traded by sea with the Middle East, shipping ivory, spices and the cotton plants to Mesopotamia. It is of considerable interest that doimens, very similar to those of Europe's second and third millennia B.C., have been found throughout India, but none seem to date before the 8th century B.C. and some much later. (Ref. 3, 4, 5)

The organization and writing of the Vedas rituals began about 1,000 B.C. and probably continued for 500 years. The writing of the Upanishads began about 800 B.C. and continued for about 300 years. The latter consisted of 108 discourses by various teachers, saints and sages with the resulting opinions and philosophies of many men. The belief in transmigration appeared there. According to Toynbee's theories (Ref. 6) this is the height of the original Vedic Society. Of incidental note is the legend in Sri Lanka that King Solomon sent emissaries to the fabled city of Gems, Ratnapura, to get precious stones with which to woo the Queen of Sheba. (Ref. 7)

1 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM h., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

4 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

5 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

6 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

7 [108] JORDON, ROBERT Paul. "Sri Lanka", National Geographic 155: 123, Jan. 1979.

The Indian Subcontinent: 600 to 501 B.C.

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

The Vedic Culture began to decay or at least to stagnate, so that Darius I of Persia had little trouble in seizing Gandhara from the disunited Aryans, and the entire area soon became divided into many small states. Darius' advance into the Indus Valley marked the introduction of coinage, iron working1 and writing into Pakistan. Although powerful and extensive kingdoms developed in the Ganges Valley at that time, they always remained unstable and were never consolidated into an enduring whole, as in China, and one reason was the heavy micro-parasitism characteristic of the warm, wet Ganges climate. This heavy infestation and infection must have reduced individual vigor and capacity for physical labor, and is probably one reason that Indian empires were fragile and subject to easy conquest by invaders from the north, until the invaders themselves became infested. The transcendentalism that became characteristic of the Indian religions accorded well with the circumstances of poverty-stricken, disease ridden peasants. In Toynbee's (Ref. 1) terminology, it was a "time of troubles" and as usual in such situations, new philosophies and religions began to appear to save man or lift him out of the drudgery of his life. By this time, the caste system was well established at least in northern India. Benares, at the gentle four mile curve of the Ganges, was already the goal of thousands of Hindus who went there to bathe and drink its water and to beseech the favor of some god. (Ref. 2, 3, 4, 5)

Gautama Buddha, scion of the aristocratic Gautama clan living at the foot of the Himalayas, was born in 563 B.C. He left his family and after an initial withdrawal period with self mortification, he returned to the active world to teach his ideas of ethics. He did not write, but talked, a man of strong will, authoritative and proud, but of gentle manner and speech and of infinite benevolence. His idea of Nirvana was complete annihilation. Later, a legend of divine birth appeared among Buddha's followers, but he, himself, claimed no divine origin and in fact was in essence an atheist, worshiping no god, having no ritual and interested only in ethics.

In the middle of this century there also appeared another religion founded by Mahavira and called "Jains". Mahavira taught that the road to release from the tragedy of life was to be found through ascetic penances and complete "ahimsa". The latter means abstinence from injury to any living thing. Gandhi was later strongly influenced by this sect. Neither Buddhism nor Jainism accepted the caste system, which was Hindu in origin, and both were opposed to violence and to any animal slaughter. The Jains even had to be careful in eating any fruit or vegetable, as it might contain an insect which might be a human soul in re-in- carnation. Finally, the only animal protein food in India was an occasional chicken or, on the coast, fish and seafood.

Aryan invaders from north India arrived in Sri Lanka in this or the preceding century and the present day majority Sinhalese ( seven out of ten Sri Lankans) claim descent from them. They are Buddhists and theirs is the official language of the island. (Ref. 7, 8) (Continue on page 207)

1 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

2 [136] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

3 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

4 [37] COLLINS, LARRY and LAPRERRE, DOMINIQUE, Freedom at Midnight. (Simon & Schuster, New York, 1975).

5 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

6 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

7 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

8 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

1.  Some believe there was iron smelting in India as early as 800 B.C. (Ref. 6, page 271)

The Indian Subcontinent: 500 to 401 B.C.

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT (THE THIRD GREAT CENTER OF CIVILIZATION)

This was a continued time of troubles in India, with political deterioration. While previously there had been some sixteen great realms along the rich Gangetic plain, the number was now gradually reduced to four - the three kingdoms of Kasi, Kosala and Magadha and the Republic of Vrijji. Nevertheless, some of the arts and sciences flourished in this valley. Most of the Indus Valley remained under Persian control. (Ref. 1)

The direction of growth of India and some of its limiting factors had been pretty well determined in this century in which Buddha died. By the end of the century Buddhism had already faded in this land of its birth and the major outlines of the religious world-view which was to govern all future Indian history had emerged, although not yet organized in its present day form. (Ref. 2)

1 [136] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

2 [46] DURANT, WILL, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

The Indian Subcontinent: 400 to 301 B.C.

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

After a century of wars, the kingdom of Magadha absorbed the other three great realms of Gangetic India and established a capital at Pataliputra (Batna) on the lower Ganges. In 327 B.C. Alexander reached India, taking about one-half of the country and making King Porus a puppet ruler over the most northern portion. Only seven years later, however, Chandragupta Maurya overcame the Macedonian garrisons and annexed all land east of the Indus and south to the Narmada River. In 303 B.C. he defeated Alexander's successor, Seleucus Nicator, and obtained the Greek province of Trans-lndus which included a large part of Afghanistan. This Mauryan government then became the most powerful then existing in the world, with a civilization at least equal to that of the Greeks. Taxila was a city of great universities; there were no slaves. Cotton clothing, made from a Burmese import, was widely worn, although lndia soon developed its own cotton supply. Government administration was controlled by the vizier, Kautilya, a Brahman who knew the political value of religion but took no moral guidance from it. This became an autocracy which Toynbee recognizes as the "universal state" of the original Vedic Society. This is thought to be the time of Panini's Sanscrit Grammar, which codified the rules for "classical" Sanscrit, as derived from the Vedas. (Ref. 1, 2, 3)

The ancient city of Anuradhapura was built in Sri Lanka in this century and it lasted until the 11th century of the Christian Era. It was located in the lowlands northwest of Polomnaruwa and was supplied by a water system which is still in use today, although the city itself is buried. There are multiple lake reservoirs and bell-shaped housing relics of the Buddha, some as high as forty stories. (Ref. 4)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

3 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

4 [108] JORDON, ROBERT Paul. "Sri Lanka", National Geographic 155: 123, Jan. 1979.

The Indian Subcontinent: 300 to 201 B.C.

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

Ashoka Vardhana (also Asoka), grandson of Chandragupta, came to the throne in 273 B.C., monarch of Afghanistan, Baluchistan and all of modern India except Tamil Land in the extreme south. At first he ruled well, although cruelly. In midlife he became intensely interested in Buddhism, changed his ways, joined a Buddhist order and became an ardent missionary and zealous administrator. He was hated by the Brahmins, the priestly class of the old religion, and in spite of Ashoka's Buddhism it was in this century that Hinduism finally evolved with a new generation of gods; Shiva, Vishnu, Rama and Brahma. (Ref. 1)

On the "Rock Edicts of Ashoka" appear "Arabic" numerals - a thousand years before they appear in Arabic literature. These numerals are one of our great heritages from India. Among inscriptions of this century are statements that hospitals had been established for humans and for animals, although it is not clear if these were the first. Elaborate dispensaries and special maternal and operating facilities were also described. (Ref. 2) Most artisans of the Maurya Empire worked in guilds which eventually developed many features similar to trade unions. (Ref. 3) After Ashoka's death, the empire was split into a number of parts.

1 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

2 [125] LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

3 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

The Indian Subcontinent: 200 to 101 B.C.

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

The Iranian Yue-chi (Tocharians), run out of central Asia by the Hsuing-nu, ended up south of the Pamirs, in northern Pakistan. (Ref. 1) The great Maurya Dynasty ended with the death of King Brihadratha in 185 B.C. and the history of the next five centuries has been pretty well lost in obscurity. It is known that the Maurya were at least partially overthrown by the Pushyamitra from the Ganges Valley and that they then established the Sunga Dynasty. This was a Brahmin dominated group which caused the Buddhists to retreat to other areas where there was soon a flowering of Buddhist sculpture. Some Greeks, Syrians and Scythians conquered the Punjab and established a Greco-Bactrian Culture under Demetrius, the Greek Bactrian king, and it existed for some 300 years.The Deccan in the south became separated from the rest of India with the formation of the Tamil states. These people were Dravidians, a dark-skinned race which some believe to be a mixture from Mediterranean, Australoid and Melanesian origins.

1 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

The Indian Subcontinent: 100 B.C. to 0

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA ("Former" Han Dynasty continued)

At its peak the Han Empire under Wu-Ti was exceedingly prosperous, rivaling Rome both in size and wealth. The capital city Ch'ang-an had 250,000 in a total empire population of about 57,000,000. While the progress of mechanization was impeded in Greece and Rome by the number of available slaves, China had too many efficient coolies. (Ref. 1) We noted above that Wu-Ti expanded into the Tarim Basin in the west by defeating the Hsiung-nu and this pursuance continued even after Wu-Ti's death. In 51 B.C. the chieftain of the southern Huns came to Ch'ang-an to submit as an Han vassal, while the northern group continued to be chased far westward into Samarkand, there to be finally defeated by a five-pronged Han force in 36 B.C. But in China proper the economic controls lapsed and nepotism and cronyism resulted in the loss of the imperial family's power.

A type of national university had come into existence to prepare men for bureaucratic careers and by the end of the century the enrollment had reached 3,000. In the Han militia system all males registered for military service at 21 years of age and were eligible for service between the ages of 23 and 56 years. Allegedly every male was to have military service in his home county one month every year and one year of continuous service sometime in a guard unit, but soon a practice of paying poorer men to serve one's time became standard practice. In addition to using cowrie shells as currency, copper coins, later called sapekes by the Europeans, came into use. Both of these competed with salt and grain as a medium of exchange. (Ref. 2) In this century the Chinese drilled deep holes, presumably for water, in Szechwan and their drilling methods were copied centuries later in the United States. (Ref. 3)

In early China the laws required punishments and torture that equaled that seen in Europe at a much later period. Death penalties were carried out by beheading or by chop- ping the offender in two at the waist. In cases of treason or some equally serious crime, all the offender's relatives might also be put to death. Lesser offenders might simply be mutilated by tattooing, amputation of nose or feet or castration. Imprisonment was rare, but hard labor on government construction was used for minor offenders. In Emperor Ch'eng's reign (32 - 7 B.C.) authority was delegated to his mother's family, the Wang clan. Ssu-me Ch'ien was a great Chinese historian of this era. (Ref. 4, 5)

In Manchuria a new state of Koguryo was founded in this century and soon also included northern Korea.

JAPAN

The Yayoishiki Culture continued into this century with rice culture appearing about 100 B.C. Animism and totemism, sex and ancestor worship satisfied the religious needs of these early Japanese. Out of the latter worship came the oldest official living religions of the nation - Shinto. This faith, called the Way of the Gods, took three forms; the domestic cult of family ancestors, the communal cult of clan ancestors and the state cult of the imperial line with its founding gods.

A Mongolian castaway group on Kyushu multiplied so rapidly as farmers that they took over all the arable land on the island and while some of the aborigines became serfs, others took to the hills from where they continued to raid the farmers for centuries. The new Kyushu community was organized as a loose confederacy of villages, each ruled by its own matriarch or fertility mother, and the woman leader of the most powerful town was called the "Sun Goddess". Early Chinese traders called her "Pime-ko", or "Hime-Ko", meaning "Sunshine Child". (Ref. 6, 7, 8) In an attempt to obtain more sea-food to feed the expanding population, a great ship-building effort was made in 81 B.C. (Ref. 9)

KOREA

Most of Korea was controlled by the Han Chinese at this time, but the northern portion was allied with Manchuria in the new state of Koguryo.

SOUTHEAST ASIA

Already controlling North Vietnam, the Chinese now added central Viet Nam to their territory which they were to maintain for centuries. No other significant changes occurred.

1 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

2 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

3 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

4 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

5 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

6 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

7 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

8 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

9 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

The Indian Subcontinent: 0 to A.D. 100

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

In the first half of the century for a brief period the great trading city of Taxila in north India (now Pakistan) was controlled by Indo-Parthians, and the surrounding Saka area had predominantly a Greek culture in spite of the Iranian genealogy. All this ended about A.D. 60 as the Tocharians and the mighty Kushan tribes took over this area. The Kushans reached Benares (150 miles west of Patna) destroying the Sakas as they went. In the far east, a Buddhist civilization flourishing in Bengal was forced to abandon that faith by a Hindu dynasty which subsequently oppressed the native people. (Ref. 1, 2, 3)

The Deccan of India was ruled by the Buddhist Satavahana Dynasty while the Munda kings continued to control southern India. The southern coast now assumed new importance because of the sea links between China, India and the Mediterranean world. Pliny complained that India's spices, jewels, muslins and exotic animals were costing Romans 550 million sesterces a year. Also shipped out were turquoise, diamonds, spikenard, indigo, silk yarn and tortoise-shell, while imports were wine, pearls, copper, dates, gold and slaves from Ethiopia, Arabia and the Mediterranean.

Christianity may have reached India even this early in that the apostle Thomas is supposed to have founded the Syrian Church in Malabar before being killed in A.D. 68. This is usually given as the time of Charaka, the great Indian physician who composed an encyclopedia of medicine still used in that country, but he may have lived much earlier. He listed 500 medicinal plants and developed a rather unsystematic catalogue of diseases and cures. His description of what constituted a good hospital would do credit to any today. The Prakrit language became the chief medium of the Buddhists and Jains and Sanskrit faded except in the professional writing of the Brahmins. (Ref. 4, 5, 6, 7)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

3 [37] COLLINS, LARRY and LAPRERRE, DOMINIQUE, Freedom at Midnight. (Simon & Schuster, New York, 1975).

4 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

5 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

6 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

7 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

The Indian Subcontinent: 101 A.D. to 200

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

Under their greatest king, Kanishka (ca. 120 - 160), the arts and sciences flourished among the Kushans. After experimenting with many religions, the king finally chose the new mystical Buddhism and called a great council of Buddhist theologians to formulate this creed for his realm. The council lowered Buddha's philosophy to the emotional needs of the common soul but raised Buddha to a divinity, thus laying the basis for the Mahayana or Greater Vehicle Buddhism which later helped to win China and Japan. It is a variation of Buddhism which shows definite influence from the Greek religions. The Kushan rule extended from Benares and Kabut to the Vindhyas, with a capital at Peshawar.

Some further discussion of the confusions which surround the history of the Kushans seems relevant. It has been mentioned previously that they were a mixture of Yu~e-chi tribes (some say five tribes), but the Chinese name is misleading in that they spoke a variety of Iranian languages. Wells wrote that the Yue-chi had originally been pushed over into western Turkistan by Hun peoples who conquered the Bactrians and then mixed with Aryan elements there to create the fusion known as Indo-Scythians who then went over the Kyber Pass down into India. This is not the current concept which is that the Kushans were entirely Indo-European. After the middle of the century, foreign kingdoms in the north began to fade and indigenous Indian groups emerged. (Ref. 1, 2)

Buddhism now became divided into two schools, the mystical Mahayana, or Greater Vehicle, mentioned above, and the Hinayana or Lesser Vehicle, also called Theravada Buddhism or Way of the Elders, which retained much of the primitive simplicity of the original philosophy. The particular branch of this religion dominant in Kashmir, the Sarvastivadin, was one of two main off-shoots of the Hinayana but Hindu faiths existed at the same time, with Siva as the most favored deity. Kanishka established a city in his own name in Kashmir in this century. Throughout all these early centuries of the Christian era, the region of Kashmir was subject to incursions of Sakas, Kushans, Tibetans and Huns from the north as well as migrations of Gujaras from the south. Kashmir kept contact with Gandhara in present day Pakistan and shared some of the artistic blending of Hellenic and Parthian influences. (Ref. 3, 4)

The Deccan was still dominated by the Munda kings. In Malwa there was a dynasty of Satraps of Ujjain, a community which became a center of Sanskrit learning and was taken as the basic meridian by Indian astronomers. In the far south of India it was Hinduism which flourished. Sanskrit influence is clear in the Tamil language grammar although not much else of Aryan India penetrated Tamil. The basic devotion was to the Hindu gods of Vishnu and Siva. Indian art was influenced by Greek sculpture and their science was influenced to some degree. Sri Lanka was briefly occupied by the Tamils in this century. (Ref. 5)

1 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [114] KITAGAWA, JOSEPH M., "The Eightfold Path to Nirvana", Great Religions of the World. (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

4 [275] FISHER, ROBERT E., "The Stone Temples of Kashmir", Archaeology 35, No. 4: 47-53, July/ Aug. 1982.

5 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

The Indian Subcontinent: A.D. 201 to 300

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

The Kushan rule in India faded away. Ujjain, in Malwa, continued as a capital and center with a continued dynasty of Western Satraps. The Buddhist community was now definitely divided into Hin-ayana and Mahayana groups, but in the far south Hinduism was the more important. Brahman colonies with Hinduism and the caste system were imported from the Ganges Valley at various periods and endowed by local rulers. This was done in Bengal. About 225 in Maharashra, the break-up of the Satakani Empire led to the establishment of the Traikutka Dynasty from local pastoral tribes. They eventually even took over the throne at Ujjain.

Sanskrit now began to be revised as a more common language, after several hundred years of partial banishment. This attested the prestige of the Brahminical tradition and proved the effectiveness of the numerous educational institutions of the land. It might be appropriate to insert here, that not all of the Brahman caste were priests. Although they were, in Hindu tradition "born twice", once at delivery and once at age six when a double stranded gut of sacred thread was looped around their necks, their privileges were not necessarily either economic nor purely religious. Some were poor farmers, some mailmen, some workers of other trades, but all supposedly lived by many daily rituals. (Ref. 1, 2)

Possibly originating in India in this century (otherwise in China) was a high quality carbonized steel made by a crucible smelting process unknown in Europe until the 1 9th century. This came to be known as Damascus or damask steel in Europe and was used particularly to make swords of amazing sharpness. Ingots of this were exported from India to the Far East, Arabia, Syria, Russia and Persia. (Ref. 3)

1 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

2 [37] COLLINS, LARRY and LAPRERRE, DOMINIQUE, Freedom at Midnight. (Simon & Schuster, New York, 1975).

3 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

The Indian Subcontinent: A.D. 301 to 400

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

The power of the Kushans continued to fade and a line of native kings appeared in the Gupta Dynasty, beginning with Chandragupta I in A.D. 320, based in Magadha. His successor, Samudragupta, in a 50 year reign, became one of the foremost monarchs in India's long history. He conquered Bengal, Assam, Nepal and southern India and with the wealth thus gained promoted literature, science, religion and the arts. It was the Golden Age of India, while Europe and China were falling into what many have labeled the "Dark Ages". Buddhist art reached its zenith. The decimal system was used here long before the Arabs and Syrians used it. Chemistry developed from two sources – medicine and industries such as dyeing, soapmaking, tanning and the manufacture of glass and cement. The making of solid sugar by boiling cane juice was begun in this century. The Iranian frontier standing between the steppes and India secured the latter against invasion and thus indirectly contributed to the flowering of the Indian culture. Toynbee (Ref. 1) considers the Gupta Dynasty as a resumed Indian universal state after the Hellenic interruption of Alexander's conquests. (Ref. 2, 3, 4, 5)

The great Hindu epic poems, the Mahabharata and Ramayana, were written down in Sanskrit in this period. The first of these was three and one-half times as long as the entire Bible. The Brahmans, the priestly class of the Hindus, were again growing in wealth and power and by the end of the century they finally won out over the Buddhists and established a universal religion of Hinduism. This emerged from older Brahminism through re-evaluation of a multiplicity of local worships.

Sushrata (also Susrata or Susruta) was a great Indian surgeon who did many advanced surgical procedures, including cataract operations, hernia repairs, lithotomies and Caesarian sections. Cataract was treated by couching (displacing the lens downward); amputations were common and several types of plastic surgery procedures were done. Since cutting off the nose was an official punishment for adultery, Indian surgeons developed elaborate flap operations turning skin down from the forehead to reconstruct a nose. Sushrata also excelled at plastic repair of torn ear lobes. His armamentaria included 121 surgical instruments. He recommended the observations of corpses as a means of learning anatomy but demands of ritual purity prevented dissection. Some 1,120 diseases and 760 medicinal plants were classified. Physicians were taught in apprenticeships and then subjected to certification by the ruler. The neophyte finally took an oath, not unlike the Hippocratic oath of Greece. (Ref. 6, 7) (Continue on page 400)

1 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

2 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

3 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

4 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

5 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

6 [46] DURANT, WILL, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

7 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

The Indian Subcontinent: A.D. 401 to 500

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

The Gupta civilization continued to flourish in northern India, but at the close of the century a new barbarian eruption shattered the peace as the Ephthalites overran and invaded northwestern India from central Asia. There is still apparently some confusion about the make-up and origin of these invaders. McNeill (Ref. 1) calls them a branch of the Mongol Juan-Juan but other authorities (Ref. 2) insist that they were of a white, Turkish race, not Mongoloid. At any event, although they had made some raids as early as 455 by 480 they had destroyed the Gupta Empire, never to be restored, and they had demolished the Buddhist monasteries.

In western India many impregnable fortresses in Rajputana kept the Asian invaders out and the local power was divided among several local dynasties. A Pallava warrior dynasty controlled the Deccan and there were many local altercations with the adjacent Chalukyas.

Individual accomplishment is often independent of external rule and so in spite of the turmoil of this period in India, Aryabhata (A.D. 499) wrote a mathematical works for use in astronomical calculations. Much was borrowed from the Greeks but some innovations appeared, including a unique system of numerical notation. He was familiar with the decimal system and with zero, although he did not actually use the latter. He taught the theory of the rotation of the earth and gave the value of Pi at 3.141.

1 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

The Indian Subcontinent: A.D. 501 to 600

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

Chaos continued from the Ephthalite invasions throughout the failing Gupta Empire in the north. The invaders were finally defeated by a Hindu confederation in 528 but they had profoundly affected the caste system and disrupted the heirarchy of ruling families. Some Ephthalites stayed in India as a distinct group. In spite of the warfare, great scientific progress was made in this northern India area, with advances in chemistry such as calcination, distillation, sublimation, production of light without heat, the mixing of anesthetic and soporific powders and the formation of metallic salts, compounds and alloys. Brahmagupta, the astronomer, lived near the end of the century and systematized rules of arithmetic, algebra and astronomy and developed an integral solution of an indeterminate equation. (Ref. 1, 2)

The third branch of Buddhism, Tantric, appeared in the Himalayan lands, interlacing Mahayana Buddhism with old Tantric cults of India that invoked deities by magic and rituals. There was a large array of divinities both male and female, along with demons. (Ref. 3)

The Deccan was not unified again until about 550, under the western Calukya Dynasty. Southern India remained essentially Dravidian, but little is known of its detailed history and nothing of its art until the end of this century when the Pallavas ruled from north of Madras to the sacred river, Kaseri, and had sculptures and cave temples. Still farther south were the Pandyas and Ceras. (Ref. 4)

In Ceylon, the original Veddas were conquered by Sinhalese invaders from northern India and the Veddas survive today only as a small group in the remote interior. (Ref. 5) (Continue on page 445)

1 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

2 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

3 [114] KITAGAWA, JOSEPH M., "The Eightfold Path to Nirvana", Great Religions of the World. (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

4 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

5 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

The Indian Subcontinent: A.D. 601 to 700

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

Harsha-Vardhana (also Sri Harsha), a scion of the Gupta line, recaptured and unified northern India in 606 and, ruling from Kanauj, gave peace and security to the area for 42 years. Arts and letters flourished and the Buddhist religion had a revival. At his death, however, chaos again ensued and India had her "Dark Ages" for the next 1,000 years. By the middle of the century a Chinese "tourist" reported that there were 70 kingdoms in the country. The two principal dynasties in western India were the Maitrakas, who created a Buddhist scholastic center, and the Gurjara, a horde of central Asiatics, who had settled in the central Rajputana.

The Deccan, on the plateau in southern India, remained independent under the Calukyas Dynasty. (Ref. 1) Under one of their more famous kings, Pulakeshin, this country controlled and commanded respect from a good deal of territory, including central India. It was the time of the famous frescoes of Ajanta. At the very southern tip of India the Pandyas Dynasty had a capital at Madurai and the Pallavas at Kanchipuram. The latter controlled the rich coastal area on the east, while similar land on the west coast was controlled by the Cheras in the region now called Kerala.

Hinduism developed two sects - Vaishnavism (worship of Vishnu) and Shaivism (worship of Shiva). As these increased in popularity Buddhism and Janism shrank in importance. The speech of ordinary people diverged more and more from the Sanskrit of the intellectual and the population of about 100,000,000 remained quite constant. (Continue on page 467).

1 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

The Indian Subcontinent: A.D. 701 to 800

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

The Moslems became established in the Indus Valley, taking Sind in A.D. 711, and they also took over the central Asian oases north of the Hindu Kush, while Moslem shipping took over control of the Indian Ocean, thus almost isolating Hindu India. The Himalayan borderlands remained beyond Moslem reach. Kashmir and Bengal had become powerful states soon after the 6th century and continued throughout the period under review. Magnificent Buddhist temples were constructed in Kashmir at this time. (Ref. 1) There were no powers in the north of India equal to those in the south but by the end of this century two new dynasties, the Palas of Bengal and the Pratiharas of Rajasthan began a struggle for the control of northern India. The former were Buddhists with strong ties to Tibet and kept the old religion alive at a time when it was disappearing elsewhere in India. It was from this group that Tibet got their Tantric form of Buddhism in this century. The Guijaras of western India united with Pratihara and together they succeeded in keeping out the Moslems for another two centuries.

In the Deccan, the Rashtrakutas overthrew the Chalukyas in 753 and began a 200 year rule. They built the greatest of the Indian rock-cut temples. The warrior kings of the Pallava continued to rule a part of the Deccan, however, as they had for almost 500 years and in their empire assemblies of village leaders, guilds and professional groups were held annually, making a unique form of democracy. At the last of the century, in the east, the eastern Chalukya Dynasty began to exert some control as a Buddhist clan with unique Buddhist bronzes. Kalinga was ruled by the eastern Gangas. In southern India, there- was conflict between Jains and the adherents of Shivaism which sometimes led to massacres. (Ref. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6)

Scientific activity continued in India, with advancement particularly in mathematics - including rules for finding permutations and combinations, the square root of two and the solving of indeterminate equations of second degree - all features unknown in Europe until the time of Euler, 1,000 years later. The staple crops were wheat, rice and some millet. Exports were cotton textiles and spices, while the most sought after import was the horse. (Continue on page 497)

1 [275] FISHER, ROBERT E., "The Stone Temples of Kashmir", Archaeology 35, No. 4: 47-53, July/ Aug. 1982.

2 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

3 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

4 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

5 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

6 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

The Indian Subcontinent: A.D. 801 to 900

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

The Arabs who had invaded Sind in the last century were held at bay by the Pratiharase. These Sind Arabs now split up into the twin kingdoms of Multan and Mansura, later to become important trading communities on the Indus and independent of the Abbasids.

The consolidation of powerful states along the northern marches gave Indian politics a new character. No one state was strong enough to unite the north Indian plain, yet each was able to prevent any other from so doing. Frontier guard against Islam no longer was a problem and the Indian rulers were free to pursue their own quarrels. Finally the Pratiharas overcame the Palas and were in control of the Gangetic plain, becoming the greatest political power in India and great builders in the Gupta tradition. (Ref. 1) Cities flourished and the revival of Hinduism resulted in more and more organization around temples, so that everyone tended to cluster within the temple precincts. Royal courts began to play only a secondary role. Tantrism had now come to full flower as an atavistic, magical and libidinous cult absorbed into the Hindu practices, with special influence from eastern India to Nepal and Tibet. The most influential Hindu religious philosopher was Shankara (also Sankaracharya), a Brahman from Kerala, who tried to reduce the multiple concepts of the Upanishands to an intellectual system. (Ref. 2) Buddhism gradually merged back into the wider field of Indian religiosity from which it had sprung and it survived as a distinct doctrine only on the fringes of the Indian world, in Ceylon, Burma and Tibet. (Ref. 3) Even in Kashmir, Buddhism seemed to give way in some degree to Hinduism with the construction of the shrine of Avantisvami, made with steeply pitched, double-pent roofs, because of the heavy winter snows. The design had a central tower shrine and a smaller shrine in each corner, the typical Vishnu, Kashmiri temple. King Avantivarman (855-883) was one of Kashmir's most beloved monarchs, reigning in an era of peace. (Ref. 4)

The Jains resisted the Tantric movement and retained their identity but with a very limited membership, chiefly in southern and western India. The Parsis, followers of Zoraster, came to India about this time as refuges from the Moslem conquest of Persia and they have survived until today mainly in the region around modern Bombay. In the Deccan, the Rashtrakutas, who had overthrown the Chalukyas, built the great temple of Ellora, carved from solid rock. They were also true patrons of literature. In the south the Pallavas were superseded by the Cholas, who sculpted hard stone and modeled bronze. (Ref. 5) Samkara, of Malabar on the southwest coast, revitalized the Vedanta1 and his doctrine became accepted as orthodox Brahmanism. He founded four scholastic monasteries (Continue on page 527)

1 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

4 [275] FISHER, ROBERT E., "The Stone Temples of Kashmir", Archaeology 35, No. 4: 47-53, July/ Aug. 1982.

5 [173] RAMSEY L.G.G., The Complete Encyclopedia of Antiques. (Hawthorn Books, Inc., New York, 1962).

6 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

1.  The Vedanta is a derivative of the Upanishads. (Ref. 6)

The Indian Subcontinent: A.D. 901 to 1000

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

We noted in the last chapter that Buddhism was being replaced to some extent in Kashmir by Hinduism, but one particular off-shoot of Hinayana Buddhism called "Sarvastivadin" tended to persist alongside Siva and Vishnu. A distinct school of Saivism developed which added deep philosophical aspects to the Kashmir intellectual tradition. (Ref. 1)

The Pratihara power in the north began to weaken as the result of Turkish raids and battles with southern dynasties. Beginning about 997 the Turk Mahmud from Ghazni, Afghanistan, made regular raids into Hindustan. The Rashtrakutas were the last southern power to ever exercise any pressure against the north until the 18th century and in this 10th century they were displaced in the Deccan by a descendant of the old Chalukya kings. In central India the Chola Kingdom developed between Madura and Madras and extended westward to Mysore. This began a long career of conquest which brought them tribute from all southern India and even Ceylon. Religion and gods and temples had definitely come to the forefront in Indian culture. The Tantric cult practices were absorbed into general Hinduism and Buddhism became an empty shell by the end of the century. (Ref. 2)

Sri Lanka (Ceylon) has strong historical connections with north India from which both its language and dominant religion, Buddhism, are derived. Artistically, however, it has been influenced by the eastern Deccan and southern India. At the end of this 10th century Ceylon was invaded by the militant Cholas and the locals moved their capital south to Polunnaruwa. At the peak of its glory the city of Anuradhapura, now buried, had an area greater than modern day Chicago. The inner city contained only holy structures, palaces and pleasure domes for royalty. Thousands of monks took their daily rice from huge stone troughs that still exist. (Ref. 3) (Continue on page 563)

1 [275] FISHER, ROBERT E., "The Stone Temples of Kashmir", Archaeology 35, No. 4: 47-53, July/ Aug. 1982.

2 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

3 [108] JORDON, ROBERT Paul. "Sri Lanka", National Geographic 155: 123, Jan. 1979.

The Indian Subcontinent: A.D. 1001 to 1100

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

As the Pratihara Dynasty fell in 1019, political power in the north of India passed to local chieftains, most of whom belonged to Rajput clans and who were descendants of Ephthalites and other invaders of the past. Then Mahmud the Turk raided from Afghanistan into western India and became the richest king in history. Moslem historians have rated him the greatest monarch of his time, as he ruled the Punjab and the northern Ganges regions, although keeping his headquarters in Afghanistan. (Ref. 1)

Palas Buddhist kings ruled Bengal and Bagadha but Chola armies from the south raided as far north on the east coast as the Ganges Delta. These Cholas, originally from the tip of the peninsula, were an ancient people who had now conquered most of Tamil, the eastern Deccan, Ceylon and parts of the Malay peninsula, under their King Rajaraja and his son, Rajendra. Then they drove north, helping to dismember the Palas domains and threatening the Bengals' independence. Ceylon (Sri Lanka) finally expelled the Cholas in 1070 when the dynasty was ended by an assassination.

It is of some interest that in this century the ancient Ayurvedic (knowledge of life), a traditional Indian healing method, was translated into Persian and Arabic and thus eventually spread to medieval Europe. (Ref. 2) (Continue on page 594)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

The Indian Subcontinent: A.D. 1101 to 1200

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

India's "Dark Ages" continued with only one bright spot, the Rajputana1. In the small sub-states of historical Mewar (now Udaipur), Marwar, Amber and adjacent areas a people one-half native and one-half descended from Scythians and Ephthalites, built a feudal civilization under the government of war-like rajas. The central feature was a blood relationship within each clan. All the Rajput courts were centers of Sanskrit learning and their chronicles included a chivalric code unique in India. Their sovereignty ended late in the century when a new Turkish power swept down from Central Asia. This was a remnant of the old Ghaznavid Empire which had been thrown out of Asia in the last century by the Seljuqs and was now led by Muizzudin Muhammad of the Ghurid family. Having overthrown their Ghasnavid suzerains, they entered the Punjab in A.D. 1186 and had defeated the Rajput clans by 1191. Muhammad (also known as Muhammed Ghuri) set up the Sultanate of Delhi, which was to rule northern India for three centuries with great cruelty and fanaticism. Wells (Ref. 1) calls this the Kharismian or Khiva Empire of Turks. Mohammad appointed Kutb-ud-dun Aibak, a slave from Turkistan, to be viceroy of his Indian conquests and left him full discretion in its management. About 1200 these Turkish Moslems swept into Bengal (now Bangladesh) and were eagerly greeted by the people who were seeking a release from Hindu oppression. (Ref. 2, 3, 4, 5) (Continue on page 643)

1 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

4 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

5 [37] COLLINS, LARRY and LAPRERRE, DOMINIQUE, Freedom at Midnight. (Simon & Schuster, New York, 1975).

1.  Rajputana is the historical state roughly corresponding to modern Rajasthan

The Indian Subcontinent: A.D. 1201 to 1300

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

We noted in the last chapter that after 1186 the Moslem Turk, Muizzudin Muhammad, led his forces down from Afghanistan to set up the Sultanate of Delhi. The first 13th century ruler (A.D. 1206) of this new dynasty was Qutbuddin Aibak, a general of Muhammad's, who established a capital at Delhi. By 1235 this sultanate had extended from the Sind to Bengal and continued to gradually expand. (Ref. 1) The general policy of those Turkish sultans of India are indicated by Ala-ud-din 's instructions to his advisors near the end of the century to the effect that they should draw up rules and regulations for grinding down the Hindus and depriving them of wealth and prosperity. Although politically succumbing to these invaders, 4/5 of the people of India remained Hindus although impoverished. Lacking power to resist they took refuge in supernatural consolations.

Hinduism argued that both mastery and slavery were superficial delusions and concluded that freedom of body or nation was hardly worth defining in so brief a life. That was and is the secret of India. (Ref. 2) Metallic guns with powder, but not cannon, were in use in India by 1275. (Ref. 3) (Continue on page 684)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

3 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

The Indian Subcontinent: A.D. 1301 to 1400

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

The Delhi (Turkish) Sultanate expanded under a new Turkish group, the Khalis, and they were alert enough to admit local Indian Muslims to high office, thus relieving much of the internal tension. Under Muhammad bin Tughlug (1325-51) the sultanate reached its maximum with 23 kingdoms, including all of the southern ones - an area larger than any Indian conglomerate since Asoka. (Ref. 1) He attempted close control over the economy, fixing prices, replacing gold and silver money with copper and brass tokens and regulated imports and exports. (Ref. 2) High taxes, an abortive attempt to move Delhi, with all its people, to the south and the sheer size of the empire led to its decline. Various states broke away and by the time of the invasion by Timur in 1398 Tughlug barely controlled the area beyond Delhi, itself. (Ref. 3) Timur sacked Delhi, however, slaying 100,000 prisoners in cold blood after defeating Tughlug's Moslem forces.

The religious and philosophical Hindu activity in Kashmir ceased when the Moslem invaders took over the valley and today Kashmiris are nearly all followers of Islam. (Ref. 4)

In southern India the state of Vijayanager began to rise as a power and soon comprised all the present native states of the lower peninsula, along with Mysoa and Madras. It was primarily a military realm which fought constantly with the northern sultanate, using cannons and cavalry. It did not fall to the Moslems until late in the next century.

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

3 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

4 [275] FISHER, ROBERT E., "The Stone Temples of Kashmir", Archaeology 35, No. 4: 47-53, July/ Aug. 1982.

The Indian Subcontinent: A.D. 1401 to 1500

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

As many Hindus began to accept the Moslem faith, both religions had adaptations to make. The caste system was not compatible with Islam, but the Sufi ideas could be adapted to Indian mysticism. Ramananda and Kabir were reformers who spoke against the caste system, reincarnation, etc. Kabir claimed all Hindus and Moslems really worshiped the same God and should be one religious community. The Sikhs trace their origin to Kabir, although their distinct religious organization did not appear as such until later, under Nanak, in 1538. The Kingdom of Delhi, although reduced in size, kept a tenuous hold over the Punjab. The Sayyid rulers laid claim to Arab descent from the Prophet. Later, in 1451, the Afghan, Buhlul Lodi, founded the Lodi dynasty in that area.

Unfortunately, one early century Kashmir ruler, Sikander, became so inflamed with Islam that he leveled most of the earlier Buddhist and Hindu structures, leaving piles of stone scattered across the valley where these beautiful temples had previously stood. (Ref. 1)

The Vijayanagar Empire was the dominant power in south India, shielding the southern people from the Moslem kingdoms of the north. The capital city, by the same name, was some 60 miles in circumference, flourishing as a trade, Brahman studies, and Dravidian art center. Their kings had great wealth and power, and during the reign of Krishnadeva Raya the empire had dealings with many Asian and European countries. In a great battle of Talikota in 1565, however, Moslem forces completely demolished the capital city and, in essence, destroyed the empire. By 1500 most of India had submitted to Moslem rule.

Incidentally, syphilis had reached India by 1498. (Ref. 2, 3)

Ceylon was involved in active spice trade with China and the Arabs in this 15th century. The Portuguese had conquered some coastal areas and implanted the Catholic religion. (Ref. 4, 5) (Continue on page 811)

1 [275] FISHER, ROBERT E., "The Stone Temples of Kashmir", Archaeology 35, No. 4: 47-53, July/ Aug. 1982.

2 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

3 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

4 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

5 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

The Indian Subcontinent: A.D. 1501 to 1600

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT (See Map in section on INDIA, 18th century)

Two separate powers continued to exist in India. In the north Babur, a Turkish chieftain, 5th in line from Timur, entered India in 1523 from Afghanistan with artillery and only the Rajputs organized to resist. After the battle of Panipat in 1526 he became the Mogul ruler who made Delhi equal to a Medicean Rome. Agricultural activity increased greatly with land-clearing, irrigation projects and new industrial crops such as indigo, sugar cane, cotton and mulberry trees for silk-worms. Silver coins appeared in this century as rupees, although affecting only the upper level of economic life. Actually India was one of the countries that in effect helped to hoard the silver from American mines. It was this American silver which fed the countless mintings and reminting of coins. (Ref. 1) The less fortunate used copper coins and bitter almonds as money. The gold coins used in the reign of Akbar were seldom seen. Even more than in Europe, fairs were a part of every day life, almost always combined with the endless pilgrimages. Barter was often more common than the use of money, except in the large fairs on the Ganges. Each religion had its own fairs; the Hindus at Hardwar and Benares; the Sikhs at Amritsar; the Muslims at Pakpattan. (Ref. 2, 3)

After Babur's death, the Afghans were expelled from India by Sher Shah and it took a new full scale invasion by Babur's grandson Akbar to restore the Mogul rule over all Hindustan except for Mewar. The Mogul emperors regularly had relays of horsemen from the Hindu Kush bring their fruit-flavored sherbets or water ices to Delhi. Persian horses were brought in by fleets and sometimes sold for 20 times the value of a slave. With no barley or hay, the horses were fed on a type of large pea, crushed and then soaked. (Ref. 4) Akbar was the greatest and most beneficial of all the Mogul rulers and overall they were the best of the foreign dynasties that had ruled India. Akbar used the Persian language in his court and had Hindu literature translated into that tongue. He encouraged all religions - Moslem, Brahman, Buddhist, Christian, Zorastrian and Jains and finally tried to promulgate a new one, including some of the features of all and called this Din lahi. It did not succeed and throughout the Mogul period it was basically the Moslem faith that was in competition with Hinduism and the greatest barrier to Hindu-Moslem understanding was not metaphysical, but social. The five original castes of the Hindus had subdivided through the centuries into almost 5,000 sub-castes, a system that the original Aryan founders had developed to perpetuate the enslavement of the original dark-skinned Dravidian peoples, who became the "Untouchables". Islam 's mosques drew millions of converts, and the vast majority were those Untouchables seeking release from the hopelessness of their place in the Hindu hierarchy.

The Moslem upper classes -many of them descendants of the Mogul (Turkish) invaders, tended to be landlords and soldiers, but the Moslem masses usually continued to be landless peasants in the service of others. There were no "great families" in Delhi. The Great Mogul appointed lords for life, only, but did not continue such grants for their children. Thus there was no feudalism and perhaps accordingly no precursor for capitalism. (Ref. 5) Muslim food became popular, particularly the addiction to sweets. Our word "candy" is derived from an Arabic word for "sugar". (Ref. 6, 7) Great famines occurred in 1555 and 1596 in northwest India and there were even reports of cannibalism. (Ref. 8)

Sikhism was developed at the warring frontier of the Punjab from the impact of monotheistic Islam on polytheistic Hinduism. It was founded by an Hindu guru trying to reconcile the two faiths, using ideas favored by the Moguls. Hounded by the Mogul cruelty, however, Nanak, the 10th guru of Sikhism, converted the new religion into a fighting faith and from that time on every Sikh's name ended with Singh, meaning "lion" and every one had to follow the law of the five K's: (1) Kesh - let beards grow. (2) Khangha - keep a steel comb in uncut hair. (3) Kucha - wear shorts for warrior's mobility. (4) Kara - wear steel bangle on right wrist. (5) Kirpan - go with a sword.

All were advised to ref rain from smoking, drinking alcohol, uniting with Moslem women and eating meat which had been slaughtered by Moslems, i.e. by cutting throats. Their most sacred site was the Golden Temple which sheltered their Holy Book, the Granth Sahib, at their capital at Amritsar. (Ref. 9)

In the south, the Empire Vijayanger, with the capital city of the same name, remained prosperous under a great King Krishna deva Raya. The city occupied an area of 60 square miles in circumference. Contrary to the situation in the north, gold coins were the major currency in the Deccan and at lower levels silver and copper were used along with sea shell money. India had no gold of its own, however, and the money came from the West for Indian merchandise. A great textile business had developed in Guijerat and there was an enormous burst of industrialism there in this 16th century. (Ref. 10) Buddhism had lost its hold in the south and a form of Brahmanism that honored Vishnu had become the faith of the people and the cow became holy. In 1565 the Vijayanager Empire fell in a day in the battle of Talikota to a coalition of Moslems, chiefly from Iran and Turkistan.

Despite the political eclipse of Hinduism by the Moslem conquerors, the overwhelming majority of the natives remained faithful to their ancient religion and considered Moslems as simply another caste. Hindu high culture, however, was impoverished and construction of Hindu temples came to a halt. The use of vernacular tongues for Hindu literature was promoted by the poet Sur Das and a new religious fervor was developed in Bengal as the holy man, Chaitanya, began to be considered God incarnate, a reincarnation of Vishnu. (Ref. 11)

It should be noted that in the interior of India, where water transportation was not available, imperial consolidation was most difficult because of the problem of obtaining cannon at battle sites. Babur attempted to cast cannon on the spot and at the end of the century Akbar hauled some overland and - thus both obtained large areas of domination. (Ref. 12)

The Portuguese began their conquests in India with a sea battle off the port of Diu in 1509 and the superiority of their long range weapons, accurate up to 200 yards, pre- vented the Moslem fleet's "board and fight" technique and led to easy victory. By 1537 the Portuguese had established trading posts on the Hooghly River, off the Bay of Bengal. The Hooghly is a secondary branch of the Ganges, going to the sea, although it is still "Mother Ganges" to the Hindus. The larger Ganges branch, the Padma, goes eastward into west Bengal. (Ref. 13) The East India Trading Company, as we noted previously, was founded in London September 24, 1599 with an initial capital of 72,000 British pounds and 125 shareholders. It was formed to compete against Dutch privateers who controlled the spice trade. Eight months later, in August of 1600, the 500 ton galleon Hector dropped anchor just north of Bombay and its Captain William Hawkins set off to explore the interior where he finally met Emperor Jehangir, the world's richest monarch and the fourth of the great Moguls. (Ref. 14)

Sri Lanka did not escape the Portuguese, who landed in 1505 and who soon controlled most of the island and its spice trade, giving it the name "Ceilao". Only the mountain kingdom of Kandy escaped them. (Ref. 15, 16) (Continue on page 902)

1 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

2 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

3 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

4 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

5 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

6 [37] COLLINS, LARRY and LAPRERRE, DOMINIQUE, Freedom at Midnight. (Simon & Schuster, New York, 1975).

7 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

8 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

9 [37] COLLINS, Larry and LAPRERRE, DOMINIQUE, Freedom at Midnight. (Simon & Schuster, New York, 1975).

10 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

11 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

12 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

13 [172] PUTMAN, JOHN J., "Down the Teeming Ganges, Holy River of India, Great Religions of the World. (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

14 [37] COLLINS, LARRY and LAPRERRE, DOMINIQUE, Freedom at Midnight. (Simon & Schuster, New York, 1975).

15 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

16 [108]. JORDON, ROBERT Paul. "Sri Lanka", National Geographic 155: 123, Jan. 1979.

The Indian Subcontinent: A.D. 1601 to 1700

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT (See map, this section in next chapter)

The sons of Akbar inherited his empire but not all of his qualities. Jehangir1, who ruled first, was an able degenerate of great cruelty with a harem of 6,000 women. His brother Jehan followed with a return to the Moslem faith and persecution of all others. His fame is in the Taj-Mahal, built in memory of his wife, Mumtaz. Actually India was then at a zenith of prosperity and prestige, in spite of one of the worst famines in history occurring in 1630-31, with hundreds of thousands dying and the countryside stinking with abandoned corpses. Human flesh was sold in open market. (Ref. 1) Copper began to run out, in spite of some imports from China and Japan, so that copper coinage began to slow down and silver came to the fore. Cowries were also again brought into common use to replace copper paysahs. (Ref. 2)

In the far north in the Pun jab the Sikhs had sought to reconcile the Moslem and Hindu faiths in a higher revelation, and their canon of religious writings was officially closed in 1604. Soon thereafter the Sikh leaders fell afoul of the Mogul authorities and the community took to arms, battling the Moguls throughout the remainder of the century. In 1699 the Guru Gobind Singh made the Granth, scriptures from writings of Hindu, Moslem and Sikh holy men, the official symbolic guru of Sikhism. (Ref. 4)

To regress for a moment, early in the century the Turkish Moguls extended their empire throughout southwestern India, including Sind, Rajputana and Gujerat, so that only the southeastern part of the peninsula remained independent as the Deccan Sultanate. Even this fell almost entirely to the Moguls as the century progressed. But these southern con- quests brought them into confrontation with a new Hindu power, the Marathas, who had established an independent kingdom on the Kondan coast beginning in 1627 under Sivaji (also Shivaji) the greatest Hindu warrior hero. (Ref. 5, 6) Sivaji opened a guerilla campaign against the Emperor Aurangzeb (1658-1707), Jehan's son, a pious Moslem, who despite his despotism, subtle diplomacy and peculiar morals was the least cruel of the Moguls2.

He warred against the Hindu religion and art and although worshipped as a saint by the Moslems, his religious zeal wrecked his dynasty and his country. Famine killed 3 million in Bengal in 1669, although in other years it was the one area of India which could export rice. (Ref. 8, 9) As in China and black Africa, human labor was widely used. When Aurangzeb made a journey to Kashmir, his loaded camels were relieved on the first slopes of the Himalayas by 15,000 to 20,000 porters. Royal orders were carried, as in Persia, by running men, relieved about every 6 miles, the teams covering a total of 30 to 60 miles a day. It is interesting that several hundred thousand people followed Aurangzeb to Kashmir, as Delhi was almost "shut-down" in the absence of the Great Mogul and his court. (Ref. 10)

Although it is well known that cattle are considered sacred and left running free in much of India, in the 17th century many were harnessed to plows and carriages and even ridden by soldiers and nobles. The Mouris caste sometimes had enormous convoys of up to 10,000 animals transporting grain and rice. India had many highly skilled workers, particularly in the textile industries, even though they did not develop the high quality tools that were used in Europe. (Ref. 11, 12)

By 1700, as the Mogul administration was in decay, the Marathas were ravaging the Deccan and eastern provinces and previous Mogul allies such as Rajputs, Sikhs, Jats and Satnamis were all revolting. In the meantime Portuguese influence on the coast shrank both in territory and cornmercial profit, but Dutch, English, French and Danish companies were all eager to set up coastal trading centers to export textiles, sugar, indigo and salt petre. (Ref. 13) Near Portuguese Goa, because of a shortage of wood, houses were small and made of straw and most had no fireplace or windows. The furniture consisted of a few rush mats. (Ref. 14) Nevertheless, every urban center in India had its money-changing bankers - the sarafs, who mostly belonged to the powerful trading caste of the Banyans. Although there were no large stock exchanges as in Europe, still there were bills of exchange, currency exchange, credit and maritime insuranCe and the Banyans acted as brokers and middle men for all the European activities. Not surprisingly the Fuggers and the Welsers of Augsburg were also well represented in India, with their joint representative, Ferdinand Cron, operating out of Cochin and then Goa. He amassed a personal fortune by 1619 working with Spanish and Portuguese, although the latter finally imprisoned him. (Ref. 15)

The French East India company, founded in 1664, never did well, perhaps because of a lack of means and the general immaturity of French capitalism. Surat, on the Gulf of Cambay, progressively became more and more of a boom city as the century progressed. First the English had a trading post there in 1609, then the Dutch in 1616 and the French in 1665, with lavish equipment. In 1652 Surat was already as large as Lyons, with a population perhaps approaching a million, acting as the gateway to the Mogul Empire. The Banyans were the most important group of intermediaries. (Ref. 16) Calcutta was founded by the British East India Company on the Hooghly River in 1690 by absorbing three villages, one of which was called Kalikata, honoring the goddess Kali, which may have given Calcutta its name. (Ref. 17)

Heirs of Sivaji, the peshwas, were a tight clique of Chitpawan (purified by fire) Brahmans, who continued to resist British rule in the south. (Ref. 18) The poet, Tulsi Das, translated material into Hindu from the Ramayana, elaborating on the divine incarnation, Rama. This was widely popular and of enormous importance for later moral and religious education. This popular movement, along with that of Chaitanya and Sin Das, helped protect Hinduism from the charms of Islam. (Ref. 19)

The Dutch arrived on Sri Lanka in 1658, changing the name again to "Ceilon". Life was hard there and it has been reported that rice cooked in water with a little salt, some green leaves and lemon juice passed for a good meal. There were no markets on the island but there were shops. (Ref. 20, 21).

1 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

2 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

3 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

4 [25] CHAKRAVARTY, AMIYA, "Hinduism". Great Religions of the World, (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

5 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

6 [37] COLLINS, Larry and LAPRERRE, DOMINIQUE, Freedom at Midnight. (Simon & Schuster, New York, 1975).

7 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

8 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

9 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

10 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

11 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

12 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

13 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

14 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

15 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

16 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

17 [172] PUTMAN, JOHN J., "Down the Teeming Ganges, Holy River of India, Great Religions of the World. (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

18 [37] COLLINS, Larry and LAPRERRE, DOMINIQUE, Freedom at Midnight. (Simon & Schuster, New York, 1975).

19 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

20 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

21 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

1 The name means "Conqueror of the World". (Ref. 3), page 211

2.  When Jehan had fallen ill, Aurangzeb had killed his 3 older brothers, imprisoned his sick father and seized the throne. (Ref. 7)

The Indian Subcontinent: A.D. 1701 to 1800

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

Shortly after Aurangzeb's death in 1707, many of the provinces became essentially independent. The Peshwas, officially the chief ministers of Sivaji's house, presided over a confederacy of Maratha chiefs representing the Sindhias, Gaikwars, Holkars and Bhonslas. (Ref. 1) In addition, as the Mogul Empire went into decay, it was subject to many raids from the outside. Nadir Shah, the Turcoman ruler of Afghanistan and part of Persia raided to Delhi, where he almost destroyed the city. At about the same time the British, French, Portuguese, and French moved in from the coasts. This is not to imply that the Europeans immediately conquered all. In 1722 combined English and Portuguese forces suffered an humiliating defeat at the hands of Kanoji Angria and in 1739 the Dutch were routed when they tried to land in the Kingdom of Travancore. Yet, after 1730 the trading balance began to shift as European shipping greatly increased, with more cargoes of goods and silver. The Westerners established their own trading networks, which in turn hastened the end of the great Mogul's Empire. (Ref. 2) India and the Far East, whose industries were as advanced as Europe's, only wanted silver - not goods - in exchange for their tea, cotton, and silk. England alone spent 30,000,000 pounds in silver between 1733 and 1766 to cover her purchases in India and the East. (Ref. 3) In the early years much of that involved the printed "calico" cotton fabrics, but after the Industrial Revolution the English made those themselves and ruined the Indian weavers. (Ref. 4) The same occurred with France, where authorities for a long time tried desperately to protect their local manufacturers from the invasion of those light fabrics from India, even levying fines and harsh punishments to those who bought or sold them. After 1759 such bans were lifted as the French established their own cotton industries.

We dealt with the money-changing bankers of India, the Sarafs, in the last chapter. Belonging chiefly to the powerful trading caste of the Banyans, these men organized an extensive commercial organization. A trader could borrow money in one city, pay back in another where he transferred the debt to a third place by borrowing again and so on. Exchange fees resembled interest, sometimes at a staggering rate, but they allowed merchants to operate as far away as Java or southern China. The Banyan bankers themselves were present in large numbers in Isfahan, Istanbul and Moscow. At home one of the commercial and shipping centers was Surat. Sometimes one merchant alone would send out 20 ships a year, each from 300 to 800 tons and carrying up to 25,000 pounds of his own merchandise. (Ref. 5)

Map taken from Reference y/.

With the collapse of the Moguls, the Sikhs had a chance to make a kingdom of their own in the Punjab, but as warriors they lost some of their religious and philosophical goals. According to Moslem accounts, the Sikh rule was one which defiled mosques, outraged women, defiled tombs, and butchered Moslems of either sex by various horrible means. (Ref. 6) They were kept somewhat in check, however, by the invading Afghans from the north, who were led by Ahmed Shah Durani (1747-1793), who developed a short-lived empire from the Aral Sea to well into India. The hopes of the Marathas to succeed the Moguls were dashed at the Third Battle of Panipat in 1761 when the Afghan Ahmad Shah Abdali decisively defeated the Peshwas' forces. This permanently weakened the Hindu armies and left India far more vulnerable than before to later English encroachment. (Ref. 7, 8)

In the Deccan the Nizam of Hyderbad was a Muslim viceroy established in the 1720s, independent of Delhi. It was a dynasty which remained the most important Muslim ruling house in India up to 1948. (Ref. 9) Bengal was the third great province to become independent and in 1756 the Bengalese even temporarily drove out the British. A side light of that conflict was the infamous "Black Hole of Calcutta" incident. As the Nabob of Bengal sacked Calcutta, 146 Englishmen were forced into a guard room measuring 18' by 14'10", with only two small windows for ventilation. On the following morning only 23 men were still alive. (Ref. 10) The East India Trading Company inevitably became embroiled in local politics and squabbles and felt that they should intervene. On June 23, 1757 Robert Clive, leading about 900 Englishmen and 2,000 Indian sepoys (native infantrymen), trained and equipped according to European methods and with 10 f ield guns, routed a Nabob's army of some 50,000 outside a Bengali village of Plassey and opened the gates of north India to the British. (Ref. 11)

Incident to the War of the Austrian Succession in Europe, French and English trading companies were in armed conf lict on the eastern coast of India. Actually the European contingents of each were very small, but they dominated the battlefields containing hordes of local mercenaries because of their superior weaponry and obedience on the field. When the treaty of 1763 was signed, France was run out of India. Thereafter, in addition to Bengal, most of the eastern coast (northern Sarkars) was secured from the Nizam by 1768.

By the year 1700 there were about 1,500 Englishmen in India, but by the end of the 18th century the British Indian Empire had increased to thousands of British officials and soldiers under a British governor-general. The English in India tended to excessive drinking and eating. In 1756 one contingent of 848 men lost 87 from liver damage from alcoholism. (Ref. 12) On the other side of the coin, 10,000,000 Indians died in 1768 in the great famine of Bengal, the worst in the world's history.

After Clive, the East India Company was run by Warren Hastings and the Company taxed the land for 50% of the produce and made additional special levies. Enormous British fortunes were made, while, according to some writers at least, 30,000,000 humans were reduced to the extremity of wretchedness in a terrible tyranny. (Ref. 13) Winston Churchill (Ref. 14), of course, has a different version, stating that since Hastings got no financial help from England he had to raise money from the wealthy Bengali to rescue Bombay and the Carnatic (southern tip of India on the east) and to stop the bloodshed which was once more engulfing Bengal from the Mahrattas. He says that Hasting left India in 1785 "-not without the gratitude of the inhabitants." Hastings had initiated some reforms, including a simplification of Indian coinage and government control of salt and opium production. (Ref. 15) He was finally charged with misconduct and brought home to stand a seven year trial in England in which he was acquitted of all charges.

Other developments on the Indian subcontinent in this century include the invasion of Nepal by Chinese armies marching from Tibet in 1792, at which time the Gurkha tribesmen were forced to recognize Chinese suzerainty. The British took over most of Ceylon in 1795 and 1796 and began the importation of great numbers of Tamil laborers, the results of which are still upsetting Sinhalese politics. Coffee rust appeared first in Ceylon and soon spread throughout Southeast Asia, forcing a change of crop to tea and rubber. (Ref. 16, 17, 18) (Continue on page 1110)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

3 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

4 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

5 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

6 [37] COLLINS, Larry and LAPRERRE, DOMINIQUE, Freedom at Midnight. (Simon & Schuster, New York, 1975).

7 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

8 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

9 [68] GARRATY, JOHN a. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

10 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

11 [37] COLLINS, Larry and LAPRERRE, DOMINIQUE, Freedom at Midnight. (Simon & Schuster, New York, 1975).

12 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

13 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

14 [31] CHURCHILL, WINSTON, Ibid., Volume III - The Age of Revolution.

15 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

16 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

17 [108] JORDON, ROBERT Paul. "Sri Lanka", National Geographic 155: 123, Jan. 1979.

18 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

The Indian Subcontinent: A.D. 1801 to 1900

THE INDIAN SUBCONTINENT

India's history shows a tendency of any strong government, particularly those in the Gengetic plain, to expand and the British Bengal government-of about 1800 followed this pattern under Governor Lord Richard Colley Wellesley1. Some territories were annexed outright; others were brought under control through a system of subsidiary alliances. The Marathas were finally crushed by the British in 1818 and all prospects of a powerful Hindu state and culture disappeared. Until 1835 the British continued to use the Mogul language of administration (that is, Persian) and in that way the Mogul Empire survived, at least in name, until 1858.

The use of legislation to institute social change began during the governor-generalship of Lord William Bentinck (1828-1835). Laws included the forbidding of suttee, as well as female infanticide, slavery and human sacrifice. Other changes included support of higher education institutions that used the English language. This was seen as a means of introducing a true understanding of the world and it was endorsed by such Indians as Ram Mohan Roy, also called Rammohun. He was a most distinguished Indian radical, at- tempting reform in Hindu customs and religion. In a sense he was an isolated forerunner of the anglicized upper class Indian, who subsequently became so important in Indian history. His influence helped to stimulate reform of Hindu laws and institutions. (Ref. 1, 2, 3)

Some regions of India deserve special attention. The Punjab in northwest India was

1/2 the size of France and was called the "Country of five rivers". It had been ruled through the centuries by Persians, Macedonians, Mauryas, Scythians, Parthians, Huns and then the caliphs of Islam. The indigent people were the Sikhs, who recaptured the area from the Moguls. It was the granary of India, a feat made possible by an immense network of irrigation canals, which were early built by the British. In this century there were some 15,000,000 Hindus, 16,000 Moslems, and 5,000,000 Sikhs, living in about 18,000 towns. The language was Urdu. Before collapsing in 1849 the Sikhs gave the British red-coats their worst defeat on the Indian subcontinent at Chilleanwala.

In contrast to the figures just given, the State of Bengal at the mouth of the Ganges, contained 35,000,000 Moslems and 30,000,000 Hindus, overall more people than in Great Britain, including Ireland. In spite of the religious divisions, all Bengali spoke the same language and came from the same racial stock, dating back to the pre-Christian era. The Moslems seemed to migrate to the east while the Hindus congregated in the west. The east grew almost no food at all, just jute, while the west grew enough rice for both.

To escape the dust and heat of the Indian summer, the ruling British established a summer retreat at the base of the Himalyas at Simla, a miniature Sussex hamlet, characterizing the complete separation of the ruling British from their subjects. Only three carriages were allowed in the entire community and the standard conveyance was a rickshaw requiring four coolies, almost all of which had tuberculosis. Indians were not even allowed to walk on the mall. (Ref. 4) Through various pressures, political unification was pretty well obtained and a modern state created by about 1855. The first steam vessel had arrived in 1826. By 1855 there were 2,500 miles of telegraph lines. Some generalizations of the impact of western rule are that trade and commerce responded to new conditions better than industry and that the creation of a market economy was important in political unification. Industry tended to remain in small enclaves entirely under western control, but through the century India had a favorable balance of payments because of the sale of jute, hides, oilseeds and wheat.

The British had a professional army of never more than 200,000 men and 2/3 of them were native Indians. Native revolts against the spreading East Indian Company, particularly the Sepoy mutiny of 1857, forced the British government to take over actual control of the country. This famous Sepoy revolt had to do with the new Enfield rifle which was issued along with cartridges, which were coated with grease. The cartridge had to be bitten open before loading and the Indian Sepoys (many of high Brahmin Hindu caste) thought that biting fat of the sacred cow would throw them back down through many life times of struggle to get back up to their present level in the cycle of rebirth, while the Muslims in the units felt that if the fat were of the unclean pig, the situation was intolerable. The mutiny of the troops started at Meerut in the far north of Rajputana and resulted in 14 months of bitter fighting. Sikh loyalty to the British in the Punjab and indifference in the Deccan and south, turned the tide eventually in favour of the British. The most important consequence of all this was an abrupt change in the British management of India.

The East India Company was terminated by royal decree on August 12, 1858 and the British crown (Queen Victoria) took over. Ultimate~y 2,000 members of the Indian Civil Service and 10,000 British officers had authority over the 300,000,000 Indian people, helped only by 60,000 British regular soldiers and 200,000 native troops. The English, after fighting 111 wars in India, using Indian money and troops, completed the conquest of that land and then, with peace obtained, did establish railways, factories and schools as a token reward for their financial despotism.

There has been much criticism of British imperialism in India, but some of it has certainly been unjust. Although the British East India Company may have taken much wealth from India, there was plenty left for the 565 princes or maharajas of the same number of states which remained more or less self-governing under British jurisdiction. Those princes had an average of 5, 8 wives, 12 to 16 children, 9.2 elephants, 2.8 private railway cars, 3.4 Rolls-Royces and 22.9 tigers killed. Most had tremendous wealth in gold, silver and fabulous jewels, even if their subjects might be starving. The Sikh Maharaja of Pateala had a pearl necklace later insured by Lloyds of London for $1,000,000, but his most intriguing item was a diamond breastplate composed of 1,000 brilliantly matched blue-white diamonds. The Maharaja of Baroda went about on an elephant with all the animal's equipment, such as the howdah, harness and great saddle cloth, made of gold, with 10 gold chains hung from each huge ear, each chain worth $60,000. (Ref. 5, 6, 7, 8)

Throughout the century the Indian army fought almost incessantly along the passes and peaks of the frontier with Afghanistan, at Landi Kotal and up and down the Kyber.

The enemy was cruel, Pathans like the Wazirs and Mahsuds, who finished off wounded prisoners with knives. Famine occurred through most of India in 1866 and again in 1877 and then periodically until 1899, although commercial agriculture flourished. When another episode of plague arrived in Bombay in 1898, within 10 years some 6,000,000 persons had died of it2. The first all Indian political organization was founded in 1885 as the Indian National Congress and it soon developed an extremist wing, which began to question the aliens' right to rule India. This organization dominated Indian political and social thinking in the next century. Mahatma Gandhi was born in 1869. The Lancashire cotton famine in Britain, generated by the American Civil War, led to a cotton boom in the Deccan and thus to the development of regional crop patterns in India. Nepal got potatoes from America and this soon became the staple food of the Sherpas. (Ref. 9, 10, 11, 12)

Map taken from Reference 97

At the end of the century India was the second largest nation on earth with about five times as many Hindus as Moslems, several million Sikhs and about the same number of Christians, a few Parsis and still fewer Jews. The observation of the occasional contrast between Christian principles and the actual practice of Christians, left India skeptical and satirical and Christianity has converted only 6% of the Indian people in 300 years, as the Hindu religion has remained supreme. There were 15 official languages and 845 dialects. There was a leper population the size of Switzerland and enough beggars to populate Holland. Cholera was endemic but became general and violent throughout this century and even spread to Europe. A virulent form of tuberculosis had developed in the previous century and continued to ravage in this one. (Ref. 14) There were still some many million aborigines, some like the Nagas of the far east Nagaland next to Burma, who still hunted heads until the middle of the 20th century. In the l9th century probably as many as 3,000,000 Indians migrated to other countries along the shores of the Indian Ocean, but they did not fuse well with local peoples and in the next century many had returned home. (Ref. 15, 16, 17, 18, 19)

After the 1830s there was a large migration of Indian Tamils to Sri Lanka to labor on the coffee, tea and rubber plantations. They joined other Tamils whose Dravidian ancestors had arrived centuries before from the south of India. Most practiced Hinduism, in contrast to the majority Sinhalese of the island, who were Buddhists. The Tamils prospered under the British rule during the l9th century, but today, in the late 20th century, many are being deported back to India. (Ref. 20, 21)

1 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

2 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

3 [37] COLLINS, Larry and LAPRERRE, DOMINIQUE, Freedom at Midnight. (Simon & Schuster, New York, 1975).

4 [37] COLLINS, Larry and LAPRERRE, DOMINIQUE, Freedom at Midnight. (Simon & Schuster, New York, 1975).

5 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

6 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

7 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

8 [37] COLLINS, Larry and LAPRERRE, DOMINIQUE, Freedom at Midnight. (Simon & Schuster, New York, 1975).

9 [37] COLLINS, Larry and LAPRERRE, DOMINIQUE, Freedom at Midnight. (Simon & Schuster, New York, 1975).

10 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

11 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

12 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

13 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

14 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

15 [37] COLLINS, Larry and LAPRERRE, DOMINIQUE, Freedom at Midnight. (Simon & Schuster, New York, 1975).

16 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

17 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

18 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

19 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

20 [108] JORDON, ROBERT Paul. "Sri Lanka", National Geographic 155: 123, Jan. 1979.

21 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

1.  Brother of the Duke of Wellington, who was Arthur Wellesley

2.  Calcutta had suffered a cholera epidemic in 1817 and the disease spread overland with British troops to the northern borders, Afghanistan and Nepal. Previously this disease had been confined to Hindu pilgrimages along the Ganges. (Ref. 13)

The Far East: Beginning to 8000 B.C.

THE FAR EAST

The famous "Peking Man", unearthed in northern China, lived some 500,000 years ago and his use of fire allowed him to live north of the frost line. He appeared to have a brain capable of speech, an erect posture and was a hunter and nut-gatherer. He was an intermediary stage of early man, evolved beyond Homo habilis who had spread across Eurasia and Africa, and was definitely related to the Java man (Pithecanthropus robustus). Both have shovel-shaped incisors, a characteristic of the modern Mongoloid race. After this early interglacial period, north China had a series of evolutionary changes with Neanderthal-like types and the fully matured Mongoloid Homo sapiens appearing perhaps 20,000 years ago. In the latter part of this period, parts of south China were occupied by pro-humans with some Negroid racial characteristics. All East Asian stone age people used a distinctive chop- ping tool that differed from the technology of prehistoric Europe and Africa. Does this mean a multiple origin of present day mankind?

About 12,000 years ago China progressed to ceramics and the beginnings of agriculture. This Yang-shao Culture is represented in more than 1,000 excavated sites in Honan and Kansu provinces, with hand-molded red, black and gray pottery painted with pigments. A hunting culture existed in central China at that time.

At 20,000 B.C. there were land bridges from China to Korea and from Korea to the southern tip of Japan and people could go freely across these areas. The first people to arrive in Japan, however, did so some 100,000 years ago and were pre-Mongolian Asiatics, similar to the aborigines of Australia today. They were wandering hunters with pale complexions and heavy beards of varying colors and degrees of curliness. For the next 90,000 years, during the last of the Ice Ages, Japan was usually linked to the Asiatic mainland by the land bridges and island chains, so that Hokkaido was accessible to Siberia and Kyushu was accessible to Taiwan and Southeast Asia. With the melting of the glaciers some 10,000 years ago, Japan was cut off from the mainland and there were two surviving cultures, each with its own language - a Siberian one in the north, surviving today as Ainu, a distant relative of some tongue of the Siberian tundra, and the southern language, which has developed into modern Japanese. In the latter, some of the more ancient and basic words such as those for "mother", "father", etc., bear some slight resemblance to some Polynesian dialects and to some words of certain hill tribes of Malaya.

Pottery found in Fukin Cave, Kyushu, Japan has a radio-carbon dating of about 129700 B.C. and is considered to be the earliest in the world. The Jomon Period of Japan, with a hunting, fishing and gathering economy and the use of pottery but not metal, started about 12,000 B.C. and continued for the next 8,000 years. In this era Japan seems to have been isolated from China and had more in common with the Pacific Islands.

Java man, whose remains were found in the Brantas Valley of Java by Eugene Dubois, a Dutch doctor, in 1891, has been dated to 400, 000 B.C., and appears to be related to Peking man in China and has the same Mongoloid, shovel-shaped incisor teeth. Some 20,000 years ago there were land bridges all about the Malayan peninsula, through Sumatra, Java and Borneo and connecting all to the regions of present Cambodia and Vietnam, making the huge subcontinent called the Sunda Shelf. The people may have been the ancestors of present-day Negritos still occupying some remote regions of this area. Most were hunters, some lived in caves, and there were cultivated foods in Thailand as early as 10,000 B.C. There have been carbon datings of 9,750 B.C. of seeds of peas, beans, cucumbers and water chestnuts of the size and shape suggesting actual cultivation. If true, this was some 2,000 years before true agriculture can be proved in the Near East or Central America. About 250,000 years ago people may have walked across the then existing land bridge from the Malaysian peninsula and the Asian mainland to the Philippine Islands. The men there may have been akin to the Java and Peking men. Cave finds west of Mindanao show crude tools of 50,000 B.C. and in some areas there are better tools dating to 20,000 B.C. (Ref. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7)1

1 Spirit Cave excavations have shown a variety of game - deer, pigs, monkeys, bamboo rats, otters, flying squirrels and from the sea - carp and crabs. Nuts, beans and melons were also available. (Ref. 8)

1 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

2 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

3 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

4 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

5 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

6 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

7 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

8 [297] PFEIFFER, JOHN, "At Ban Chiang a lost civilization comes to light", Smithsonian, Jan. 1933, pp. 98-107.

The Far East: 8000 to 5000 B.C.

THE FAR EAST

While there were probably many people in the Far East at this period, most remained in the Mesolithic stage. The Yang-shao painted pottery culture people of China lived in small villages of perhaps one hundred cottages, growing millet, keeping dogs and pigs and hunting with bows and arrows. They buried their dead and practiced fertility rites. Japan had the Jomon Culture, date of origin uncertain. The British Museum Guide lists it from 7,000 B.C. on but others believe it existed even at 8,000 B.C. or before. It was a distinct hunting, gathering and fishing society with a low-fired hand made pottery sometimes impressed with patterns made by twisted rope. The word "Jomon" means "rope patterns". There is some evidence that the people of this society were not the ancestors of the present day Japanese, but rather those of the Ainu, now pushed into the northern fringes of the islands by the later immigrants. The Jomon Culture was related to the southeast China traditions and to those of the Soviet Maritime Province and Kamchataka, but is not related to the Yang-shao (Ref. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6)1

1C. (Ref. 7)

In Southeast Asia people cultivated rice as early as 6,000 B.C. with evidence found in Spirit Cave in northern Siam. Mesolithic cultures have been identified in Vietnam, Siam and Malaya, with early cave sites excavated in Sumatra, Borneo and Cambodia. In Thailand, by 6,000 B.C., people used a wide variety of foods, with many of the plants domesticated. These included almonds, broad beans, betel nuts, cucumbers, peas, water chestnuts and gourds, as well as rice. There was widespread distribution of mankind in New Guinea by 8,000 B.C. with a flake tool-chopper stone industry. Although some were already there by 6,000 B.C. more people began arriving in the Philippines by sea from Indonesia, Malaysia, Indochina and the Arab world. (Ref. 8, 9)

1 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

2 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

3 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

4 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

5 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

6 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

7 [297] PFEIFFER, John, "At Ban Chiang a lost civilization comes to light", Smithsonian, Jan. 1933, pp. 98-107.

8 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

9 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

The Far East: 5000 to 3000 B.C.

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA

There was a Neolithic Yang-Shao culture in both central and western China with domesticated animals and cultivated millet, which reached a peak about 3,000 B.C. The Chinese are not a homogeneous people, and represent a medley of human varieties, different in origin, language, character, customs and government. The earliest Chinese city was Liang Ch'eng of the Lung-Shan Culture, dating to about 3,500 B.C. The inhabitants had great technical skill and a high level of organization and ritual. Prior to that the ancestors of the present Chinese civilization were developing an agricultural community around 49000 B.C. in the loess covered highlands of north and northwestern China, where the well drained soil of the river terraces was ideal for the early crops. The Lung-Shan Culture appeared on the lowland north China plain and eventually spread over all of China proper except the southwest, but it had many regional variations. Overall it was characterized by wheel made, unpainted, black pottery with a burnished, lustrous surface. The people lived in walled communities on the river plains, almost from Manchuria to Vietnam. They had rice as well as millet, domesticated cattle and sheep. Their religion emphasized ancestor worship (Ref. 1, 2)1

1 Ritual ceramics were made with the potters' wheel and the artisans were beginning to temper their wares during firing. (Ref. 3)

JAPAN

Neolithic societies only.

KOREA

Neolithic societies only.

SOUTHEAST ASIA

There is evidence of a bronze industry in Thailand by 3,600 B.C. and probably the tin came from Malaysia, which remains today the world's greatest producer of that metal. Wild rice was cultivated at Non Nok Tha, Thailand, by 3,500 B.C. Some excavations near the Loatian border at Ben Chieng show bronze weapons and wheels, carved ivory and pottery, all beautifully made. Sometime in this period Malayan people joined the first inhabitants of the Philippines and Madagascar. Hypothetically some of them could even have gone to Brazil around the south end of Africa (Ref. 4, 5, 6, 7, 8)2

29) describes a current exhibit at Ban Chiang, which has objects recently excavated from the Stone Age of 5000 B.C. to the Bronze Age, beginning at least by 3600 B.C. These excavations indicate settlement soon after 4000 B.C., with raised domestic stock and probably rudimentary rice cultivation. Unusual was the use of metals, not in an urban context, but in villages, in such things as spear points, axes and personal ornaments.  They had beautiful pottery from 3600 B.C. on, and the culture, overall, lasted about 4,000 years. John Pfeiffer (Ref. 10) confirms these findings and adds that 350 bronze bracelets, anklets, rings, axe and spear heads were distributed among about 2,000 other objects. The bronze seems to have appeared full blown without antecedent pure copper use. Whether this was brought in from the outside or developed locally is not known.

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

3 [314] SANGRAW, CLARENCE, "Treasures from Shanghai", Archaeology 361, No.3: 60-63, May/June, 1983.

4 [155] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Archeological Map of Middle America, Ibid. Oct. 1968.

5 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

6 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

7 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

8 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

9 [296] WHITE, JOYCE C. "Ban Chiang: Discovery of a Lost Bronze Age", Archaeology 36, No.1:52-55, Jan./Feb. 1983.

10 [297] PFEIFFER, JOHN, "At Ban Chiang a lost civilization comes to light", Smithsonian, Jan. 1933, pp. 98-107.

The Far East: 3000 to 1500 B.C.

CHINA AND MANCHURIA

Chinese legends are bountiful with alleged records at least back to 3,000 B.C., all of which are not easy to substantiate. Excavations in Chekany province in central southern China have revealed a Neolithic Culture, the Yang-Shao, which we have mentioned previously, with painted pottery, dating to about 3,000 BC. The more wide-spread Lung- Shan, black pottery culture peaked at about 2,000 B.C. The legends describe a number of great emperors who taught the people marriage, music, writing, painting, fishing with nets, domestication of animals and the feeding of silk worms. Tradition has it that Empress Si-Ling, wife of the great Huang-Ti, discovered silk about 2,640 B.C. Brick structures may have been erected about 2,600 B.C. along with observations for the study of stars and the construction of a correct calendar. Chinese medicine allegedly began with the legendary Fu Hsi in 2,953 B.C. followed by Shen Nung, the Red Emperor (Hung-Ti), who compiled the first medical herbal material, the Pen-Tsao, about 2,800 B.C. He supposedly personally tested 365 drugs and drew up the first acupuncture charts. More famous is the great medical compendium, the Nei Ching (Canon on Medicine) allegedly developed by Yu Hsiung, the Yellow Emperor (Huang Ti), about 2,600 B.C.. This was transmitted orally until probably the 3rd century B.C. and was still later revised in the 8th century of the Christian Era. The Nei Ching deals with all phases of health and illness, prevention as well as treatment, including acupuncture. Tea, which grows wild in Manchuria1, was cultivated there about 2,000 B.C. At first the Chinese merely chewed the leaf. (Ref. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6)

From the middle of the third millennium B.C. the heart of the Yellow River valley was densely populated. It took a large and disciplined force to drain and flood control this flood plain. A small type of pig was found in every hut and the ox-cart was known by 2,000 B.C. The horse and chariot came a little later with the horses similar to the wild Mongolian ponies with heavy heads and short legs. Foxtail millet and a small amount of wheat (spread from the west) were grown. Rice was cultivated much later, beginning south of the Yangzte2, a foreign land, wooded, marshy and peopled with nomads of a different race. The first truly urban, known civilization in China was the Shang Bronze Age Culture of 1,700 to 1,600 B.C.. Hucker (Ref. 7) says the Shang monarchy emerged from the Honan branch of the Lung-Shan, black pottery culture and perhaps began as early as 1,176 B.C. Recent excavations at Loyang and Chengchow demonstrate progressive development from Lung-Shan into the ever more mature Shang. There urban development was about 1,000 years later than that in Mesopotamia and about 500 years after that in the Indus valley, so some elements from the west undoubtedly diffused to China. The last twelve of the Shang kings lived 273 years (beginning about 1,395 B.C.) in the An-Yang area at Yin-hsu (the ruins of Yin). The entire dynasty is sometimes called "Yin" after this capital. The Shang cities were large and had a high order of bronze technology and horse-drawn chariots as well as a fully developed Chinese writing system and a culture dedicated to war against the outlying "barbarians". Their bows had a 160 pound pull and could kill at 200 yards, a weapon later used by the steppe nomads and known to the westerners as the Turkish compound bow. Although traditionally the Shang was described as controlling most of northern China, actually it was probably a loose confederation of clans. The Huang-Ho society, on the Yellow River, had an ideographic script about 1,500 B.C. Wherever it appeared, writing in China is generally admitted to be the result of diffusion from the west. (Ref. 8, 9, 10, 11, 12)1

1 They made silk and created baskets. This was before the Shang period. (Ref. 14)

JAPAN

Peopled with Neolithic societies.

KOREA

There is archeological evidence of people on this peninsula in a Neolithic society by 3,000 B.C. (Ref. 15)

SOUTHEAST ASIA

Most of this area had peasant farmers and hunting groups and we know that bronze was used very early in Thailand. Iron objects seem to have been made there about 1,600 B.C. or even earlier. This was "wrought" iron, made by heating ore only to about 1,083 degrees Centigrade and then hammering away the slag from the iron globules. (Ref. 16, 17)

Waves of Stone Age people colonized the Indonesian islands from the mainland. An Austronesian people using Lapita pottery appeared in the Moluccas area of Indonesia sometime in this period, and they began to migrate slowly eastward. From about 3,000 B.C. on, the Malays in the Philippines were joined by a more advanced race from Indonesia. These two peoples merged, building up a tribal system known as the barangay. (Ref. 18, 19)

1 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

2 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

3 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

4 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

5 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

6 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

7 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

8 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

9 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

10 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

11 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

12 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

13 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

14 [314] SANGRAW, CLARENCE, "Treasures from Shanghai", Archaeology 361, No.3: 60-63, May/June, 1983.

15 [113] KIM, h. EDWARDS, "Seoul: Korean Showcase", National Geographic 156: 770, Dec. 1979.

16 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

17 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

18 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

19 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

1. This tells something about the climate of Manchuria, in that tea cannot tolerate frost or drought

2. Trager (Ref. 13) says the rice was brought from the Mohenjo-daro civilization about 2,300 B.C., but the source of this information is not given

The Far East: 1500 to 1000 B.C.

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Shang Dynasty until about 1,122 B.C., then Chou)

About 1,500 B.C. China passed abruptly from the Neolithic state to a full bronze age, probably getting bronze-working technique from the Near East or Thailand, as the Chinese scholars claim. China received its first farm-yard poultry as the domesticated jungle fowl from the Malayan peninsula. (Ref. 1) The first historical dynasty, the Shang, as noted in the last chapter, was a powerful political regime controlling most of northern China, even though in actuality it was a loose confederation of clan domains, many little more than village settlements. Two of their six capitals, at Cheng-chou and An-Yang, have been excavated, the latter showing a Black Pottery Culture. The people were basically Chinese, but some think that the aristocratic, charioteer warrior leaders may have come from farther west in the steppes. They used compound bows and bronze weapons. Fortifications dating to 1,300 B.C. along the Yellow River have evidence of these same warrior bands who may have originated on the Iranian plateau and moved step by step from oasis to oasis, conquering the Neolithic societies in their way. This was an aristocratic age with a sharp cleavage between noble warriors and helpless peasants. A recent newspaper article reports that Chinese scientists have uncovered the remains of 1,000 slaves killed as human sacrifices near An-Yang. Supposedly these were sacrificed for funerals or to honor the ancestors of the nobility, all demonstrating the extreme cruelty and barbarity of the slave-owning nobility of this Shang Dynasty. The religion was a mixture of ancestor and nature worship and their script was ideographic and strictly Chinese. About 1,200 B.C. iron was used in its meteoric form and treated like a semi precious stone. It was of ten mounted in bronze fittings for ceremonial weapons. (Ref. 2, 3)

The concept of heaven dates to the beginning of this period, with the rulers traveling north to Mount T'ai where sacrifices were made, sacred music played and ceremonial dances accomplished. Shang-Ti (Lord on high), an anthropomorphic god, lived in heaven and watched over the actions of people and ruled the heaven of various spiritual beings who were considered to be ancestors. (Ref. 4)

In 1,122 B.C. or perhaps a little earlier, the Shang were overthrown by the Chou, a client people, possibly of different ethnic origin. Hucker (Ref. 5) says they were Chinese speaking people of Lung-Shan descent. The Chou, the Shang and the warrior charioteers mentioned above, all mixed, providing the biological prelude to the first true, historic civilization of the Far East. Toynbee (Ref. 6) calls this the original Sinic Society. Prior to the overthrow, the Shang had considered the Chou as semi-barbarians and "country cousins" but had finally conferred the title of "Chief of the West" on one of their leaders and had given him a Shang noblewoman as a wife. The Chou had probably early allied with and mixed with proto-Tibetan people called "Ch'iang", considered no better than animals at one time by the Shang. This idea of undermining Shang authority by making alliances with neighboring chief s was conceived by a definite historical figure, King Wen, and when his son, Wu, came to power as king of the Chou, he built a new capital, Hao, near what is now Sian. Legend says that he then accumulated 50,000 troops and in 1,122 B.C. overcame a Shang army of 700,000. Apparently many of the latter were unhappy with the last Shang king and actually joined the Chou. Tradition also gives King Wu's brother, the Duke of Chou, great credit for laying the groundwork for the long-lived Chou Dynasty as he established seventy-one new administrative units and built a new city at modern Loyang to serve as an auxiliary capital. (Ref. 7, 8)

JAPAN and KOREA

These areas were both still in a Neolithic stage with farmers and gatherers.

SOUTHEAST ASIA

There is archeological evidence of the Somrong-Sen Culture spreading throughout all of Indo-China, including present day Vietnam, Cambodia, Laos, etc. This was a full Neolithic culture, with early bronze activity apparent about 1,000 B.C. in northern Viet Nam. H.O. Beyer found in 1948 that tanged and rectangular adz blades were used in the northern Philippines between 1,750 and 1,250 B.C. and nowhere else in Indonesia or Melanesia. The interesting sequel is that these are almost identical with those used much later throughout Polynesia. The route of this adz and the people using it from the Philippines to Polynesia can only be explained in one way according to Thor Heyerdahl - up the Japanese Current to below the Aleutians to the North American coast and then back into the Pacific. (Please see the Pacific section) (Ref. 9, 10)

1 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

2 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

3 [235] WICHITA FALLS TIMES, Wichita Falls, Texas, Apr. 29, 1977.

4 [26] Chan, Wing-Tsit, "The Orderly Realm of Chinese Sages". Great Religions of the World. (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

5 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

6 [168] Pei, MARIO. The Story of Language. (Revised Edition). (J.P. Lippincott Co., Philadelphia & New York 1962.

7 [168] Pei, MARIO. The Story of Language. (Revised Edition). (J.P. Lippincott Co., Philadelphia & New York 1962.

8 [101]. HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

9 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

10 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

The Far East: 1000 to 700 B.C.

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (continued Chou Dynasty)

The leaders of the Chou Dynasty rewarded their aides by making them almost independent rulers of the many provinces into which the new realm was divided, thus setting the stage for a feudalism which eventually proved dangerous to government, but stimulating to Chinese letters and philosophy. At sometime during this period the Institutions of Chou was completed, detailing the duties and organizations or physicians. Hao, south of the Wei River, was the Chou capital until 771 B.C. when the last king of the Western Chou Dynasty was killed by a noble, as his capital was overrun by Northerners. A year later his son proclaimed Lo-Yang, south of the Yellow River in Honan, as his capital. This started the time of the Eastern Chou Dynasty, but the main functions of the king then began to be chiefly ceremonial, as the various area lords controlled their own sections. This feudal age was to last for some 500 years. It was different from European feudalism in that the Chou ruling class was principally unified by kinship ties and the king was considered as the head of a vast family. By 700 B.C. there were three powerful feudal states giving only lip-service to the Chou king. These were Ch'in in the old royal domain in Shensi, Chin in the north and Ch'i in the east. This subdivision of the Eastern Chou, which lasted over 250 years (722-481 B.C.) is called the "Spring and Autumn" era, after the name "Ch'unch'iu" which has the same meaning. (Ref. 1, 2)1

1C. may have been a result of a Scythian cavalry raid from the Altai region. The records of cavalry harassment from Mongolia are not clear until those of the 4th century B.C. (Ref. 3)

Although there were some 200 Chou statelets by the 8th century B.C. there were still many non-Chinese people about the borders who still had sometimes military and sometimes diplomatic contact with the Chou court. In the north were the "Ti", in the west and central uplands the "Jung", on the eastern coast the "I" and in the south all non-Chinese were lumped together as "Man". In the Yangtze delta region was a loose political entity called "Wu" and farther south a Yueh state.

From the philosophical standpoint, there was now a shift from the fear of spiritual beings to emphasis on human behavior and the groundwork was laid for the later humanistic thoughts of Confucius. Technically the Chinese also advanced and even built ice houses which were kept cool by evaporation. They developed a curved mouldboard plow which overturned the sliced sod, and was used continuously thereafter for rice cultivation. This advancement in agriculture was not used in Europe for another 1,400 years. (Ref. 4, 5, 6)

JAPAN

By the beginning of the first millennium B.C., the northern Ainu people had extended down to the central island of Honshu, while the southern aborigines, speaking a form of Japanese, led sedentary lives as shell-fish eaters. This situation continued until about 500 B.C. (Ref. 7)

KOREA and SOUTHEAST ASIA

These areas remained essentially as noted in the last chapter.2

2C. This suggests the beginning of centralization in that region. (Ref. 8)

1 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

2 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

3 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

4 [26] CHAN, WING-Tsit, "The Orderly Realm of Chinese Sages". Great Religions of the World. (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

5 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

6 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

7 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

8 [297] PFEIFFER, John, "At Ban Chiang a lost civilization comes to light", Smithsonian, Jan. 1933, pp. 98-107.

The Far East: 700 to 601 B.C.

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Continued Chou Dynasty)

The many provinces of early China gradually coalesced into five states covering what is now the district of Honan and some adjacent areas. The most important provinces were T'si, where the basic type of Chinese government developed, and Chin (or Tsin), which gave to China the name by which it is known to nearly all the world but itself. The organizing genius of T'si was Huan Chung, adviser to the Duke of Huan (683-640 B.C.). As prime minister, Kuan Chung replaced bronze with iron weapons and tools. Cast iron was used either in this century or the early 6th B.C., some 1,000 years before it was used in Europe. Sophisticated kilns developed for firing ceramics laid the foundation for this, in reaching the very high temperatures (1,835 degrees centigrade) necessary. T'si became a well ordered state with a stable currency and efficient administration. A code of manners, ceremonies and a sense of honor was developed and served as a substitute for religion among the upper classes. Extensive canals irrigated fields and agriculture and the silk industry prospered. Huan Chung taught the farmers to dig drainage ditches, stored surplus grain and rented farm equipment for them. (Ref. 1) Carts were used, leather shoes were worn, and houses were well built, with tables and chairs available. In the early years of the Spring and Autumn Era of the Eastern Chou, warfare was really more of a polite gamesmanship with very limited real fighting and few people hurt or killed. The art of diplomacy was supreme. (Ref. 2, 3, 4)

JAPAN

Three elements appear to be mingled in the Japanese race: A primitive white strain through the Ainus, who seem to have entered Japan from the region of the Amur River in Neolithic times; a yellow Mongol strain, coming from or through Korea in this 7th century B.C.; and a brown-black Malay and Indonesian strain, filtering in from the western Pacific islands. Gradually a new race developed from this 7th century on. In the Japanese mythology, 660 B.C. dates the legendary first emperor, Jimmu.

KOREA AND SOUTHEAST ASIA

Neolithic societies continued as previously, with metal in use in Thailand.

1 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

2 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

3 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

4 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

The Far East: 600 to 501 B.C.

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Chou Dynasty, continued)

Although China was nominally still under the Chou Dynasty actually it was essentially in a feudalistic age called the Spring and Autumn period. A unique institution of this period was the hegemon (pa) which was rule by a yearly conference of dukes from the three powerful statelets, offsetting the ineffectiveness of the Chou king. From 600 B.C. on the peasants made real progress in farming the flood plain of the Yellow River, by shifting from millet to rice. Vast diking, draining, canalization and engineering control was necessary to create an unbroken carpet of rice paddies. The amount of labor involved in all this is almost unbelievable. Rice, originally a dry land crop, still requires good oxygenation of its roots and the waters of the paddies cannot become stagnant but must be regularly circulated, necessitating constant attendance to pumps and various hydraulic systems. Farther south the Yangste Valley could not be farmed satisfactorily at that time, even though the river was much less wild and geologically less difficult, because the warmer, wetter climate allowed a great variety of parasites. Malaria may have been one of the worst, along with dengue fever and schistosomiasis, which has been definitely identified in a later, second century corpse. (Ref. 1, 2, 3)

This was the age of Lao-Tzu, the greatest of the pre-Confucius philosophers. His identity is disputed, but at least the Taoist philosophy became prominent with "Tao" meaning "The Way". Basically this was a way of thinking or refusing to think, for in the view of Taoists thought is a superficial affair, good only for argument and more harmful than beneficial to life. The Way is to be found by rejecting the intellect and all its errors and leading a modest life of retirement, rusticity and quiet contemplation of nature. Knowledge is not a virtue but on the contrary, rascals have increased since education spread. The worst conceivable government, in this philosophy, would be by philosophers themselves, as they botch every natural process with theory. Silence is the beginning of wisdom. Disregard of the Tao led to illness, not so much as punishment for sin as the inevitable result of acting against natural laws. Toaist philosophy became the religion of a considerable sized minority of the Chinese from this century down to our own time. Confucius, of the impoverished but noble K'ung family, was born in 551 B.C. and it is said that he had some contact with and learned from the Old Master, Lao-Tze. His teaching will be discussed under this same heading in the next chapter. The standard of living in China at that time was probably higher than in the contemporary Greece of Solon. (Ref. 4, 5)

JAPAN

The Jomon Culture hunting and fishing society of Japan continued through this century.

KOREA

The Neolithic societies of Korea continued as in the previous centuries.

SOUTHEAST ASIA

The people who now occupy southeast Asia began at about this time to leave their ancestral homes in southern China and Tibet and start their migrations southward, displacing or absorbing the aborigines of the area.

1 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

2 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

3 [259] Mac Neish, Richard STOCKTON, "Food Production & Village Life Developed in the Tehuacan Valley, Mexico", Archaeology 24: 307-315, Oct. 1971.

4 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

5 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

The Far East: 500 to 401 B.C.

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA. (CONTINUED CHOU DYNASTY UNTIL 403 B.C.)(THE FOURTH GREAT CENTER OF CIVILIZATION)

The early century was the productive time of K'ung Ch'iu, known to us as "Confucius"1 and one of the great philosophers of all time. He taught no system of philosophy, merely how to think. He was essentially an agnostic, but made a heroic effort to make men decent. The rules of propriety and ways of living which he laid down in his five "Ching" or Canonical Books were, however, a sort of strait-jacket preventing change in the centuries to come. His was a prim and Puritanical way, without any place for pleasure and little for friendship and love. Nobility was a matter of education and conduct. Confucian gentle- men ruled China for over two millennia and through most of that time gave a remarkable stability and coherence to Chinese culture and politics.

Another philosopher, Mo Ti, appeared in the last half of the century, teaching an opposite doctrine of universal love and peace. Although China had known and used iron for some purposes for centuries, only in this century can it be said that the country really entered the Iron Age, at approximately the same time as Scandinavia, Britain and Ireland.

During this century the political climate of China changed. The state of Chin became weak and was divided, leaving Ch'in, Ch'i and Ch'u as the dominant powers nominally under the Chou Dynasty. Warfare became less gentlemanly and states now went to serious battle, with the period beginning in 403 B.C. thereinafter called the "Warring States era". The crossbow and iron weapons were introduced and added to the deadliness of war. Cast metal coins came into use not later than this century. (Ref. 2)

In Chinese medical diagnosis, the feeling of the pulse has always been of primary importance and they have felt that interpretations of this could reflect the condition of each internal organ. A pulse chart was originally written in this or the preceding century by Pien Ch'iao. Exercise, massage and complex combinations of food to get proper relation of yin and yang were as much a part of treatment as medicines, although there were eventually some two thousand items in their pharmacopoeia. (Ref. 3)

JAPAN

At about 500 B.C. the southern aborigines of Japan began to be replaced by the Mongolian type of people associated with modern day Japan. Traces of the southern aborigines' curly hair, gray eyes, brown or even red beards, may still be found in upland valleys, but their chief contributions to modern Japan was their language. The newcomer Mongolians apparently just drifted in by raft, canoe or boat and each group learned to speak the existing native dialects, while they gradually brought in improved stone techniques, thatched roofs, potters' wheels2 and new agricultural ideas. Such arts seem to have allowed the newcomers to survive and multiply to the extent that they could push the aborigines back into the hills. (Ref. 4)

KOREA

Continuation of Neolithic societies.

SOUTHEAST ASIA

Continuing the centuries-long migrations from the north, some people settled in Vietnam and Cambodia, becoming the Chams and Khmers; some in Burma and east Thailand becoming the Pyus and Mons; some in the long peninsula becoming the Malays. Others took to the sea, spreading throughout Indonesia and eventually Melanesia. The Bronze Age began here about 500 B.C. with some evidence of the use of iron in central Siam (Thailand). We have noted before that there may have been bronze in Thailand three millennia previously and we must assume that the Siamese were far more advanced in metallurgy than their neighbors. (Ref. 6) Metal was used widely in the Philippines by 500 B.C. and there was a spread of agriculture, involving rice and millet. (Ref. 7)

1 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

2 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

3 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, r. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

4 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

5 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

6 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

7 [153] NANCE, JOHN, The Gentle Tasaday. (Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, Inc., New York 1975.

1.  "Confucius" is the Latinized version of K'ung fu-tzu, the latter word being a superlative variation of "tzu", meaning "master", - thus "Master K'ung". (Ref. 1)

2.  The British Museum Guide (Ref. 5) states that the Mongolians did not introduce the potters' wheel into Japan until about 300 B.C.).

The Far East: 400 to 301 B.C.

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Warring States Period of the Chou Dynasty)

The "Warring States" period continued, with chaos, corruption and division of the country. Even so, in the midst of this there was a profuse development of philosophies with rabid intellectual discussions as in earlier Athens. Mencius was a successor to Confucius who re-stated the latter's views and modified them so that he contributed greatly to the survival of Confucianism. Very different although not incompatible with Confucianists were the Legalists, who believed man basically bad and therefore must be curbed by stringent laws. The Naturalists had introduced the Yin (female) and Yang (male) principles which persist in Chinese thought even today. Taoism was expanded in this period to say that everything in a material world was relative, and that concepts existed only as contrasts. Eleven cities were considered to be very large, including the Ch'i capital, Lin-tze, consisting of 70,000 households, in modern Shantung province. By 325 B.C. regional lords had begun to call themselves "kings". Chopsticks were used in China at least by 400 B.C. Although Chinese tradition teaches that irrigation practices were still more ancient, it was in this and the next century that they were used on a large scale, along with intensive land clearing and the necessary hydraulics. (Ref. 1, 2, 3)

The marshy coastal districts did not lend themselves to charioteering so the infantry armies of the southeastern states of Wu and Yueh began to dominate the battles; chariot fighting declined and by 300 B.C. there were infantry masses in the hundreds of thousands. But in the far west and north, the non-Chinese nomads had developed cavalry for new assaults on China. (Ref. 4)

It is said that about 329 B.C. a Chinese general conquered the Tien Kingdom of Yunnan and settled there, introducing the Chinese culture to this region although it did not come under direct Chinese control until the 7th century C.E.. Recent excavations have shown a Bronze Age culture there with some indication of the use of iron. The art of the Yunnan people, including animal drawings, seems related to the people of the steppes of Asia. (Ref. 5, 6)

JAPAN

The Jomon hunting and fishing culture continued, with a mixed population, as indicated previously. (Ref. 7)

KOREA

No new information available for this century.

SOUTHEAST ASIA

The peoples of Southeast Asia had developed a complex agricultural civilization by this period, growing chiefly rice but also domesticated tubers and legumes, especially yams1. Their work animals were the ox and water buffalo. Bronze was not used in Vietnam until this century, although it had been used in Thailand for some 3,200 years and in China for 900 years. The reason for the slow spread of the metal is unknown. Burmese cotton was the best in the world and was exported in large quantities to India. (Ref. 8, 9)

1 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

2 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

3 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

4 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

5 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

6 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

7 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

8 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

9 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

1.  This refers to large tuberous roots of the climbing vines of the genus Dioscorea and is not the same plant as the sweet potato of America which is sometimes called a "yam" but is the root of the Convolvulaceae family

The Far East: 300 to 201 B.C.

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Warring States period of Chou until 221, Ch'in to 207 then Han from 202 B.C. on)

Two fundamental Chinese social aspects had become apparent by the end of this Formative Age of the early dynasties:

(l) The concept of the patrilineal family as the basic unit in society, with blood kinships of the highest importance and (2) the concept of natural differentiation into classes, each regarded in proportion to their contributions to the whole society.

In Shang times slavery had been common with the slaves being war captives or criminals, but this decreased with the Chou Dynasty and finally disappeared as social status became more fluid and transitory. With the disappearance of the early feudalism, free-hold farming became the dominant food support in the small amount of arable land available.

As population had greatly increased, there was no longer room for grazing herds and the Chinese had settled for scavenger-breeding animal husbandry consisting of plow oxen, pigs, chickens and occasionally dogs. Nomads first started bothering northern China in earnest in this century. The nomads were all milk-drinkers and still had the necessary lactose for digesting that in their physiological make-up, while most Chinese didn't have that enzyme after infancy because of the long scarcity of milk-giving animals. Yet today, Chinese as a whole find milk indigestible because of this lack of lactose and the classical Chinese have considered milk products unclean or tainted since 2,000 B.C. Yogurt, curds or cheese can be eaten, however, because the lactose sugar has been broken down. Stir fry cooking developed on the flood plains as a result of the very limited fuel supply, using wafer thin fragments of meat and vegetables which cook in minutes. Another innovation can be seen when a basic bean is taken through several processes and allowed to ferment in a loaf in a dark area over winter - then the fungus is scraped off and the leaves are soaked in brine. The briny liquid, when strained off, is "soy sauce". The debris of the loaves is made into a thick "cheese", now partially blamed for the high incidence of stomach cancer in Asia. (Ref. 1, 2)

Early in this century (as continued from the last) the Confucian principles were kept alive and elaborated for posterity by Master Meng K'o, Meng-tzu (Latinized - "Mencius") an extravagant, arrogant aristocrat who nevertheless recognized that public morale should be the first concern of every ruler and he did not hesitate to tell them so. But perhaps the greatest Confucian thinker of the century was Hsu~n-tzu. a ruthlessly tough-minded rationalist who set down his philosophy in a well organized book. In addition, the present form of the Lao-tzu, the Taoist philosophy, was made in this century with authorship really unknown. It has been called the most profound and beautiful book ever produced by the Chinese and has been translated into English more of ten than any book except the Bible. Its meanings, however, can still be elusive and debatable. (Ref. 3)

The era of Warring States continued until 230 B.C. when Shih Huang-ti began a campaign of conquest and unification of China which was completed by 222 B.C., establishing the Ch'in Dynasty. Coming from the Wei Valley, a true frontier country, the leader adopted this title of Huang-ti, meaning "August Lord", but usually translated "Emperor", and "Shih" simply means "first". He began as King Zheng of Qin at thirteen years of age, when the country was initially ruled by the chancellor, Lu Buwei. This First Emperor built the Great Wall of China, one of the greatest construction feats of all time, to protect the nation against barbarians. Seven hundred thousand forced laborers were used in building the wall and thousands of them died, crushed beneath some of the massive gray rocks. The wall was roughly 1,500 miles long and wide enough for six horses to gallop abreast along the top. The nation's first standing army, consisting of perhaps millions, was created to guard the wall from northern invaders and it did discourage the Huns, who then turned west into Europe.

Shih Huang-ti spent thirty-six years building a subterranean palace in which he could spend eternity and used seven hundred thousand conscripts to build this, also. Recent excavations of his tomb indicate that a guardian army of six thousand life-size pottery men and horses were constructed to stand eternal guard at his tomb. In addition, however, he did build great highways and encouraged science while discouraging letters and especially Confucian scholars. He buried 460 of the latter alive. China was divided into provinces with civil and military officials in a hierarchy of ranks; writing was standardized and there was an elaborate postal system and a great irrigation system in the Chengtu region of Szechwan. It was the Chinese written language in ideographic characters whose meaning is totally unrelated to local variations in pronunciation and spoken dialects, and which can therefore be understood throughout, that provided an important unifying instrument, even in the south which was occupied by people of non-Chinese origin.

The Yangtze Valley and other southern territories, although under political domination by the Chinese, could not be fully incorporated into the Chinese social structure because of disease barriers1. Huang-ti did build the Ling Canal, joining the Yangtze River basin to the Canton area via the Li River, and this canal helped supply one-half million Chinese troops conquering the lands to the south. The canal is now used chiefly for irrigation.

In the countryside south and west of the canal one-third of the people even today belong to minority groups such as the Zhuang, considered barbarians by the Hans.

Following the death of the First Emperor, disorder and civil war broke out, with nature adding its bit by floods and droughts. Shih's son was killed and chaos reigned until Koa-tsu, a petty official, turned general and emerged as the supreme ruler and founder of the Han Dynasty in 202 B.C.. The Formative Age of China had ended.

Huang-ti is generally regarded as the author of the canon of internal medicine called "NeiChing", but this may have originated much earlier. This work says that the blood current flows continuously in a circle and never stops. It describes acupuncture with needles from 1" to 10" long, a system which is still used to restore the balance of Yin and Yang in the body. It was in this century that iron weapons finally became common in China almost a thousand years after its use in Thailand and in the West, although the metal had been introduced some two centuries before. An interesting point is that when the Chinese did start to use iron it was cast, rather than wrought iron, and cast iron requires a heat of 1,400 degrees Centigrade at which temperature the iron melts and the slag is drawn off, allowing the molten iron to be poured into molds, like bronze. From the beginning the Chinese smiths knew only this method, and the heat required, which needs some type of blast furnace, was not produced in the West until many centuries later. (Ref. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11)1

1 That variety of nephrite is considered the only true jade. Jade veils have been found in several aristocratic burials of the late Eastern Chou period (770 up to 256 B.C.) in Luoyang.  (See also Additional Notes in 1st century C.E.)  Iron battle suits came into use in this century or earlier. (Ref. 12)

JAPAN

About 300 B.C., a new wave of Mongoloid immigrants from the mainland introduced rice culture, bronze, and if it was not already there, the potter's wheel to Japan, beginning the Yayoi Period. Although Chinese rulers had kept the seri culture secret until this century it now came to Japan, perhaps through Korea. (Ref. 13, 14) Bergamini (Ref. 15) states that in addition to the bronze and rice, traders brought in iron at this time.

KOREA

The Korean people are related racially, linguistically and culturally to the ancient peoples of Manchuria and Siberia as well as to the Japanese, but their post-Neolithic civilization came largely from China. In this century, among several existing states, the most civilized was Chosen, a semi-sinicized community in the northwest. (Ref. 16)

SOUTHEAST ASIA

Distinctive, massive, bronze drums decorated with images of animals and men date to 300 B.C. at Dong Son (North Vietnam). From the study of material in the National Archeological Museum in Tripoli, North Africa, Barry Fell (Ref. 17) writes that inscriptions copied from a cave in northwestern New Guinea in 1974 appear to be the work of a Libyan navigator who signed his name M-W (Egyptian "Mawi" means "navigator") sounding like Polynesian "Maui". The date of the New Guinea inscription was "the 15th year of Ptolemy III of Egypt" or 232 B.C. Further comments regarding the possible significance of this finding will be given in the next section. In 218 B.C. the Chinese Huang-ti, in his conquests, took over the Red River delta area (now Hanoi and Haiphong) and brought strong Chinese influences as well as Chinese blood to this area.

1 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

2 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

3 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

4 [69] GARRETT, w.e., "China's Beauty Spot", National Geographic 156: 536, Oct. 1979.

5 [89] HEARN, MAXWELL, "An Ancient Chinese Army rises from Underground Sentinel duty", Smithsonian, Nov. 1979, page 39.

6 [219] TOPPING, AUDREY, "China's Incredible Find", National Geographic 153: 440, Apr. 1978.

7 [69] GARRETT, w.e., "China's Beauty Spot", National Geographic 156: 536, Oct. 1979.

8 [221] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., Change and Habit. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1966).

9 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

10 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

11 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

12 [306] Kao, JEFFREY AND ZUOSHENG, YANG, "On Jade Suits & Han Archeology", Archaeology 36, No.6: 30-37, Nov./Dec. 1983.

13 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

14 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

15 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

16 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

17 [66] Fell, Barry, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

   1.  Even at the time of the "Flying Tigers" of World War II, General Chenault wrote that cholera, malaria, typhoid and other lesser known diseases plagued the people of this area. (Ref. 4)

The Far East: 200 to 101 B.C.

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (The "Former" Han Dynasty continued)

As briefly noted in the last chapter, between 206 and 202 B.C. Kao-tsu, a condot-tier, had seized the throne of China and founded the Han (Western or Former) Dynasty. Freedom of speech and writing was restored and a laissez-faire style of governing allowed prosperity and population growth. Although Kao-tsu died in 195 B.C. his wife and descendants ruled conservatively through the first half of the century. Taxes were cut markedly, but still the state granaries were full and the government had vast cash reserves. The greatest Han emperor was Wu-Ti, who in the last half of the century pushed back invading barbarians and extended China's rule over a vast territory, including Korea, Manchuria and even part of Turkestan. This western territory (Tarim Basin and the Turf an Oasis) was obtained by war against the Hsuing-nu, the tribal federation of central Asia that had developed along with the Chinese Empire and which had previously raided China as well. The western area became important because of the Chinese Silk routes to the West. Even by this century the Chinese had become very active in the silk trade, starting caravans at Paochi, moving along inside the Great Wall to its western end, then across Chinese Turkestan, then either north or south of the Tarim Basin, through the Pamir Mountains to Merv. The silk road had not functioned well before the time of the protection of the Chinese Hans, because of the nomad pirates.

Wu-ti experimented with socialism, founding great government industries, transportation services, deliveries and miscellaneous services, developed governmental control of prof it and levied a 5% income tax. He made Confucianism official and the Confucian classics were reassembled and transcribed. Through his conquests, south and west, contact was made with the Indian cultural sphere. This was accomplished by sailing 3,000 miles south through the straits of Malacca around the Malayan peninsula and the 1,200 miles across open seas to the Indian shore near what is now Madras. Seasonal monsoon winds were used for power on both the original and return trips, in different seasons. Chinese ocean-going junks had a much better sail arrangement, better cargo and cabin space and many other features unknown to western ships for many hundreds of years in the future . Cowrie shells, the first Chinese money, probably came from the far away Maldive Islands. The Chinese ambassador, Chang Chien, spent more than ten years in the middle east, gathering information on drugs, viticulture and many other subjects. Sometime during this Han Dynasty a noted clinician, Tsang Kung, described many diseases, including cancer of the stomach, aneurysm and rheumatism. (Ref. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6)1

1C.) the use of jade burial suits for the aristocrats came into its own. The tomb of Liu Sheng, Wu's brother, provides the best early example of this type of jade burial shroud. (Ref. 7)

JAPAN

Megaliths, similar to the ancient ones of Europe, appeared in this century throughout Japan and they continued to be built for the next eight or nine centuries. Strangely none appeared in China. This was the beginning of the Yayoishiki Culture period in Japan, but the people were still in a neolithic stage. These inhabitants, who now began rice cultivation, weaving and the use of metals such as bronze and some iron, may all have been immigrants from Manchuria and perhaps Korea, replacing the more native aboriginals of the Jomon period. They definitely had some relationship with Korea. (Ref. 8, 9)

KOREA

The state of Chosen continued to prosper. Near the end of the century at about 108 B.C. an alliance of the Koreans with the Hsiung-nu provoked the Chinese emperor, Wu-ti, who promptly sent troops and established an Han colony at Lo-lang, near the modern P'yongyang. (Ref. 10)

SOUTHEAST ASIA

Much of the mainland area of southeast Asia was now controlled by China with north Vietnam being subject to the Chinese for the next 800 years. But there was also foreign influence from India. Development of seafaring in the Indian Ocean and the China Sea allowed the people of the Ganges, already tolerant to tropical parasites, to implant Indian court culture along the river valleys and islands of southeastern Asia, even in Indonesia. In spite of the tremendous geographical area involved, however, powerful civilizations did not develop, probably because of the attenuating effects of malaria, dengue and waterborne infections of the gastro-intestinal tract. The use of iron spread from Siam to Borneo and Palawan by about 200 B.C. (Ref. 11, 12)

1 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

2 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

3 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

4 [43] CUNLIFFE, Barry, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

5 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

6 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

7 [306] Kao, JEFFREY AND ZUOSHENG, Yang, "On Jade Suits & Han Archeology", Archaeology 36, No.6: 30-37, Nov./Dec. 1983.

8 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

9 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

10 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

11 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

12 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

The Far East: 100 B.C. to 0

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (“Former” Han Dynasty continued).

At its peak the Han Empire under Wu-Ti was exceedingly prosperous, rivaling Rome both in size and wealth. The capital city Ch’ang-an had 250,000 in a total population of about 57,000,000. While the progress of mechanization was impeded in Greece and Rome by the number of available slaves, China had too many efficient coolies. (Ref. 1). We noted above that Wu-Ti expanded into the Tarim Basin in the west by defeating the Hsiung-nu and this pursuance continued even after Wu-Ti’s death. In 61 B.C. the chieftain of the southern Huns came to Ch’ang-an to submit as an Han vassal, while the northern group continued to be chased far westward into Samarkand, there to be finally defeated by a five-pronged Han force in 36 B.C. But in China proper the economic controls lapsed and nepotism and cronyism resulted in the loss of the imperial family’s power.

A type of national university had come into existence to prepare men for bureaucratic careers and by the end of the century the enrollment had reached 3,000. In the Han militia system all males registered for military service at 21 years of age and were eligible for service between the ages of 23 and 56 years. Allegedly every male was to have military service in his home county one month every year and one year of continuous service sometime in a guard unit, but soon a practice of paying poorer men to serve one’s time became standard practice. In addition to using cowrie shells as currency, copper coins, later called “sapekes” by the Europeans, came into use. Both of these competed with salt and grain as a medium of exchange. (Ref. 2). In this century the Chinese drilled deep holes, presumably for water, in Szechwan and their drilling methods were copied centuries later in the United States. (Ref. 3)

In early China the laws required punishments and torture that equaled that seen in Europe at a much later period. Death penalties were carried out by beheading or by chopping the offender in two at the waist. In cases of treason or some equally serious crime, all the offender’s relatives might also be put to death. Lesser offenders might simply be mutilated by tattooing, amputation of nose or feet or castration. Impriconment was rare, but hard labor on government construction was used for minor offenders. In Emperor Ch’eng’s reign (32-7 B.C.) authority was delegated to his mother’s family, the Wang clan. Ssu-me Ch’ien was a great Chinese historian of this era. (Ref. 4, 5).

In Manchuria a new state of koguryo was founded in this century and soon also included northern Korea.

JAPAN

The Yayishiki Culture continued into this century with rice culture appearing about 100 B.C. Animism and totemism, sex and ancestor worship satisfied the religious needs of these early Japanese. Out of the latter worship came the oldest official living religions of the nation – Shinto. This faith, called the Way of the Gods, took three forms; the domestic cult of family ancestors, the communal cult of clan ancestors and the state cult of the imperial line with its founding gods.

A Mongolian castaway group on Kyushu multiplied so rapidly as farmers that they took over all the arable land on the island and while some of the aborigines became serfs, others took to the hills from where they continued to raid the farmers for centuries. The new Kyushu community was organized as a loose confederacy of villages, each ruled by its own matriarch or fertility mother, and the woman leader of the most powerful town was called the “Sun Goddess”. Early Chines traders called her “Pime-ko”, or “Hime-Ko”, meaning “Sunshine Child”. (Ref. 6, 7, 8). In an attempt to obtain more sea-food to feed the expanding popuations, a great ship-building effort was made in 81 B.C. (Ref. 9).

KOREA

Most of Korea was controlled by the Han Chinese at this time, but the northern portion was allied with Manchuria in the new state of Koguryo.

SOUTHEAST ASIA

Already controlling North Vietnam, the Chinese now added central Viet Nam to their territory which they were to maintain for centuries. No other significant changes occurred.

1 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

2 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

3 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

4 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

5 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

6 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

7 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

8 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

9 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

The Far East: 0 to A.D. 100

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA ("Former" Han to A.D. 9, Hsin to A.D. 25, then "Later" Han)

At the beginning of this century China's population was just short of 60,000,000. Interrupting the Han Dynasty, the Wang clan was acting as regents for a boy emperor and the last of these regents, Wang Mang, gradually outmaneuvered all opposition until by A.D. 9 he could declare the Han Dynasty defunct and take the throne himself. Even so, he was the highest type of Chinese gentleman and promoted many improvements for the country, including the abolition of slavery and the redistribution of some very large, landed estates among the peasants. He continued state monopolies of salt and iron and added other state ownerships. As of ten happens with such planned economies, however, some natural calamities, including a series of poor harvests, drought in the Shensi basin and a series of breaks in Yellow River dams resulting in vast flooding with changes in the river's course and thousands of drowned and homeless people, upset everything, revolts broke out and he was killed (A.D. 25). Things reverted to the previous situation and the rule fell to a scion of the House of Han, inaugurating the "Later" Han Dynasty which was to last until A.D. 220. It was this dynasty which helped to defeat the Hsuing-nu as detailed under Central Asia. The restorer of this Han Dynasty, Kuang-wu-ti, moved the capital to Loyang in Honan and thus the term "Eastern Han" is sometimes used as synonymous with "Later" Han. Kuang-wu-ti at the same time allowed a group of southern Hsuing-nu to settle in northern Shensi and Shansi provinces. He and his immediate successors were vigorous, conscientious rulers and the population and economy rapidly rebounded.

The Han emperors sent soldier-farmers to the far western extensions of the Great Wall in the region of present day Jiayuguan, to secure their frontier, even as the Communists have done recently. They watered the desert by building irrigation systems to bring down mountain snow-waters, set up mulberry plantations for silk worms and prospered. This was on the original southern silk route. The Chinese preferred to let others do their hauling and in these centuries silk either went over-land on the silk route or to India in Indian boats and from there on in either Indian, Greek or Arab vessels. (Ref. 1, 2)

The year 67 marks the coming of Buddhism to China. The first known manufacture of paper dates to about A.D. 100. In this century these far easterners used power drive bellows and blast furnaces, such objects not seen in Europe until the Middle Ages. The principle of the compass was also known in China at this time and was used on Chinese ships long before it appeared in the west. (Ref. 3)2

2D. 58-76) (Ref. 4)

JAPAN

At about the time of Christ the current Sun Goddess (See preceding chapter) allied herself with a marauding pirate trader from Karak, Korea (modern Pusan) and later arranged for him to marry her granddaughter. A son and grandson of this marriage ranged widely up the Inland Sea, exploring and provisioning along the southern Honshu coast.

When the grandson, Jimmu, became of age, he moved his entire pirate fleet - ships, warriors, women and utensils away from the matriarchal Kyushu across to Honshu, at what is now Osaka. Because the local southern aborigines there needed help against the hairy Ainu hunters from the north, they welcomed Jimmu's warriors who also found an iron ore with the right impurities for making steel. Within a few generations Japan was in the steel age, making the finest blades of the world. After three years of campaigning, about A.D. 501, Jimmu proclaimed himself Emperor of an area which includes present day Osaka, Kobe and Kyoto, and he called this "Yamato". Jimmu was the present day Emperor Hirohito's ancestor, 69 generations removed, and practically all present day affluent Japanese are his progeney or that of his three most able lieutenants, Nakatomi, Mononobe and Otomo. Jimmu and his immediate descendants practiced a savage, spartan puritanism which equated cleanliness with godliness, using countless ceremonies of ritual purification. They seemed to be terrified of the pollution of death, and when an emperor passed away, the entire capital was moved to a new site.

On the local spirit worship Jimmu built the basis for later Shintoism, adding the continental worship of ancestral ghosts. He showed his people a bronze mirror, a bright sword and a string of semi-precious, half-moon shaped, smooth stones and made these the talismans of his divinity, allegedly bestowed on him by the Sun-Goddess. These objects have been protected as symbols of the divine emperor down to this day. (Ref. 6)

During the first four centuries of the Christian era this imperial Yamato clan seems gradually to have taken over most of central and western Japan in a long series of wars with other clans and the Ainu in the east and Kumaso in the west. The latter appear to have been of alien and quite possibly southern origin. A Japanese embassy was established in China in 57. (Ref. 7)

KOREA

Records from Korean kingdoms show that from A.D. 42 to 562 Karak, Miniana, as the Japanese later called it, and which we now know as Pusan, was recognized as an independent Japanese city-state. This may originally only have been a way-station for raiders going to the far south Malayan area. In the north, Koguryo and other states at- tempted to assert their independence from the Chinese colony in the region. (Ref. 8)

SOUTHEAST ASIA

The Chinese Han Empire extended its civil administration over Chinese colonies in North Vietnam. In South Vietnam and present day Cambodia there was the state of Funan, perhaps started by Khmers with an Indian spiritual background. It prospered by its position on the trade route between India and China. In the Mekong delta the people built canals to control floods and to limit the intrusion of salt water on to the land. Java and neighboring islands were conquered by Hindu princes from India and thereafter a number of Hindu empires divided the region. (Ref. 9, 10, 11)

1 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

2 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

3 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

4 [306] Kao, JEFFREY AND ZUOSHENG, Yang, "On Jade Suits & Han Archeology", Archaeology 36, No.6: 30-37, Nov./Dec. 1983.

5 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

6 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

7 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

8 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

9 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

10 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

11 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

1.  The chronology used here, of Jimmu's "coronation" at A.D. 50, is that of the archaeologist Edward Kidder. Official Japanese dating, adopted for ideological purposes, places this some 600 to 800 years earlier. (Ref. 5)

The Far East: A.D. 101 to 200

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Later Han Dynasty)

In the entire first half of the century there were a series of Han Dynasty empresses ruling weakly for themselves and/or various infants and youths, with the help of some very clever court eunuchs. By A.D. 157 the population had reached a peak of almost 55,000,000. Han court records refer to Roman ambassadors with dates of visits and the names of current Roman emperors, but conversely these embassies are not mentioned in any known Roman records. The Chinese government's return to laissez-faire policies allowed the great land- owners to again dominate the serfs and avoid taxes. Then a series of natural disasters occurred, beginning with massive floods and locust infestations at A.D. 175. At about the same time, in at least two different years, there were great pestilences which broke out in the army fighting on the northwestern frontier, with three or four out of ten dying. This plague, whatever it may have been, apparently seeped down all through Asia to some degree in the next 20 years. Peasants began seeking refuge in Taoist inspired religious cults, which offered faith healing and alchemical prescriptions. (Ref. 1, 2, 3)

It was the massive religious uprising of the "Yellow Turbans" against the palace eunuchs in A.D. 184 which finally began to bring down the Han Dynasty. The remaining eunuchs were finally massacred by Yuan (War Lord) Shao in 189 and the capital Loyang was sized by General Tung Cho in 190. Some 700 other officials and some 1,000 students were thrown in prison and tortured and cannabalism has even been alleged. In this Later Han period the student body of the national university had swelled to some 30,000 youths, many apparently evaders of military and other state service. Local militias were now abolished to lessen local war-lordism and although the dynasty continued officially on into the next century, in actuality the last few years were an era of chaos and divided states. (Ref. 4, 5, 6)

Chinese art, astrology and astronomy appropriated some Hellenistic elements, but it is of interest that in many simple items the Chinese were far ahead of the western world. For instance, in this century the Chinese used wheelbarrows, cranks, objects mounted in gimbals to keep level (as shipboard lamps), treadles and rotating fans, none of which were used in Europe until variously the 9th to the 18th centuries. Paper was invented by Tshai Lun in A.D. 105 and was made from decayed vegetable matter, although the process was kept secret by the Chinese for many centuries. The chair was introduced in this or the next century but didn't come into general use for several hundred years. Most of southern China remained in the hands of aboriginal peoples for centuries to come. (Ref. 7, 8, 9, 10)1

1 This excellent, lethal instrument was about as easy to use as a handgun and needed no special strength to cock it, while the long bow required years of practice to develop sufficient thumb and finger strength to draw the bow to its full arc. Technically, manufacture of the cross-bow involved a most difficult lamination procedure using wood, bone, horn and sinew, as well as the skilled construction of a metal trigger apparatus. (Ref. 11)

JAPAN

For five generations after Jimmu, the Yamato emperors were very careful not to mix their blood with the aborigines and they imported women of their own race from the home fief in Korea. Each prince and vassal had as many wives as he could afford and the old records tell of families with 100 children. After the first five generations, Jimmu's court descendants began to marry their own cousins and although the inbreeding was great, the stock was healthy and a large percentage, probably more than one-half, of modern Japanese are descended from it. At A.D. 200 the Empress Jingu is said to have sent a vast fleet of multi-oared ships to dominate the Koreans and exact tribute. (Ref. 12, 13)

KOREA

Koguryo continued as an independent state, and there were now other communities which could break away from the weakened Han control. At the end of the century part of Korea was forced to pay tribute to Japan. (Ref. 14)

SOUTHEAST ASIA

We noted in the last chapter that China had occupied North Vietnam and Champa. In this century the Hindu influenced state of the Chams arose in the area now known as South Vietnam, but north of Saigon. For the next 1,200 years they struggled to remain independent of the expanding Viet and Khmer kingdoms. Funan existed as a prosperous state in the Cambodia and extreme southern Vietnam areas, developing a network of irrigation and transportation canals that made the huge Mekong River valley fertile and the country rich with commerce. Burma, Thailand, Cambodia and Laos became the chief lands for the Hinayana or Lesser Vehicle Buddhism. (Ref. 15, 16, 17)2

2 In the Mekong delta an inland center called "Oc-eo" was a small scale Venice. It had many gold artifacts, including a seal ring with Sanskrit inscription, a life-sized Hindu statue and gold metal from Rome, dated A.D. 152. (Ref. 18)

1 [65] FELL, Barry, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

2 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

3 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

4 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

5 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

6 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

7 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

8 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

9 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

10 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

11 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

12 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

13 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

14 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

15 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

16 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

17 [114] KITAGAWA, JOSEPH M., "The Eightfold Path to Nirvana", Great Religions of the World. (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

18 [297] PFEIFFER, JOHN, "At Ban Chiang a lost civilization comes to light", Smithsonian, Jan. 1933, pp. 98-107.

The Far East: A.D. 201 to 300

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Han to 220, Three Kingdoms to 280, then Chin)

At the beginning of the century the capital was at Lo-yang and northeastern China grew in importance. The Han Empire now reached as far south as Haiphong, but "The force of the imperial unity played itself out in 220, when the last of the Han emperors officially abdicated at the bidding of a general who had already kept him in custody for several years." (1) There followed a period of disordered life and a stalemated civilization, during which time there were three kingdoms: Wei, in the north, directly following the Han Dynasty, under Ts'ao P'ei; Wu, in the southeast, based at Nanking under Sun Ch'u~an; and Shu, controlled by Liu Pei and based at Chengtu in the southwest. Liu Pei and his family, originally lieutenants of General Ts'ao Ts'oa, protector of the last of the Hans, then became the greatest enemy of the Wei, giving rise to legends, fiction and drama in China for centuries to come. Even so, Shu Han was absorbed by Wei in A.D. 263 and Wu gave way in 280, ending the Three Kingdoms era. In the meantime, the Ssu-ma family generals had taken over Wei and changed the name to Chin, and for a generation after 280 China again had a fragile unity. The population at that time was only 16,163,0009 a drop from 55,000,000 in the middle of the 2nd century. A severe pestilence was a major factor in this population decline, as in Europe at the same time, but at least part of it was due to wide-spread cannibalism. China had entered her four centuries of "dark ages". The southern Hsiung-nu lived on the frontier as a hostile minority and the long delayed clash was about to occur. (Ref. 1, 2, 3, 4)

Mo Ching wrote the Pulse Classic, an intensive method of diagnosis from study of the pulse, a procedure still used in China and which had originally been described in the 6th or 5th century B.C. Chang Chung-ching wrote a classic treatise on "Typhoid and other Fevers" and it was perhaps in this century that Ko Hung described beriberi, hepatitis, and plague and gave an early report on small-pox with an accurate description of the pustules. Chinese medicine continued to progress from this time until the 10th century, when it became static. Although sugar cane was known near Canton, it was not commuted to sugar, proper, and honey remained the universal sweetener. (Ref. 5, 6, 7)

JAPAN

Sometime between A.D. 200 and 250 the 10th emperor, Sujin, had the royal bronze mirror and the sword enshrined outside the palace for all to see and admire. The mirror, called "the mirror of knowledge" was housed at a shrine called "Ise", which even today is a prime holy place of Japan. The Yamato Culture of Korean origin was introduced with iron implements and megalithic burials. Handicrafts were soon organized into guilds. Beneath this artisan class was a slave class, recruited from prisons and battle- fields. Social organization was partly feudal, partly tribal and each clan had a sovereign head. Government was primitively low and weak, although it was a period of geographical expansion and victory over the Ainu. (Ref. 8, 9)

KOREA

This was a period of some turmoil, with early century invasions by Kungsun Manchurians and late century conquests by the Chinese of the Wei Dynasty. About A.D. 250 northern invaders established the state of Paikche, in the southwest.

SOUTHEAST ASIA

Burma was under Indian influence and by this era Hindu peoples had established commercial settlements on the coast and river mouths. These settlements developed into small kingdoms in contact with Tibeto-Burmese tribes. Champa, Funan, Viet and Khmer kingdoms continued rivalries. The Chinese controlled Haiphong and it is probable that Chinese and Indian traders met at Go Oc Eo in southern Cambodia, from whence the Indians carried the Chinese goods on across the Malay Peninsula and on to India. From A.D. 200 on the island kingdoms of Indonesia derived their civilization from India, through contacts with Hindu traders and Buddhist monks. (Ref. 10, 11)

REFERENCE Quotation taken from Mc Neill (Ref. 12), page 324.

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

3 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

4 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

5 [136] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

6 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

7 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

8 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

9 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

10 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

11 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

12 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

The Far East: A.D. 301 to 400

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Chin to 316, then north-south division with Wei)

We ended the last century with the new Chin Dynasty ruling a somewhat unified China but this era was dominated by great landowning families, each with hundreds of serfs and private soldiers. In A.D. 304 a sinicized Hsiung-un chieftain established a state called "Han" (later Chao) in Shansi and from there he sacked the Chin capital at Loyang seven years later. At this same time a great pestilence, preceded by locusts and famine, left only one or two people out of a hundred alive in the northwestern provinces of China. In 322 another epidemic, which may have been small-pox, hit with three out of each ten dying. Maximal political fragmentation coincided almost exactly with the arrival of this disease and the population, overall, was nearly halved. The political upheavals involved several short-lived dynasties of foreigners from the steppes, some Hsiung-nu, some proto-Mongolian Hsien-pei, some Turkic and Avar and even some Tibetan tribes. It was the Shansi Hsiung-nu who again overwhelmed the new Chin capital at Ch'ang-an. They were led by Liu Yuan who was six feet tall and had red strains in his long beard1. Subsequently this area of northern Honan, in central China, was ruled by the Chieh, one of the 19 tribes of the Hsiung-nu. These Chieh had high noses and full beards and were definitely non-Mongolian, perhaps Tocharian, in origin. They were finally massacred, all 200,000 of them, in A.D. 349 by Jan Min who then became lord of the region. (Ref. 1, 2, 3, 4)

Refugees from the north set up a new Eastern Chin Dynasty at Nanking and in 347 they reconquered Szechwan but in the latter half of the century a Tibetan general, FuChien, temporarily consolidated the north. His plan to add the south was wrecked at a famous battle of the Fei River in 383 when he was defeated by the Eastern Chin. Finally in 386 a powerful Turkic people, the Toba (Northern Wei) who became avid Buddhists, succeeded in re-unifying northern China once again. Their kingdom actually included a large part of Siberia and Manchuria, carrying the absorbed Chinese civilization to the Arctic. This has been compared to Charlemagne's Empire in that in both the barbarians became civilized - "Chinicized" or "Romanized" respectively. The Buddhist art of north China was profoundly influenced by Central Asia for the next 200 years, although in the south, as the Chinese achieved some mastery of the concepts and terms of Indian Buddhism, they began to develop schools of their own (Ref. 6, 7, 8)

JAPAN

Southern Japan was still in the Great Tombs or Kofun Period, in which the nobles used pottery coffins, high-fired stoneware, iron and bronze implements and weapons. (Ref. 9) The victories of the half-legendary Prince Yamatodake over the Kumaso and the Ainu seem to reflect a period of rapid expansion in the early decades of this century. There were many Japanese campaigns now onto the Korean peninsula by the armies of the Empress Jingo, with the establishment of a Japanese protectorate over a group of miniature states known as Kara or Imna, in southern Korea.

The 12th emperor, Keiko, who reigned probably from A.D. 280 to 316 returned to Kyushu and after getting rid of the queens of the ancient, savage tribe he negotiated a permanent merger of Yamato and Kyushu.

As Yamato grew in geographical size, chiefly by driving the Ainu farther and farther north, the population increased and the emperors, like the Egyptian pharaohs, began to construct vast mausolea. Each successive ruler wanted a bigger tumulus and a larger company of victim vassals to be buried with him and convey him to the spirit world. Forced retainer sacrifice was practiced routinely in this and the next century. (Ref. 10)

KOREA

By A.D. 313 the last remnants of Chinese colonies were extinguished by the native states of Korea, although Chinese culture remained dispersed throughout the peninsula.

Three kingdoms emerged: Koguryo in the north; Paekche in the southwest; and Silla in the southeast. All had high-fired pottery of great excellence. The Japanese foothold, mentioned in the second paragraph above, was established between the two latter kingdoms. (Ref. 11)

SOUTHEAST ASIA

Tibeto-Burmese tribesmen migrated from the north into present day Burma, forming the Pyu Kingdom. Chenla was the country of Khmer people occupying what is now Thailand and Laos. Funan, under its Khmer rulers, continued as a prosperous agricultural and trading country on the Cambodian plateau. Active civilizations existed in the Indonesian area with sea-faring men trading with Africa and Europe. Cinnamon from Malaya and Indonesia was sent all the way to Rome. (Ref. 12, 13)

1 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

2 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

3 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

4 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

5 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

6 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

7 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

8 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

9 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

10 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

11 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

12 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

13 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

1.  Maenchen-Helfen (Ref. 5) gives this as additional evidence that the Huns, which presumably descended in part from the Hsiung-nu were a mixed group, probably including some "Europoid" elements

The Far East: A.D. 401 to 500

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Northern and southern dynasties)

The ruling Toba Wei had become completely Sinicized by this time and had carried out a redistribution of land to bring more under cultivation and rehabilitate the economy in northern China. The southern dynasty, the Eastern Chin, pushed northward regaining access through Kansu to the central Asian trade routes but through court intrigues and usurpations there was an ever increasingly weaker series of dynasties, including Sung (42?-429) and southern Ch'i (479-502). Even so, these southerners, considering themselves the saviors of the old Han civilization, absorbed most of the aboriginal peoples of the south China area into the Chinese mainstream, as Buddhism became the predominant intellectual and religious force. (Ref. 1)

There was also intense activity in philosophical as well as religious thought. Taoism broke into sects and never became a unified religion. Ch'an Buddhism (similar to Japanese Zen) was brought to China allegedly by Bodhidharama. Chinese junks sailed regularly to the head of the Persian Gulf with cargoes for Babylon, although little or no apparent exchange of ideas and techniques occurred between east and west. The junks, for many centuries, had had single rudders, water tight compartments and staterooms, all far advanced inventions not used by westerners for up to 1,600 years later. The ships carried fresh ginger growing in pots and thus unknowingly prevented scurvy. (Ref. 2, 3, 4)

JAPAN

The mausoleum constructed for Emperor Nintoku, who may have died in 4271, is a moat-girded artificial mountain, 80 acres in area, more than one-half mile long and after 1,500 years of weathering still over 100 feet high. It took 20 years to build by conscription labor. Japan's royal family has refused any excavation of any of the royal mounds to this day. In this 5th century the Chinese system of ideographic writing was brought to Japan but phonetic symbols had to be invented to express the Japanese word endings and it was actually another 200 years before it became a real vehicle for Japanese thought and record. In the meantime, during the reign of Inkyo, music and dance were promoted and Chinese Buddhism was introduced and began to rival Shintoism in popular favor. (Ref. 5, 6, 7)

KOREA

The Three Kingdoms period continued. King Changsu brought Kogurya to the height of its power and moved the capital from the Yalu River to P'yongyang. Silla continued expansion in the south. (Ref. 10)

SOUTHEAST ASIA

No important changes from the last century have been identified from the literature and the reader is referred to those previous centuries.

1 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

4 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

5 [12] BERGAMINI, David, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

6 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

7 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

8 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

9 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

10 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

1.  This date is from Bergamini (Ref. 8) but there is some confusion here in that Durant (Ref. 9) indicates that the next emperor, Inkyo, started his reign in 412

The Far East: A.D. 501 to 600

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Northern and Southern Dynasties to 581, then Sui)

The T'o-pa Turks of Manchuria gave way early in the century to a new nomadic empire of the Juan-Juan tribes, a mixture of proto-Turk and proto-Mongol elements. Overthrown in 551 they migrated westward to become the Avars of European history. The powerful Korean state of Koguryo controlled a part of Manchuria in this period.

The northern part of China continued to be dominated most of the time by nomadic border tribes. Among these was the Western Wei Dynasty which in the middle of this century adopted an old Mongol tribal institution in that every family that had more than two sons had to send one for permanent service in one of the 100 garrisons in the state. The militiamen were exempt from taxes and other labor levies and this system, called "fu-ping", was intended to separate elite fighting men from the farming population. In some form it persisted through several centuries. There were other nomad intrusions and civil conflicts, but the invaders always adopted Chinese customs and culture and the Chinese upper class, particularly in northwest China collaborated and intermarried with the Turks and Hsien-pei with a resulting Sino-nomad aristocracy, many people speaking both Chinese and Turkish. It was from this mixture that came the ruling house of the Sui, who took control in 581 and finally unified all of China under a Chinese, Yang Chien, who had previously been a minister of the northern Chou court. (Ref. 1, 2)

This was the great age of Mahayana Buddhist sculpture in China, as this type of the religion had swept into the country from India and flourished there as it lost ground in its homeland. At this time China built suspension bridges held up by chains, a procedure not used in the West for some 1,200 years. The rebuilding of old canals linking the capital, Ch'ang-an, with the Yellow River in 584 contributed to stability and work was started on what westerners call the Grand Canal, linking the Yellow and Yangste rivers. All this was done under Wen-ti (581-604)5 a Sui emperor who was an effective administrator and skilled propagandist. (Ref. 3, 4)

JAPAN

Up until about this time the Japanese islands formed part of a large culture, nomadic in origin, which included Manchuria, eastern Siberia and Korea. We mentioned in the last chapter that Buddhism had crossed over from China to Japan via Paekche, Korea and it made rapid conquest with the help of Emperor Senka. (Ref. 5) Unfortunately the Korean missionaries also brought a lethal disease, perhaps small-pox, and epidemics followed in Japan about each thirty years throughout the remainder of the century, although some medical help came from China. Both the religious needs of the people and the political needs of the state gave Buddhism fertile ground. This was not the agnostic, pessimistic and puritan philosophy of Buddha, himself, but the Mahayana variety of gentle gods, cheerful ceremonies and personal immortality. It offered the people that unity of feeling and belief which serves as a source of social order. With it also came fine and useful arts such as painting, sculpture, architecture, music, bronze works, textile making and medical arts. The written Chinese language continued to be modified into a complex system by adding phonetic elements to the ideographs, for writing the Japanese language. The period of Haniwa sculptures of human figures, generally coil-built cylinders of unglazed, iron-bearing clay, fired to a warm buff color, has representation today in the Rockefeller collection. (Ref. 6, 7)

In 587 Emperor Bidatsu (31st emperor) embraced Buddhism on his death bed but the clan of court armorers, the Mononobe, would have none of this and they rebelled and burned Buddhist temples far and wide. But the Kyushu ladies' faction at the court exterminated this clan, bringing to power the son of a Mononobe mother, Prince Shotoku Taishi, who agreed to a Chinese type of program for strengthening the nation. Prince Shotoku was a child prodigy who had mastered the Chinese system of writing by the age of seven. We shall hear much more of him in the next century. (Ref. 8, 9)

KOREA

In the north, Koguryo continued as a powerful state with some territory also in Manchuria. In the south, Silla finally adopted Buddhism and then began to make rapid progress in civilization and in geographic expansion at the expense of the adjacent Japanese colony. By 554 Silla won an outlet on the East China Sea in central Korea, giving her easy sea communications with China. Chinese medicine spread to Korea at this time. (Ref. 10, 11)1

1 (Ref. 12)

SOUTHEAST ASIA

Dvaravati, Thaton and Pegu were Mon kingdoms appearing at this time in what is now southern Burma. They spread Buddhism that ultimately became the faith of most of the peninsula. Around A.D. 550 the Funan Kingdom was overthrown by the Kambujas, a mountain people from Chenla (Laos), after floods had ravaged the Mekong Valley. Their king was also of the same royal line as the Funan (a Khmer) and these people were closely tied to the Hindu tradition and deities. (Ref. 13)

1 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

4 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

5 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

6 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

7 [186] SAKELLARAKIS, YANNIS AND SAPOUNA-SAKELLARAKI, efi, "Drama of Death in a Minoan Temple", National Geographic 159: 205-222, Feb. 1981.

8 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

9 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

10 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

11 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

12 [305] FOCKLER, SHIRLEY, "Kyongju", Travel Holiday, Sept. 1981, page 41.

13 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

The Far East: A.D. 601 to 700

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Sui to 618, then T'ang Dynasty)

The Sui Dynasty consolidated China in part through state patronage of a style of Buddhism which was acceptable by both north and south and by construction of a canal system linking the Yangzte with the Yellow River in the Peking region. They did not do well in foreign affairs, however, as they had lost the Tarim Basin, Manchuria and Korea and several early wars to reclaim these lands had failed. Some historians have even considered the first Sui emperor of this century, Yang-ti, a complete madman who had supposedly poisoned his father to get the throne. (Ref. 1) Civil war soon developed and victorious was the family of Li, who established the T'ang Dynasty. In A.D. 610 we find the earliest description of bubonic plague, which soon became common in Canton on the sea. Perhaps this plague was a factor in the demise of the Sui Dynasty. (Ref. 2, 3)

For a short while the warlike Turkish nomads of the steppes became allies of the new T'ang Dynasty and the Chinese even adopted Turkish fashions, developed Turkish Chinese dictionaries and wore Turkish clothes. The T'ang, like the Sui before them, came from a mixed Turkish-Mongolian-Chinese aristocracy. Their second ruler, T'ai Tsung (AD. 627-650) was one of the greatest of Chinese emperors. All the aristocrats of this period were of the mixed blood and characteristically hard-drinking, hard-riding, fighting men who hunted with falcons and whose women played polo. We have noted that in the preceding centuries work had been started in the clearing and draining of the luxuriant jungles of the Yangtze Valley so that by the beginning of this century this valley not only supported a large population but was capable of producing large surpluses of food. To widen the canal between the Yangtze and Huany Ho Valley, about 5,500,000 workers, including all commoners between 15 and 50 years of age in some areas, were concentrated under the control of some 50,000 police. They were forced laborers but not slaves, in the true sense. As a result of all this the T'angs had a double base, the Yellow and the Yangtze rivers, and by 611 the Grand Canal joining the two had been completed so that shipments of large quantities of rice and other goods was possible from the south to the northern capitals. The imperial bureaucracy managed the collection, transport and distribution of such goods, while the Great Wall in the north was re-constructed for defense. These factors of a biological mix, a thriving economy and the spiritual stimulation of Buddhism, with a genius ruler, started China on its greatest age. T'ai Tsung, after reunifying much of China by war, returned to his capital, Ch'ang-an, and gave himself to the ways of peace, spreading the philosophy of Confucius, revising penal laws and beautifying the city. He welcomed all religions and exempted all temples from taxation. After his death, one of his harem women, Wu, pulled out of a nunnery by T'ai Tsung's oldest son, Lao-tsung, poisoned her way to power, made herself empress and proclaimed the Chou Dynasty. Actually a subsidiary of the T'ang this dynasty ushered in another creative age, with the profits of exported rice, wheat, silk and spices spent for unparalleled luxury. Furs, precious jewels, statues, paintings, poems and money were everywhere in abundance. (Ref. 4, 5, 6, 7)

The fu-ping system of military conscription, started by the Wei Dynasty (see page 423), evolved to the T'ang system of elite, career soldiers who also performed agricultural work to support themselves, as far as possible. The T'ang had more than 600 garrisons clustered primarily around Ch'ang-an. Their statuary punishments came under five categories: death by strangulation or bisection; exile from home (up to 1,000 English miles); hard labor for up to 3 years; beating with heavy bamboo rods up to 100 blows. Commutation to fines was often possible for people of wealth. (Ref. 8, 9)

In the period of their foreign excursions in the 660s Chinese armies intervened in India and Central Asia, re-occupying the Tarim Basin, Dzungaria and Afghanistan and they briefly sat up protectorates in Tukharistan, Sogdiana, Ferghana and even eastern Persia. Yunnan came under Chinese suzertainty at the end of the century and a portion of Manchuria, previously under Korean control, was returned to China as Empress Wu intervened in a Korean civil war. After three centuries of importance the use of the armored, great Persian horses in cavalry units came to an end in China. If a cross-bowman could knock even a heavily armored man off his horse, it made no sense to have these expensive units. (Ref. 10, 11)

Sun Szu-miao wrote a 30 volume summary of medical knowledge gained up to that time and then headed a committee which produced a 50 volume treatise on pathology. It was in this century that examinations were first required to qualify as a physician, a process that preceded the first licensing program in the West by some 4 centuries. It was about this time that women of proper family started to bind their feet (i.e. the mothers bound the infants' feet) producing a severely deformed, cavus foot. This greatly restricted their activities and allowed their legs and mons to accumulate much fat, thus supposedly making them very attractive sexually to the Chinese men. The custom was continued for a thousand years.

JAPAN

As the century opened, the child prodigy, Prince Shotoku Taishi, had formed groups of scholars who wrote the first histories, geographies, grammars and legal codes of Japan and who drew up orderly plans for a census, land surveys, equitable conscription and taxation. He also worked out a compromise between Buddhism and Shintoism that could be tolerated. At his death in 621, the Shinto princes and the Buddhist princes of the imperial family actually came to a small war, with the Nakatomi family eventually winning power to put Crown Prince Tenji on the throne. He carried out Shotoku's ideas which were known as the great "Taika Reforms". (Ref. 12)

Despite these civilizing factors, within a generation of Prince Taishi's death a violent crisis appeared which included a terrible famine with thousands dying. Along with this developed a strange new religion called "Tokoyonomushi" in which devotees worshiped a large worm, drank sake and danced in the streets, giving away money. (Ref. 13) A palace revolution produced such a marked change that native historians refer to it as the "Great Reform" of 645. The Japanese government was reconstructed into an autocratic, imperial power. The sovereign was elevated from the leadership of the principal clan to paramount authority over every official in Japan, thus creating a closely-knit monarchical state. The emperors were allowed as many wives or consorts as desired and the heir to the throne was picked from any of his off-spring. The early emperors were devout Buddhists but Shintoism was never completely abandoned. Japan then had an embassy in China and Chinese civilization continued to be imported via Japanese students, monks and physicians studying in China. (Ref. 14)

In 670 when the old Nakatomi reformer who had put Tenji on the throne was dying, the emperor sent a pregnant concubine of his to comfort the old man. When the boy child was born the emperor gave him the name Fujiwara, and it was this boy's descendants, the Fujiwara clan, which took the place of the Nakotomis as the emperor's most intimate counselors for the next 1,275 years.

KOREA

China tried to conquer Korea again in 612 and failed but did essentially accomplish this in 668 as the Chou Empress Wu intervened in a Korean civil war and helped Silla to forge a united Korea while holding a few areas under Chinese suzertainty. As Koguryo was destroyed China also regained some Manchurian territory formerly dominated by these Koreans. Within two years Silla had pushed the Chinese out of Paekche and started the period which was the acme of Silla power and culture. Buddhism and its art flourished, particularly at the capital near the modern Kyongju. Skilled metal work was one of the special accomplishments.1

1D. 688 that Silla absorbed Paekche and Koguryo.  Their capital city had 178,936 households with 1,000,000 people and was one of the world's greatest cities of the time.  Buildings were roofed with tile and heated by charcoal. The burial burrows of that period are great archeology treasures. (Ref. 15)

SOUTHEAST ASIA

It is as difficult to record and explain the history of southeast Asia as it is the Balkan peninsula of Europe, in that in both the names and borders of many small countries have changed almost as rapidly as the years. In this 7th century there was a Cambodia where small Hindu temples were being built at Angkor Borei. A Sanskrit inscription in Cambodia of A.D. 604 shows a decimal position, suggesting an advanced knowledge of mathematics. The Funan Empire continued under control of Chenla and in Pyu (now Burma) a Buddhist capital of Srikshetra (now Hinawza) was founded some 200 miles north of present Rangoon, in 638. In Thailand the earliest kingdom was of a Mon people from lower Burma, who settled in the valley of River Menan and established a capital at Dvaravati, from which comes the name of their kingdom and their art. Under Isaravarman (611-635) the Khmers extended westward and developed great artistic and hydraulic engineering projects. (Ref. 16, 17, 18, 19)

In the Indonesian archipelago, the Empire of Srivijaya, based in Sumatra, dominated the straits of Sunda and Malacca and taxed the commerce in those waters for the next six centuries. Palembang, in southeast Sumatra, besides being the capital of that maritime empire, was a center of Sanskrit Culture. (Ref. 20)

1 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

4 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

5 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

6 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

7 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

8 [125]  Lyons, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

9 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

10 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

11 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

12 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

13 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

14 [125]  Lyons, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

15 [305] FOCKLER, SHIRLEY, "Kyongju", Travel Holiday, Sept. 1981, page 41.

16 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

17 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

18 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

19 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

20 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

The Far East: A.D. 701 to 800

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Continued T'ang Dynasty)

After the death of Empress Wu the true T'ang Dynasty resumed control. Of particular note is Ming Huang (or Hsuan Tsung) (712-756), the "Brilliant Emperor" under whom China stood in the very forefront of civilization, the most powerful, enlightened, progressive and best-governed empire on earth. By the middle of this 8th century the imperial officers began exchanging excess grain for various luxury goods and the effect was to expand a market for highly skilled artisan wares such as fine silks, porcelains, lacquer works, etc. A substantial enlargement of merchant and artisan classes ensued, with an increase in urban growth. Sugar cane, native to Bengal, was imported in China and adapted itself readily in the neighborhood of Canton where a wooded hinterland supplied the great amount of fuel necessary for its processing. Tea, known in Szechwan for centuries, now spread throughout the country. (Ref. 1) From the Han to the T'ang dynasties China's population had varied greatly but had now built back up to about 50 million people, kept from being still larger, at least in part, by infanticide. (Ref. 2, 3)

The army was professional and largely recruited from and commanded by "barbarians". In fighting with the expanding Arabs in west Turkistan, the Arabs were helped by the Karluk Turks, who attacked the Chinese from the rear. In the steppe, the Uigur and Girghiz Turks were now in control and the last of the Turkic peoples to reside in Mongolia. In China, proper, in 754, 75% of the total population lived north of the Yangtze River. The city of Ch'ang-an had 2,000,000 inhabitants with half of those living within the walled inner city of 30 square miles. A total of 26 cities had registered populations of over 500,000. The oldest datable printed materials were produced in 770 when 1,000,000 copies of a Buddhist charm were run off by commission from a Japanese empress. (Ref. 4, 5)

It has been said that Emperor Hsuan-tsung lived too long, because in 745 at age 60 he fell in love with one of his sons' concubines, Lady Yang (Yang Kuei-fei), and soon her family monopolized the most powerful ministerial posts. One of these, An Lu-Shan, an audacious Turk, had the run of the palace as Lady Yang 's adopted son. Soon thereafter when the "barbarians" of Asia again bore down on the Chinese borders, An Lu-Shan, then a general, rose in rebellion against the T'ang forces and they had to be recalled from the frontiers to defend the emperor. The rebellion was checked in 763, but the T'ang Dynasty had been eroded and Chinese power did not return to central Asia for six centuries. (See also previous section, this chapter). This type of revolt by a border "guard" was always a threat to the Chinese central authority and explains, in part, their continual efforts to keep the military under tight control. The same paranoia determined their policy of breaking up undue concentrations of wealth. No one - military commander or rich trader – was ever to be in a position to challenge the authority of the political ruler. (Ref. 6) In the An Lu-Shan revolt some 3, 500,000 lost their lives and this was followed in 762 by a plague in Shantung province with more than one-half of the people dying. The disease risk in the south was greater than the risk of death on the nomad frontier. (Ref. 7, 8) Intervention of the Uighur Turks from Mongolia helped to save the T'ang Dynasty after the tragedies, but thereafter the T'ang court was essentially a vassal of the Uighur khan. In this period of tragedy from revolt and disease, Chinese poets reached great heights, with Li Po becoming the "Keats" of China.

In Manchuria, the proto-Mongolian people, the Khitan, had begun to raid the Chinese border as early as 695 and they continued throughout this 8th century. A little to their east were the P'o-Hai, a powerful kingdom set on the Chinese model but established by the remnants of the Korean Koguryo nobles. They remained independent from 710 on for some two centuries. (Ref. 9)

JAPAN

We have previously indicated that for centuries it had been the custom for the Japanese royal family to change its capital each time a ruling emperor died. The so-called Nara period started with the capital at that city in 710, but this metropolis was too large to be torn down and moved each generation and that practice was stopped, at least until the final move to Kyoto in A.D. 794. Both Nara and Kyoto had been constructed using Baghdad as a model. (Ref. 10) After Emperor Kammu transferred his capital to Kyoto, Japanese art, previously under Chinese influences, developed its own mature style and taste. (Ref. 11) After Kammu's death the emperor's role deteriorated somewhat. Throughout this period, under Fujiwara ministers, court life had become a great pageant of ceremonies and costumes, and gradually the emperor's person, itself, became so taboo and awe-inspiring, as a rouged and gilded doll, that he began to be veiled from the world and the Fujiwaras took all responsibility for decisions, good or bad, shielding the throne. gradually came to believe in an emperor who was at the same time "a mortal god, a zero infinity, an impotent omnipotence"1. New civil and penal codes and the Yoro Laws, which were revisions of the Taiho Reforms, came into effect about 757 and gradually became more effective.

In 752 the Great Buddha at Nara, a 53 foot bronze figure, was dedicated as the cherished project of the Shomas. At the end of the century, in 790, Japan had a sustained epidemic with women under 30 years and males of all ages afflicted. (Ref. 13)

KOREA

Most of Korea was now united under the Silla Dynasty. Buddhism and art flourished, particularly at the capital on the site of modern Kyongju.

SOUTHEAST ASIA

The T'ai, or Shan, peoples had been infiltrating down into the southeast Asian peninsula for several centuries and now they formed a kingdom in Yunnan province of China.

The Dvaravati kingdom of Khmer people was Buddhist, rather than Brahman in religion, and in this century migrants were sent to the upper Menam Valley where they established the independent Kingdom of Haripunjaya, with a capital near the present Chiengmai. All of this occurred in what is now Thailand. Burma was under Indian influence and had Hindu commercial settlements on the Tenasserim coast and at the principal river mouths. In Cambodia the war-like course of the Chenlas was brought to an end when a king from Java entered and beheaded the Chenla ruler. Although the Javanese soon withdrew, that kingdom declined. On the Atlantic coast was Champa, under strong Indian influence. (Ref. 14, 15, 16)

Throughout the first millennium after Christ, but particularly from the 7th to the 16th century, Indian culture and religious influence spread throughout Indonesia and in particular it created a distinctive civilization in Java. This society, controlled by the Buddhist king of the Sailendra Dynasty, was second only to the Khmers in southeast Asia. (Ref. 17, 18) In this and the next century, Arab traders brought the Moslem religion to the Philippines and then, in turn, came the Indians. (Ref. 19)

1 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

2 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

3 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

4 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

5 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

6 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

7 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

8 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

9 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

10 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

11 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

12 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

13 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

14 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

15 [37] COLLINS, LARRY and LAPRERRE, DOMINIQUE, Freedom at Midnight. (Simon & Schuster, New York, 1975).

16 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

17 [18] BRITISH MUSEUM, (Personal notes, 1978).

18 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

19 [153] NANCE, JOHN, The Gentle Tasaday. (Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, Inc., New York 1975.

1.  The quotation is from Bergamini, (Ref. 12)

The Far East: A.D. 801 to 900

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Continued T'ang Dynasty)

The "Eastern Turks" pretty well dominated Manchuria at this time. In China it was an age of weak rulers with the emperor almost a vassal of the Uigur Khan. Even what power the emperor had was lost to the eunuchs of his court and the situation ended in violence. The first surge of religious persecution occurred between 843 and 846 when the rich Buddhist monasteries were suppressed, perhaps chiefly for fiscal reasons. In 845, 44,600 Buddhist establishments were destroyed, 260,500 monks and nuns were put back onto the tax lists and 150,000 of them were enslaved. Chinese Buddhism never recovered from this blow. In this connection it is interesting to note that in the far northwest corner of China there are 60 meter-high cliffs running for some 1,600 meters, near the town of Dunhuang, in which caves of various sizes had been filled with Buddhist sculptures for generations. There are still some 600 caves in as many as 4 levels. After A.D. 781 the area had been occupied by invading Tibetans but in 848 the latter were expelled and the caves came under control of local families nominally under allegiance to the Chinese T'angs but in actual fact acting as a separate kingdom throughout the remainder of the century and even after. In this way these beautiful art works were protected from the severe persecution of Buddhism occurring in the other parts of China. (Ref. 1) These Dunhuang caves are not the only ones of this type. We have previously mentioned the Caves of the Thousand Buddhas of Asia, on page 444, and now we should mention the Longmen Caves in the limestone cliff s just south of the capital of Luoyang along the Yi River in Henan province. Started in 494, these carvings were continued throughout the T'ang period and still show 1,300 grottoes, 750 niches and 40 pagodas decorated with almost 100,000 images. (Ref. 2)

In addition to the destruction of Buddhism, China suffered a series of bitter peasant rebellions between 874 and 883. In 1879 when the rebels took Canton, thousands of Moslems, Jews, Christians and Manicheans were slaughtered. Prior to this the Chinese had been tolerant of Manicheism, which was the religion of their erstwhile allies, the Uigur Turks. After the latter were defeated by the Kirghiz Turks in 840, however, the necessity for tolerance disappeared and Manicheism was banned along with Buddhism. (Ref. 3) Gunpowder was made in this century with saltpetre, sulfur and crushed charcoal, although it was not used in firearms for another two centuries. (Ref. 4)

JAPAN

The Fujiwaras ran Japan skillfully over most of the entire period from 670 to 950. They exerted influence partly through their sisters and daughters, who for 1300 years, were the chief source of wives and concubines of the palace so that Fujiwara women bore no less than 54 of the 76 emperors between 724 and Hirohito's birth in 1900. In A.D. 808 over 1/2 the population of Japan died of disease which may have been bubonic plague, since it had been on the China coast just prior to this. After that tragedy, however, Japan entered its Golden Age, with progress in civilization and technology which incidentally brought an increase in social distinctions. It was a period of handicrafts with silks, wood- work, porcelains, lacquers and painted paper screens. The court ate rice, radishes, fish, Soya-bean yogurts and cheese, with wild boar, venison and pheasant along with uncultivated vegetables such as bamboo shoots, mushrooms and lotus roots, but the peasants ate barley, millet, fish, oysters, seaweed, beans, radishes, wild herbs and ferns. Buddhism demanded no meat-eating and the court encouraged the people to be pious, while privately subsidizing guilds of butchers and meat cooks. (Ref. 5)

Other great families arose - the Taira, the Minamoto and Sugauara, who subsequently made and unmade emperors. They were military families who established heritary dictatorships, reducing the emperors apparently to mere puppets1. A simplified, somewhat phonetic, alphabet called "Hiragana" with 51 basic characters was developed to partially supplant the Chinese Konji with its thousands of characters. (Ref. 6) Disease hit again late in the century when the "coughing violence"2 struck in 861, 862 and 872. (Ref. 7, 8)

Buddhism persisted in Japan and won even greater support when Kukai brought the Shingon3 or Tantric sect back with him from China in 806, founding a monastery which became one of the great centers of Buddhism. Posthumously, Kukai was given the title Kobo Daishi (great teacher and propagator of Buddhist law) and the places associated with his early asceticism and the temples he founded later became objects of pilgrimage.

KOREA

As in China this was a period of political decline, although the Silla Dynasty remained in power. Buddhism survived here, even though it was under persecution and fading in China.

SOUTHEAST ASIA

Thailand continued under the Dvaravati control while the Burmese empire of Pagan superseded the fallen Pyu. Champa, Pegu and Thaton continued as separate and distinct states.

In Cambodia the Khmers' Chenla Dynasty, under Jayavarman II, set up three capitals in 802 in the Tonle Sap Lake region at the present site of Angkor and this became the center of a vast expanded Khmer Empire. They received Indian scholars, artists and political leaders while they continued to develop both Hindu and Buddhist art. Jayavarman II had himself declared a God-king, the earthly incarnation of Shiva, establishing a cult which provided legitimacy for 30 Khmer kings of Cambodia and its satellites. (Ref. 11, 12) About 885, Indravarman I constructed a vast irrigation system which sparked the great Angkorian Khmer Empire. Farmers were able to draw water in the long, dry, winter season and three rice crops a year became a possibility. Under this king the Khmers built Hariharalaya, 15 miles southeast of the site that was to become Ankor Thom. In addition, a year after his coronation, Indravarman had arranged for the excavation of a baray4 five miles long and a mile wide and in 881 he had begun the Bakong, the first great monument built entirely of masonry in Ankor. (Ref. 13, 14)

In the great southern islands there were the Srivijayan Empire of Sumatra and the Sailendra Empire of Java, with the latter the dominant nation of all southeast Asia in this century. Although there were some Hindus there, administration was Buddhist and their greatest architectural accomplishment was the majestic Borobudur, a stepped pyramid of unmortared andesate and basalt volcanic stones, standing 105 feet high with a base 403 feet square. Situated in the tropical forested Kedu Plain, it is a three dimensional model of the Mahayana Buddhist cosmos. Its 160 bas-relief sculptured panels represent the World of Desire and another 1,300 carved panels depict the World of Form, as they show scenes and teachings from the life of Buddha and Buddhist texts. (Ref. 15)

Elsewhere in that area, Arab dhows rode the monsoon winds for Zanzibar ivory, Malayan tin, Indian spices and China silk. These merchants carried Islam to Indonesia. Megaliths, recently discovered in remote areas of Borneo, date to this era. (Ref. 16, 17, 18, 19)

1 [282] PEKARIK, ANDREW J., "The Cave Temples of Dunbruang", Archaeology 36, Vol. 1: 20-27, Jan./Feb. 1983.

2 [285] KERSHAW, Norma, "Journey to the Caves of China", Archaeology 36, Vol. I: 66-69, Jan./Feb. 1983.

3 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

4 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

5 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

6 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

7 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

8 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

9 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

10 [200] STATLER, OLIVER, "Pilgrims' Path in Buddhist Japan", Great Religions of the World. (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

11 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

12 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

13 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

14 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

15 [286] MORTON, w. BROWN, III, "Indonesia Rescues Ancient Borobudur", National Geographic 163: 126-142, Jan. 1983.

16 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

17 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

18 [2] ABERCROMBIE, THOMAS J., "The Sweep of Islam.", Great Religions of the World, (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

19 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

1.  This has been the traditional western view, as for example in Toynbee, Reference 221, but more recent investigators have a different interpretation of the emperor's power. See JAPAN, next chapter

2.  This was probably whooping cough. (Ref. 9)

3.  Shingon means "The True Word". (Ref. 10)

4.  A "baray" is a reservoir for water.

The Far East: A.D. 901 to 1000

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (T'ang to 907, Divided Kingdom to 960 and then Sung Dynasty)

In Manchuria (and a part of Mongolia) Khitan tribes established the Liao Dynasty about A.D. 916 and overran part of China as the T'ang Dynasty collapsed. The Liao administration was well established in the P'o Hai area of eastern Manchuria by 934 and they executed invasions of northern China in 936 and 960, using siege machines, metaled corselets and helmets, with disciplined troops organized on a decimal system similar to that of the ancient Assyrians and the Mongol armies of the future. (Ref. 1) The name "Cathay" was derived from Khitae or Ch'i-tan, as they were sometimes called. They resisted Sinicization better than any other invader and retained their tribal nomadic life while remaining essentially Shamanists. Their use of human sacrifice and brutish punishments were particularly offensive to the Chinese. (Ref. 2, 3, 4, 5)

Having become the dominant war-lord of north China by 900, Chu Wen soon took the imperial T'ang court at Ch'ang-an under his protection and then slaughtered the ruling eunuchs. He followed this in 904 by murdering the emperor himself, installing a boy successor for three years and then taking over the throne personally. But with this turmoil and the Liao pressure, China broke up into the "Age of the Ten States". It was only in 960 that reunification was accomplished by General Chao-Kuang-yin who founded the northern Sung Dynasty, using a bureaucracy of Confucian officials and an almost socialistic control of the economy. The Sung, however, had to pay tribute to the Manchurian Liao all through this and the next century and they were never able to recover the northern tier of Chinese provinces.. In Charles Hucker 's classification the year 960 marks the end of the Early Empire of China. (Ref. 6)

Throughout all the political changes of the century the cave temples of Dunhuang, mentioned in the previous chapter, went undisturbed and, in fact, carving in the caves continued. Today there are still 492 grottoes on five distinct levels. (Ref. 7, 8) Paper money first appeared in A.D. 950 and the first report of chemical explosives for military use was in A.D. 1,000. By that time the Chinese seemed to have achieved biological accommodations to their previous infections and the population began to jump rapidly. In spite of malaria, bilharzias, and dengue fever the Yangtze Valley was finally conquered. (Ref. 9, 10)

By the year A.D. 1,000 China had reached its "modern" form and it changed very little thereafter until the 20th century. In comparison with the West, the limitations of this society were:

Human agriculture production (instead of animal and plow) kept a narrow margin between subsistence and production per agricultural head and gave less chance for a high standard of living for common people
A low level of peasant consumption of artisan products, which were essentially restricted to landlords and officials. European manufacturing, although on cruder material, catered to a wider base
Merchants were disreputable in China, as Confucius had ranked them near the bottom of the social scale. This inhibited the development of massive mercantile capital and hindered trade abroad. Thus, exploitation of Chinese inventions like paper, porcelain and gun-powder had to wait for the looser ordered society of western Europe. This was one of the side effects of the "command" system mentioned at the beginning of this chapter (Ref. 11, 12)

JAPAN

Under Daigo, greatest of the emperors set up by the Fujiwara clan, Japan continued to absorb and began to rival the culture and luxury of China. The period 901 to 922 is called the "Engi period" and was the acme of the Golden Age. Wealth accumulated and gave rise to great luxuriousness in dress, cuisine, manners, arts and tastes. Literature flourished as the syllabary simplification of Chinese characters allowed extensive writing in the Japanese language. In 905 the Kokinshu, an anthology of over 1,000 poems in Japanese, was completed by imperial order and within a century Japanese prose was to rise to great heights. The imperial family's Shintoism fell into disuse.

The curtain that the Fujiwaras put around the throne was not meant to stifle its occupant but only to shield it. When an emperor showed talent and interest he did not exercise power while remaining emperor, but would abdicate in favor of one of his children, go to a monastery, set up his own court and administration and there he would run the Fujiwaras, who ran Japan. It is Bergamini's (Ref. 13) concept that throughout history, even including the time of World War II and Pearl Harbor, that the imperial family always ran Japan, although they exerted their domination through the powerful families of the court, such as the Fujiwaras1. By A.D. 950 the emperors, who had never set up royal lands for their own income, found themselves dependent on the Fu jiwaras for money and at the same time the nation seemed to fall apart into baronial estates, each with its own Iron Age companies of soldiers. (Ref. 14, 15) Further epidemics of the "coughing violence" (probably whooping cough) between 920 and 923, mumps in 959 and an unknown pestilence of 994 and 995 when over one-half of the population of Japan died, undoubtedly contributed to the decay of the state as the century progressed. Chinese acupuncture had spread to Japan by the end of this century and a medical school was founded by Wake Hiroya, based on Chinese methodology. (Ref. 16, 17)

KOREA

In A.D. 918 the Koryo Dynasty began in west central Korea and was to rule for almost 500 years. By 935 it had peacefully absorbed the Silla area, uniting the country. Late in the century the Liao of Manchuria began to threaten the Koreans, just as they had the Chinese, and this was only the first of many invasions that occurred in the next several centuries. In this adversity the Koreans turned to Buddhism and built many temples. The ceramics of this period are perhaps the finest expression of Korean art. Chinese acupuncture had spread to Korea by the end of this century. (Ref. 20, 21, 22)

SOUTHEAST ASIA

After 15000 years the Vietnamese rebelled against the Chinese Sungs in the Red River Delta and gained independence as Dai Viet, or Annam, which is presently North Vietnam. Although traditionally hostile to the Chinese, these people absorbed much of the Chinese character, copied Chinese industrial and agricultural techniques and followed the Confucian political ethic. In Thailand, the Dvaravati continued in power and the great

Khmer Empire carried on in Cambodia with Yasovarman I proceeding with the fabulous construction projects, including a reservoir some five square miles in size and a stone pyramid to honor himself. (Ref. 23, 24)

In Java there was a shift of the cultural center to the eastern part of the island and this situation was to continue for the next five centuries. The great Buddhist temple of Borobudur in the center of Java, however, continued to inspire its followers. (Ref. 25) There was no significant change in Sumatra from the last century.

Southeast Asia's medical systems were a mixture of Chinese, Indian and Arabic disciplines. The Arabic influence, coming in part from the Greeks, showed up in the four humors (phlegm, blood, bile and wind) whereas Indian concepts were seen in the placement of the soul in the spinal column and instruction in methods of breathing. (Ref. 26, 27)

1 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

2 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

3 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

4 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

5 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

6 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

7 [282] PEKARIK, ANDREW J., "The Cave Temples of Dunbruang", Archaeology 36, Vol. 1: 20-27, Jan./Feb. 1983.

8 [285] KERSHAW, NORMA, "Journey to the Caves of China", Archaeology 36, Vol. I: 66-69, Jan./Feb. 1983.

9 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

10 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

11 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

12 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

13 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

14 [46] DURANT, WILL, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

15 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

16 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

17 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

18 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

19 [242] PEFFER, NATHANIAL, The Far East. (Univ. of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1958).

20 [173] RAMSEY L.G.G., The Complete Encyclopedia of Antiques. (Hawthorn Books, Inc., New York, 1962).

21 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

22 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

23 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

24 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

25 [286] MORTON, W. BROWN, III, "Indonesia Rescues Ancient Borobudur", National Geographic 163: 126-142, Jan. 1983.

26 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

27 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

1.  This concept of true power resting ultimately in the Japanese emperor from the beginning throughout history to the 20th century is a relatively new one, put forth by Bergamini in his book published in 1971. (Ref. 18) The previously unanimous view was typified in the 1958 text of Peffer (Ref. 19) when he says that: "In any analysis of the major elements in the composition of the Japanese scheme, the emperor deserves a minor place". (Page 39) He felt that the emperor's cabinet and Diet were the ornamental and dignified figureheads with the reality being in others, at least until very recent times

The Far East: A.D. 1001 to 1100

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Sung Dynasty)

The Northern Sung capital, Kaifeng, is said to have had over 50 theaters, some large enough for several thousand patrons, entertained by acrobats, dancers, clowns, musicians and actors. China, in this century, was the most populous, prosperous and cultured nation on earth. A new invasion in the northwest by Uigurs in A.D. 1035 and the rise of a Western Xia Dynasty (1032-1227) apparently did little damage to the main area of China, but they did cut off Dunhuany completely from the mainstream of Chinese culture. (Ref. 1)

After A.D. 1000 Neo-Confucianism, having absorbed important elements from Buddhism and Taoism, emerged unchallenged as the official intellectual system of China. This was a victory for the gentry as against the mercantile and military intruders, although industry continued to thrive. One of the greatest Sung advances was the introduction of the Champa rice, a new strain more drought resistant and faster ripening than previous varieties1. Even then, however, the southern Chinese never attempted to conquer the mountain regions. With insufficient draft animals the wretched mountain-dwellers grew rice on dry land and did not participate in the low-lander peasant prosperity. (Ref. 2)

Hundreds of workmen in the Kaifeng region were employed in large scale coal and iron complexes, accounting for about 1/2 of the country's total iron production. One huge complex at Ch'its'un in Hopei had 700 coal miners, 1,000 ore miners and 1,000 blast furnace workers, producing annually some 42,000 tons of coal and over 14,000 tons of pig iron. The national total iron production was 125,000 tons a year, by A.D. 1078. (Ref. 4) Although the principal of the blast furnaces had been known in China for 1,000 years, it was the use of coke in the early decades of this 11th century which solved not only the fuel shortage but greatly improved the iron and steel production. Canals connected the capital, Kaifeng, with Honan and Hopei and it became a vast market for the iron and steel. But the government continued to closely supervise the minting of coins (made from iron) and the manufacture of weapons and agricultural implements after 1083 with carefully controlled directives and taxation. A rising population meant that poverty did not disappear even in the face of the rising production, with the old story of "the rich got richer and the poor got poorer". (Ref. 5) It is one of the main hypotheses of the historian, William H. McNeill's recent book Pursuit of Power (Ref. 6) that China's rapid start toward industrialization and rapid change towards a market-regulated (as opposed to a "command" society) behavior in this and the next few centuries tipped a critical balance in world history. While politicians found it less and less possible to escape the effects of the financial market interchange, new forms of management and compromise between rulers, military power and money power had to be developed. (Ref. 7)

Paper currency was monopolized by the government in 1024. Movable type was available in 1040 as the invention of Pi Cheng, but little use was made of this and block type continued in use for a great profusion of literature. The compass was invented in the late part of this century. Inoculation for small-pox was accomplished by putting the crusts of pustules from active cases into the nose, a process which may have come from India. (Ref. 8, 9, 10, 11)

The years of the administration of Wang An Shih, Socialist prime minister as well as poet and writer, were from 1069 to 1076. He promoted regulation of industry, made codes of wages and prices, nationalized commerce, had state insurance against unemployment, poverty and old age and held examinations for public office. Wang An Shih considered that the carrying of arms was a disgrace, yet at the beginning of his term of office 80% of the government income was needed to support the approximately 1,000,000 despised soldiers. (Ref. 12) As taxes increased and military requirements expanded in order to repel northern invaders, opposition arose and finally the emperor discharged this illustrious premier and all those socialistic measures disappeared. (Ref. 13)

The main part of Manchuria, as well as adjacent Inner Mongolia, was ruled throughout this century, as well as the previous one, by the Liao Dynasty of the Khitan tribe. In the northwest another powerful kingdom, the Hsi-hsia, was founded by the Tibetan Tanguts in Ninghsia and Kansu (now Gansu). Both of these groups tended to raid the classical Chinese borders, but they were kept pretty well in check by "brotherly gifts" from the Sung court of large amounts of silver and bolts of silk2 Even then, punitive campaigns had to be launched against the Tanguts in 1069 and again in 1081 - 1082. Sung China had a standing army of 1,250,000 by this time, but the people were losing the will to fight. In the far north of eastern Manchuria among the proto-Manchu Jurchen tribes, a new leader appeared who was later to give China much trouble. This was Wan-yen a-Kuta (1068-1123). His people were originally forest hunters in the mountains of eastern Manchuria but they became tough cavalrymen whom both the Khitans and the Koreans tried to hold back by constructing walls and palisades. (Ref. 14, 15)

JAPAN

On the political front, this was the apex of the Fujiwara period. Michinaga's rule over his clan and the state resulted in some of the most brilliant decades of artistic and literary achievement, although there was much turbulence among the monks with frequent marches upon the capital and some actual fighting. In about 1080 the Minamoto clan in eastern and northern Japan began to establish dominance. The island population was not large enough to enable such killer diseases as measles to become endemic childhood illnesses and serious, repeated epidemics of these held back economic and cultural development of the islands. (Ref. 16)

KOREA

The greater part of this peninsula continued to be controlled by the kingdom of Koryo. As mentioned above, the Koreans were threatened by the Jurchen Manchurians and by 1044 the former had completed a great wall across the northern border of their country to keep out the invaders. (Ref. 17)

SOUTHEAST ASIA

MAINLAND SOUTHEAST ASIA

Burma--In the first 1,000 years of the Christian era Indian forms of society, religion and arts had been carried to Burma by traders and colonists, but in this 11th century, having conquered and absorbed their non-Burmese neighbors, including Mon, Shans, Karens and Arakanese, the Burmese established their own kingdom which was to last 200 years.

King Anawratha introduced Buddhism, ruling from Pagan in upper Burma on the Irrawaddy River, as the major political and artistic center. The Burmese language was developed and Buddhist scriptures were translated into this tongue. (Ref. 18, 19)

Thailand

This became a province of the great Khmer Empire of Cambodia in this century. It was a river empire on the lower Mekong. (Ref. 20)

Angkor

The main Khmer kingdom continued toward the peak of its civilization around Angkor. (Ref. 21)

Champa: Annam

This area, which is now North Viet Nam, became independent of China. This was the source of early maturing rice which, when imported in China, allowed the two harvests a year.

INDONESIA AND ADJACENT ISLANDS

Sumatra--Srivijuya was a prominent, Indianized state which was attacked by the Cholas of southern India near the end of the century. Following this attack their empire began to decline.

Java

In 1006 a disaster struck in the center of Java in the region of the great temple of Borobudur. A devastating earthquake and the eruption of the volcano Merapi covered the landscape and the temple with lava, ash and land slides. The population fled, probably to the eastern part of the island where Majapahit arose as another great Indianized state. The holy Buddhist place was abandoned and forgotten for more than 800 years, with time and weather and earthquakes taking their toll. (Ref. 22)

1 [282] PEKARIK, ANDREW J., "The Cave Temples of Dunbruang", Archaeology 36, Vol. 1: 20-27, Jan./Feb. 1983.

2 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

3 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

4 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

5 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

6 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

7 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

8 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

9 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., m.d. and PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

10 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

11 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

12 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

13 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

14 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

15 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

16 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

17 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

18 [19] British Museum Guide, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

19 [175] Readers Digest, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

20 [19] British Museum Guide, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

21 [176] Readers Digest, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

22 [286] MORTON, w. Brown, III, "Indonesia Rescues Ancient Borobudur", National Geographic 163: 126-142, Jan. 1983.

1.  In later centuries this was to be reduced to 30 days, through seed breeding. (Ref. 3)

2.  It is interesting to recall that at this same time the English were similarly paying Danegeld to hold off the Danes

The Far East: A.D. 1101 to 1200

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Sung to 1127, then Southern Sung Dynasty)

At this time there were perhaps 100,000,000 people in China. There was notable development of maritime and rivertine trade and great cities arose on the coast and along the Yangtze River, with merchant vessels going to the Indian Ocean and South Asia. Cotton sails1, adjustable center-boards, larger vessels and the compass all contributed to this increased sea activity. The mathematicians of China of this era may have been the best in the world. Gun-powder was first used in war in 1161. (Ref. 1) Although there was general prosperity paupers were not eliminated and impoverished rural folks swarmed into towns hoping for work, even as has occurred throughout the world many, many times since. Public relief activities were begun in 1103 but were only partially successful and even in 1125 some were still sleeping in the streets.

The Tungusic speaking tribes of central Manchuria, the Jurchen, who were the ancestors of the later Manchus, arose against their Khitan masters in Manchuria in 1114 under the leadership of Wan-yen A-ku-ta, proclaimed the Chin Dynasty2 and aided by the Chinese Sung, destroyed the Liao Empire as early as 1125, taking Peking in 1126. Then the Chin turned on the Sung and conquered all of north China, leaving terrible devastation behind them. The Jurchen had already gained access to Chinese artisan skills and had improved armor and a greater supply of metal for weapons. (Ref. 3) The northern Sung capital, Kaifeng, was soon brought under siege and when that city ran out of supplies and the people had to turn to cannibalism, the Sung government withdrew and headed south to what is now known as Hangchow. For more than a decade Jurchen and Chinese armies struggled for control of the Yangtze Valley. After 1127 the Chinese dynasty was known as the "Southern Sung", who established their new capital at Hangchow in 1138. They came to rely on specially designed warships to guard against the Jurchen horsemen. These vessels included armored ships driven by treadmills and paddle wheels, used particularly for river and canal fighting. Crossbowmen, pikemen and projectile throwing machines were mainstays; hundreds of ships and as many as 52,000 men were used. (Ref. 4)

In spite of continued political and military troubles Chinese economy and culture flourished with new agricultural technology and productivity. The south coastal regions were fully assimilated and populated by Chinese and merchant ships from Southeast Asia and the Indian Ocean jammed the coastal harbors. The mountainous topography south of the Yangtze hindered the use of canals and riverways there so the merchants had to take to the open seas. Commerce with other peoples could be subject to excise taxes and by 1137 about 1/5 of the emperor's government income came from those taxes on maritime trade. Hang-chow had a population in the millions. Both block and movable type was used to promote printing and great libraries were collected. The heavy military cost, the tributary payments which had to be made to the Jurchen and heavy reliance on paper money led to increasing inflation and increasing inequities between the rich and the poor. (Ref. 6, 7, 8, 9)

Chu Hsi (1130-1200) saved Confucianism for the Chinese by building upon the loose aphorisms of Confucius an orderly system of philosophy which helped the political and intellectual life for the next seven centuries. In the meantime the Jurchens had established the Chin (also Kin) Dynasty, with a capital at Peking. (Ref. 10, 11)

JAPAN

An ex-emperor, Shirakawa, effective ruler for two children emperors, in 1126 decreed a strict Buddhist rule against killing any living thing and even all fish-nets were collected and burned. (Ref. 12) But this was a feudal age in Japan and local sources of authority grew in power as a distant government failed to maintain security and order. The people paid taxes to Shoguns, or generals, rather than to the central government. About 1192 a member of the Minamoto clan, Yoritoma, getting his title of Shogun3 from the Emperor Go Toba, gathered an army and established an independent military authority at Kamakura. For the next several hundred years, although they never entirely ruled Japan, the Shoguns held the balance of military power in the nation while the emperors retained the spiritual powers. As indicated on page 530, in effect the emperors were "shielded" from foreign eyes while still remaining supreme in the final national decisions. Cultural activities continued and by this 12th century Japanese lacquer had surpassed both Chinese and Korean. By 1185 Kyotohad about 1,500,000 people, surpassed probably only by Constantinople, Cordoba and possibly Hangchow.

KOREA

The Jurchen Chin Dynasty of Manchuria forced the - Koryo kingdom of Korea to submission early in the century. This affected the people as a whole very little and there was no change then until 1170 when military officers seized the government and condemned Buddhism, describing it as dangerous. Some 26 years passed before the Ch'oe family could gain central control again and establish a new native dynasty.

SOUTHEAST ASIA

Burma remained a fully sovereign state in its Pagan Period. Thailand continued as part of the Khmer Empire which now reached its greatest extent in Cambodia under Suryavarman II (1113-1150), who built the temple tomb of Angkor Wat and extended the Angkor power from the China Sea to the Indian Ocean. This great power and wealth was continued under Jayavarman VII at the end of the century, even though in between these two great leaders, considerable trouble had developed with a civil uprising and a murderous invasion in 1170 by neighboring Chams, who actually temporarily took Angkor. In Indonesia, Sumatra and Java remained as separate entities, as in the last century. (Ref. 14, 15, 16, 17)

1 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

2 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

3 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

4 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

5 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

6 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

7 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

8 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

9 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

10 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

11 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

12 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

13 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

14 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

15 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

16 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

17 [176] READERS DIGEST,The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

1.  Cotton reached China from India in this century and spread extremely rapidly. (Ref. 2)

2.  "Chin" here means "gold", as a symbolic name for the Jurchen Dynasty. (Ref. 5)

3.  The complete title was "Sei-i Dai Shogun", meaning "Great Barbarian-suppressing General". (Ref. 13)

The Far East: A.D. 1201 to 1300

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Southern Sung to 1279, Yuan after 1264)

Before the Mongols hit China in this century it was more populous, productive, wealthy, orderly and stable and had a more advanced science and technology than contemporary Europe. It was the world's greatest power and its culture the most splendid, with the Jurchen Chin, now Sinicized considerably, ruling in the north and the Sung in the south. Hangchow, at the height of the Southern Sung days, is said to have had a population between 1,000,000 and 1,500,000, with 17 amusement districts, including theaters with multiple tiers of balconies. Although coke was probably known to the Chinese at this time, they did not utilize it, waiting for England to do so five centuries later as the breakthrough inaugurating the industrial revolution. They did have excellent steel, however, and China was probably the original source of damask steel, as we have previously intimated. (Ref. 1)

China bore the brunt of the Mongol invasion more than any other country. It has been postulated that the gradual drying up of the regions behind the northwestern frontier, making the desert incapable of supporting the hardy Mongol population, had forced them, under their fiery leader Genghis Khan, to win new fields. He had ridden some 1,200 miles across the Gobi Desert and pierced the Great Wall of China, invading the independent Chin Empire as early as 1211. Then, while preparing to invade Khwarizm, the khan had left the eastern campaign against the Chin to Mukali. In this conquest of northern China, the Mongols caused immense destruction. Much of the land went out of cultivation, ninety some towns were left in rubble and Peking burned for more than a month in 1215. When Mukali died, the emperor of Chin signed a treaty with the Great Khan's impudent vassal, the king of the Tibetan Tanguts of the imperial state of Hsi Hsia. Later in the 1220s Genghis again personally started for China but decided to liquidate the Tanguts on the way. When the Mongols reached the Tangut stronghold at Ning-Hsia on the old China Wall, the old khan had actually died enroute, but the gates were forced open and every living creature was slaughtered. On the return to Mongolia Genghis was buried, along with 40 jewelled slave girls and 40 fine horses. (Ref. 2, 3, 4, 5)

Genghis Khan's successors, Ogedei, Mangku and Kublai in turn continued aggression against the Southern Sung, with Kublai finally establishing the Yuan1 Dynasty of China in 12602. Kublai is known in Chinese history by his posthumous temple designation, Shih-tsu. The Sung valiantly defended two walled cities in the Yangtze Valley, Hsiang-yang and Fan-ch'eng, but the Mongols brought in siege specialists from the Near East and with the help of a newly built navy conquered both in 1273 after 4 or 5 years of almost continuous siege. The Asians then surged through the south, taking Hangchow in 1276. The khan and his family had no political need to adopt the Toaist religion of their Chinese subjects because the latter took no part in the high government and were treated as second class citizens, forbidden to marry Mongols or learn their language. Kublai did not share his grandfather's admiration for the Chinese learned Mandarins and his ministers were Moslems, Nestorians or Buddhists from the western part of the empire. If Kublai had any preference it was for the Shamanistic Tibetan version of Buddhism. In 1260 the Lama 'Phags-pa, best remembered for devising an alphabetic script for the Mongolian language, was named Kublai's mentor and given viceregal authority in Tibet.

For awhile Kublai Khan had as his "roving secretary of state" the Catholic, Marco Polo, who was especially impressed with the size of the capital city, Kanbalu (Peking) and with the road system which included the posting stations, each having up to 400 horses. He estimated that the Great Khan kept some 200,000 horses and 10,000 posts on the Silk Road. (Ref. 9) The Khan insisted on imperial administration of the iron producing regions of Hopei and Honan but by that time production had sunk from the previous 35,000 tons per annum down to about 8,000 tons and this was exclusively consigned to equipping the Mongol armies with armor and weapons. Iron production was not restored to its former level, in part because of vast disasters to the canal system following an 1194 flooding of the Yellow River, with subsequent establishment of a new path to the sea. The canals were never restored. (Ref. 10)

At the time of Polo's visit to Hangchow, ships from the Indies brought spices and left with Chinese silks. This was a metropolitan city with Arabs, Persians and Christians and there were hotels, restaurants, taverns and tea houses. Under the Yuan Dynasty, however, the country's productivity fell and commerce was disrupted. In the countryside people ate snakes, grasshoppers and rats. Southwestern China, the present Szechuan and Yunnan, had a different people, cut off from the rest of the nation and there Marco Polo3 ate mutton, buffalo beef and poultry - raw. In far western China at Jiayuguan, the mul- berry trees died of neglect as the Silk Route had shifted to the north and for this and the next centuries, life in this area was very harsh. In contrast, northern China still apparently grew much grain. (Ref. 11, 12, 13, 14, 15)

In spite of many deficiencies, Kublai did promote many public projects, patronized education, letters and arts, carried out many socialistic measures4, revised the calendar and promoted architecture to its greatest height, but he never truly became Sinicized. When he died in 1294, the titular supremacy of the Supreme Khan disappeared, but at its highest point this far eastern Mongol Empire contained all of China, Korea, some of Southeast Asia and Mongolia. (Ref. 16)

As in India, metallic guns were in use in China by 1275. (Ref. 18) Economic difficulties of this and the next century, inherent in the archaic circulation of heavy caixas of copper or iron and the enlivened external trade along the Silk Route, was partially solved by the use of paper money. This not only facilitated internal payments between provinces but reserved silver for trade with Central Asia and the West. (Ref. 19)

JAPAN

About 1200 Zen Buddhism arrived in Japan from China as an antagonist to the ritualism and intellectualism of earlier sects. As the Kamakura Bakufu Dynasty weakened, a rival family had set up the Hojo Regency in 1199, ruling the Shoguns, who in turn "ruled" the emperors for the next 134 years. In 1268, during the supremacy of the first shogun family, the Genji, envoys from Kublai Khan arrived in Japan with a letter ordering that country to submit to Mongol suzerainty or be invaded. The envoys were returned with no answer, so Kublai ordered his vassal kings in Korea to construct a great invasion fleet and for six years both nations prepared for the coming battle. In 1274, 15,000 Mongols and 8,000 Koreans5 sailed for southern Japan, first attacking two small islands just off Kyushu. The Japanese garrisons on the islands fought until the last man was dead. The invasion fleet then landed at Hakata where the Japanese fought a savage holding action on the beaches, awaiting reinforcements from central Kyushu. When a severe storm came that night, sinking 200 ships, the Mongol generals, who had already lost 13,000 of their 23,000 men, had an excuse to retreat to Korea. Kublai Khan was not about to give up, however, and in the following year he again sent envoys to Japan demanding surrender. This time the envoys heads were cut off, in the charming manner often seen in those times. Kublai was busy advancing into south China at the moment, so it was another six years before he returned to launch his next attack on Japan. In the meantime the Japanese had built hundreds of firefly boats to harass the Chinese war junks and had constructed a stone wall more than 100 miles long and 2,5 meters high with which to contain the most likely beachheads in Hakata Bay. In 1281 Kublai impressed all the junks of Canton and Korea and sent 4,400 ships and an army of 142,000 troops6, including 40,000 of his own Mongols, landing them in greatest strength at the two ends of the stone wall in Hakata Bay. There was desperate hand to hand battle for 53 days before a hurricane Kamikaze, "the divine wind", arrived to almost destroy the N,ongol fleet over a 48 hour period. Only perhaps one-half of the 140,000 Chinese and Mongols returned to the mainland. Some estimates give 4,000 ships sunk and 100,000 casualties. The Mongols never threatened Japan again.

Only in this century did Japan's population become great enough to allow the threshold to be crossed from epidemic to endemic disease, so that measles and small-pox became "children's diseases". The dynamic growth occurred with the population jumping from 4,410,000 about A.D. 1000 to 9,750,000 by about A.D. 1200. (Ref. 22)

KOREA

After the Mongols had conquered the Chin on the northern Chinese mainland, they reached Korea by 1235 and through intermarriage, the Koryo kings became merely a branch of the Mongol imperial family. This, and the rise of Confucianismn, led to acceptance of Chinese leadership in political and cultural matters. Mongol influence remained until well into the middle of the next century. (Ref. 23, 24, 25)

SOUTHEAST ASIA

In Burma, Ava developed on the upper Irrawaddy, Toungoo on the Sittang and Pegu became the capital of a new Mon kingdom of the south. All of these were Theravada

Buddhist areas and they had stupas, not temples, as places of worship. Ancestors of the modern Thai entered the country from Yunnan and founded dynasties with capitals at Cheingmae and Ayuthia (near modern Bangkok). By the end of the century Buddhist monks from Ceylon had converted the Thai and there resulted Buddhist art and ceramics, with a marked preference for a green glaze, imitating the famous Chinese celadon. (Ref. 26)

We noted in the last chapter that the Chams had taken over Angkor, but Jayavarman VII, although already in his 50s, launched a merciless counter-attack and drove them out, allowing him then to continue to build Angkor's royal city complex. He rebuilt Angkor Thom as his own royal capital and added 10 miles to the original walls of the city as well as constructing many monuments and temples in all the cities of his empire. He also ordered 102 hospitals and 121 hostelries built along the hundreds of miles of highways. Jayavarman VII died about 1219 and from then on no Khmer king undertook such projects and the dynasty actually went into decline. Many social and economic factors contributed to this weakness, including the gradual migration of the Thais and Vietnamese southward out of the Khmer sphere of influence. The capital city, however, maintained its magnificence. (Ref. 27) Phnom Penh was developed on the Mekong in this century. After Mongol attacks, Burma, Siam, Annan and Champa all accepted vassal status to the Yuan Dynasty.

One Mongol expedition, using a rebuilt navy, even hit Java in 1292 and 1293, but no settlements were made and they did not establish enduring control over the island. They did help a son-in-law of a recently killed king of the Srivijaya Dynasty put down the rebel murderers, but then the Mongols themselves were trapped and the son-in-law, Vijaya, started a new dynasty with a capital at Majapahit. This Hindu empire ruled a large part of present day Indonesia from 1291 to 1513, although Islam was already being brought to Sumatra by Arab traders. (Ref. 28, 29, 30, 31)

The use of metallic guns drifted into southeast Asia at the end of the century from India and China, so that it is possible that Philippinos saw gun-fire before Frenchmen did. (Ref. 32)

1 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

4 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

5 [27] CHAMBERS, James, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

6 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

7 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

8 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

9 [247] Winn, MICHAEL, "Following the trail of Marco Polo across the roof of Central Asia", Smithsonian 13: No. 1, pp. 46-55, Apr. 1982.

10 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

11 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

12 [27] CHAMBERS, James, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

13 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

14 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

15 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

16 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

17 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

18 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

19 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

20 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

21 [278] MOZAI, Torao, "The Lost Fleet of Kublai Khan", National Geographic 162: 635-649, Nov. 1982.

22 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

23 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

24 [64] Farb, Peter, Man's Rise to Civilization. (E.P. Dutton & Co., New York, 1968).

25 [175] Readers Digest, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

26 [19] British Museum Guide, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

27 [176] Readers Digest, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

28 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

29 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

30 [175] Readers Digest, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

31 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

32 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

1.  "Yuan" means "a beginning"

2.  This date is from Chambers (Ref. 6) Others, such as The Times Atlas of World History, (Ref. 7), state that this dynasty began at 1280 and Charles Hucker (Ref. 8) gives 1264

3.  See map of Marco Polo's journeys on page 753

4.  The source for this, Will Durant (Ref. 17), assumed that socialistic measures were always good

5.  These are Bergamini's figures. (Ref. 20) Mozai (Ref. 21) says there were 40,000 men in 900 ships

6.  This represents about 34 times as many ships and 5 times as many men as in the famous Spanish Armada

The Far East: A.D. 1301 to 1400

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Yuan Dynasty to 1368, then Ming)

By the beginning of this century the use of moveable, wooden characters for printing had become widespread in China and had even spread to - Turkestan. (Ref. 1) In the early decades as much grain was carried in seagoing vessels as moved on the canals, in part because improvement of navigation techniques shortened the sea trip along the coast. The use of great rafts began at this time with tree trunks tied together with a type of wicker rope to bring wood from Szechwan down to Peking. For the open sea they had large, four-deck junks with water-tight compartments, four to six masts carrying up to 12 large sails and manned by about 1,000 men. Local rebellions and sea piracy soon became problems that interfered with long distance shipping, however, and even before the collapse of the Mongol Dynasty sea shipments had become markedly reduced. (Ref. 2, 3) The use of the Chinese abacus for calculations and the Indian decimal system had already traveled to the western world across the southern seas and had helped to stimulate trade.

The Yuan (Mongol) Dynasty faltered as the Mongols lost power in Europe and western Asia. The bubonic plague spread eastward, also, so that in 1331 9/10 of the population of Hopei died and between 1353 and 1354 perhaps 2/3 of the entire population of China expired. This, combined with civil war occurring as the Mongols were beginning to be overthrown after 1335, along with disastrous floods in the eastern plains from 1254 to 1359, wrecked havoc on China's population and it dropped from 123 million about A.D. 1,200 to 65 million in 1393. The revolt against the Yuan rulers was led in 1368 by an ex-Buddhist monk, Chu Yuan-chang, who burned the great Mongol center at Karakorum in the Gobi desert and entered Nanking in triumph, proclaiming himself the first emperor of the Ming or Brilliant Dynasty. It was not until 1387-8 that all of China was conquered and the Mongols were finally completely defeated. The use of cannon by the Mings helped in their victory. (Ref. 4, 5)

The Ming revised agriculture by rebuilding irrigation and drainage works and carrying out reforestation projects so that another period of prosperity developed by the end of the century. By 1380 the population of the south was 21/2 times that of the north, because of rice cultivation, with 2 or 3 harvests a year. (Ref.6) At first the Ming had an aggressive foreign policy, with campaigns against the Mongols in the far north and- the restoration of Korea to vassal status. (1369). The Ming also rebuilt the navy. A Chinese ship of that period, now being recovered from under water near South Korea, reveals a three-masted junk with squared off ends, flat bottom without keel and bulk heads dividing the ship into compartments. The ship had many treasures, including porcelain, lacquer ware and bronze and iron cooking utensils and silver and iron ingots. (Ref. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11)

Chaulmoogra Oil was used for leprosy in this century, but even the Chinese seemed to find no solution for the plague. Tuberculosis may have occurred and venereal disease, although not well defined, was present and treated with a variety of therapies, including metals. (Ref. 12, 13)

JAPAN

After their victory over the Mongols, which was detailed in the last chapter, the Japanese fought among themselves and the role of the Shoguns in Kamakura deteriorated. In 1333 the Hojos power came to an end as Go Daigo got the rival Minamoto and Ashikaga clans rallied to him to defeat the degenerated Hojos and make him emperor. The Ashikagas then turned on Go Daigo, however, and established their own puppet emperor, Kogon, organizing the Ashikaga Shogunate which was to rule for 250 years of chaos and civil war. In this period in Japan, skill at arms, rather than family pedigree, was the best way to win and hold land.

There were two imperial courts from 1339 to 1392, a southern and a northern one. True Shintoists considered the former to be the true court because it had the imperial regalia - the mirror, sword and necklace. Actually, by the rules of primogeniture, the northerners had the better claim, but in 1392 they accepted a big financial settlement and ended the schism by returning to Kyoto. But settling the schism brought no lasting peace and civil wars raged on continuously in the next century. (Ref. 14)

KOREA

Surviving a short period of Mongolian overlordship, the Koryo Dynasty continued through most of this century as in the previous one, subject, however, to Ming overlordship after 1369. In 1392 General Yi Song-gye, with the help of the Mings, overthrew the Koryos and took over the throne in Songdo (Kaesong), which is now in North Korea. He then changed his capital to Hansong (present day Seoul) and ruled as king of the Yi Dynasty, one which was to dominate Korea for the next 500 years. Yi Song-gye later became known as King Taejo, which means "great original ancestor". This new dynasty rejected Buddhism in favor of Chinese Confucianism. (Ref. 15, 16)

SOUTHEAST ASIA

In the area of Burma several independent states emerged - the Burmese proper about Ava in the north and Mons about the city of Pegu in the south, but other peoples were evolving slowly, also. In Siam, the Thai political center moved south to Aijutthaya about 1350 and formed the modern state of Thailand. The Thai converted to Buddhism, but the Moslems won the coasts. The Khmers now had abandoned Ankor and retreated to the Mekong. Pagan declined after the Mongol invasion and Shan princes assumed rule over the northern portions. The Shans were Theravada Buddhists who lived with a distinctive structure of feudal states. The men wore turbans and were of ten heavily tattooed. In Vietnam, the Chinese lost their hold and a new kingdom, Dai-Viet, appeared and absorbed the Kingdom of Champa. (Ref. 17)

Islam had pretty well won the contest of religions in the southern island empires. On Sumatra, Malacca took the place of Srivijaya and Islam began to spread into the archipelago to be halted only two centuries later by the Spanish seizure of Manila. The Empire of Majapahit continued as the greatest of the Indo-Javanese kingdoms and Arabs and Persians came there to trade. The Malays, who settled the peninsula named after them, came in this century from Sumatra. (Ref. 18)

1 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

2 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

3 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

4 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

5 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

6 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

7 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

8 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

9 [112] KEITH, DONALD H., "A 14th Century Cargo Makes Port at Last", National Geographic 156: 231, Aug. 1979.

10 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

11 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

12 [12] BERGAMINI, David, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

13 [125  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

14 [12] BERGAMINI, David, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

15 [113] Kim, h. EDWARDS, "Seoul: Korean Showcase", National Geographic 156: 770, Dec. 1979.

16 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

17 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

18 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

The Far East: A.D. 1401 to 1500

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Ming Dynasty)

In 1428 the Ming Empire was divided into thirteen provinces, plus the two metropolitan areas of Peking and Nanking. China's canal system was enlarged and nothing in the world equaled China's internal water traffic and trade. Eventually some of the river rafts were three miles long, able to ingeniously fold so as to make the bends in the rivers. (Ref. 1) Fortunately the invention and construction of deep water locks throughout the length of the Grand Canal allowed the use of that canal 12 months a year, without having to worry about high and low water periods. (Ref. 2)

In addition, great maritime expeditions established Chinese hegemony over the key commercial centers of the Indian Ocean, the Malacca straits, Ceylon, Calicut and less definitely at the Persian Gulf. By 1420 the navy was comprised of at least 3,800 ships of which 1,350 were fighting vessels, including 400 large floating fortresses. (Ref. 3) Between 1405 and 1433 a Chinese Admiral Cheng-ho, actually a Moslem eunuch, had made seven voyages into the Indian Ocean, bringing back objects from Java, Ceylon and even East Africa. He had 62 ships, the largest vessels probably displacing about 1,500 tons1 and carrying 28,000 men. Including the expeditions under other leaders there were perhaps some 250 vessels participating in the various overseas projects, all of which came to an abrupt halt in 1434 when the emperor suddenly ordered the expeditions stopped and prohibited any further ship construction. The result of this was delivery of the China coast into the hands of the Japanese2 and Malay pirates along with the Portuguese sailors. (Ref. 4, 5, 6, 7)

Politically, Ming China was somewhat subdued, because of the previous excesses of the Mongol Dynasty and some conscious social leveling affected by the early Ming rulers.

The rich were humbled, slavery was abolished and the poor were pampered with low rental, state land and gifts of seeds, tools and farm animals. China received her horses from Asia, particularly through special frontier fairs in Mongolia and Manchuria. (Ref. 10) Fairs were not seen in the number and way that we met in Europe. When the nation was pretty well unified under the Mings, the fairs almost -completely disappeared from the interior and appeared only on the external frontiers, as noted regarding the horse fairs near Manchuria. Occasionally a caravan would arrive from Moscow, setting up fairs in Hanchu or Cheng Tun. (Ref. 11)

In the first half of the century metal characters for use as moveable type were perfected (this may actually have been done in Korea) and these soon became widely used for 50 years before the Gutenberg "invention". Inflation, which had been occurring over several centuries, now reached the point where 1,000 paper notes were required for 3 caixas of cash, so the state abandoned the paper money and private banks put it out only for local needs. As paper money disappeared, rice reappeared as a money substitute for ex- change. (Ref. 12)

There was still intermittent warfare and civil uprisings. The third Ming emperor, Ch'eng-tsu, came to power by overthrowing his nephew, after three years of civil war, but he rebuilt Peking and reconstructed the silted-up Grand Canal, thus allowing grain and textiles to come to the city from the rich southeast. He bullied Japan into nominal vassalage for the first time. In the middle of the century the emperor Ying-tsung (era name - Tien-shun) was taken captive and his court slaughtered by a Mongol raider, Esen. Rural problems also led to a number of rebellions, chiefly in the central and southeastern China, leading to a million deaths. (Ref. 13, 14)

JAPAN

Although organization and administration was sometimes neglected and chaotic, many of the dictators of the Ashikaga Shogunate were patrons of the arts and collected pieces that are prizes of collectors today. Local rulers of wide territories were called daimyos, meaning "feudal lords" and their subordinate soldiery were samurai, a word originally simply meaning "attendant". In the civil wars which raged throughout Japan, sometimes an entire clan family would be killed off and then their remaining fighting retainers would become masterless samurai or- ronin (wave-men). Some of these became pirates, terrorizing the coast of China and even the Philippines. (Ref. 15) In 1428, transport workers struck in protest against high prices and they, backed by farmers, rioted in the streets and wrecked warehouses, temples and houses. (Ref. 16)

Towns developed, eventually becoming the modern cities of Osaka, Kobe and Fukuoka. Kyoto was the undisputed political and cultural capital. This was still a thoroughly Buddhist age in Japan, but intellectual life began to free itself from the bonds of religion. The Ashikaga power began to decline early in the century and the Onin War (1467-77) began a hundred years of strife between the feudal lords. (Ref. 17, 18)

KOREA

The new Yi Dynasty was dominated by the Chinese and there was a suppression of Buddhism. Japanese pirate raids subsided somewhat and Korea had a period of great prosperity and cultural development. King Sejong (1419-1451) was a great patron of learning. It was at this time that the native phonetic script called "Onmum" was introduced and it is possible that the movable metal printing characters mentioned above were actually developed in Korea. (Ref. 19, 20)

SOUTHEAST ASIA

The Chinese Ming occupied Annam (Vietnam), through their navy, from 1407 to 1427, but then met resistance and finally allowed the region its independence in 1428. A Lao tribal monarch established the Laotian Kingdom of Lan Xang in mid-century. This included present day Laos and much of northern and eastern Thailand. The Siamese (Thai), under King Trailok, had centralized bureaucracy and a codified system of law. They ravaged Angkor in 1431 and took over a great part of the southern Khmer Empire, leaving them only what is now the general area of Cambodia and which was then called "Kambuja". After the sacking of Angkor the Siamese went home with as much loot as they could carry and when they returned for more a year later the city, where once there had been a million people, was deserted. No one knows where the people went, but through neglect the huge reservoirs, canals, roads and bridges all gave way to the jungle. (Ref. 21, 22, 23) Braudel (Ref. 24) says that the Siamese attacks upset the daily life and agriculture so that the rice field water cleared, allowing the malaria carrying mosquitoes to thrive and that the disease apparently decimated the population.

Northern Burma was under the Shan power while southern Burma was under the Mon (Pegu). The new Vietnamese kingdom of Dai-Viet gradually absorbed Champa territory, annexing its capital, Vijaya, in 1471. (Ref. 25)

Since the Moluccas Islands and Malay, along with Ceylon, were the source of almost all spices, Malacca became an international port, shipping to China and the Malabar coast of India from where Arabs, Indians and Persians took over for further distribution. Built in a dismal swamp almost inaccessible by land, Malacca had been of no importance except as a pirate storage headquarters until in this and the preceding century it became a port for peaceable shipping. (Ref. 26) The men of Islam overthrew the old Majapahit Empire and their religion, which had been introduced into the Malayan archipelago from India in the 10th century, now finally became dominant as the Hindus were driven to Bali and a few other islands. (Ref. 27, 28)

1 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

2 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

3 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

4 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

5 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

6 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

7 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

8 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

9 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

10 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

11 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

12 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

13 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

14 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

15 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

16 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

17 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

18 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

19 [233] Wheat, Joe Ben, "A Paleo-Indian Bison Kill", Scientific American, Jan. 1967, page 44.

20 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

21 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

22 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

23 [176] Readers Digest, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

24 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

25 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

26 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

27 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

28 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

1.  In comparison, Vasco da Gama's flagship displaced only 300 tons. (Ref. 8)

2.  Although the Japanese were blamed, McNeill (Ref. 9) says that these actually were chiefly Chinese merchant sailors who now had to make their living illegally in this way.

The Far East: A.D. 1601 to 1700

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Ming Dynasty to 1644, then Ch'ing [Manchu])

The Ming government reached its lowest point early in the century when the young, indecisive emperor, Hsi-Tsung, gave dictatorial power to Wei Chung-hsien, the most notorious palace eunuch of all Chinese history. He proceeded to brutally purge the government of all dissidents. In the first decades of the century the Jurchens, originally called Kin and now called "Manchus" gradually expanded into the modern provinces of Liaoning and Kirin and established a first capital at Mukden (subsequently Shenyang) from 1625 to 1644. The Manchus owed their nationhood to Nurhachi and his son Abahai, starting as petty tribal chieftains selling medicinal herbs to Chinese settlers in Manchuria. Abahai ended as the strong emperor at Mukden. (Ref. 1) From this base the Manchus subdued inner Mongolia in 1629 and made Korea a vassal state in 1637. At about the same time the Russian advance to the Pacific was stopped as these Manchurian people confronted them at the Amur River. The Manchus then headed south to China, where the population at 1600 was about 150 million or 2 1/2 times as great as it had been in 1368. Braudell (Ref. 2) points out that the early settlement and precipitous rise in population were-possible because of the small amount of meat eaten. When one adds up calories available for human consumption, agriculture on a given amount of land will always have the advantage over stock raising, feeding from 10 to 20 times as many people. "The choice between cereals and meat depends on the number of people."1 Early 17th century warfare reduced the total population drastically, however, as after 1627 there were waves of rebellions following crop failures in the northwest. Disastrous droughts and plagues of locusts were among the natural disasters occurring and paralleling those in the France of Louis XIII.

The basic crop of China, of course, was rice, but occasionally a peasant could get in a wheat crop between his 2 yearly harvests of rice. The Chinese made a sort of heavy dough from the wheat, not knowing how to knead it and so it helped very little in their meager dietary supply. (Ref. 4) On the other hand, China had plenty of highly skilled artisans. The cotton works of Songjiang, south of Shanghai, employed 200,000 workers, not including tailoring and dressmaking, by the end of the century. Su-chi had between 3,000 and 4,000 silk-looms. (Ref. 5) Still by 1636 almost all of central, northern and northwestern China was in rebellion. In that same year 3 Portuguese cannon, hauled upon the Great Wall, put the Manchurian army to flight and gained another decade of life for the Ming Dynasty. Rebel leader Li Tzu-ch'eng from Honan and adjacent areas, took Peking in 1644 in spite of its wide, guarded walls. The last Ming emperor then committed suicide. We should note in passing that Peking participates in the cruel Siberian cold for 6 months of the year and thousands of Mandarins clothed themselves in expensive sable and had boots, saddles, chairs and tents made with those same skins. (Ref. 6)

Li, as the conqueror of Peking, never got to form a dynasty because of the almost immediate invasion of the Manchus, who came down from Liao-tung with the aid of some Chinese defectors. (Ref. 7) Driven south, the remnants of the Ming eventually occupied Taiwan (never previously under Chinese control) in 1662, wresting it from the Dutch and they remained there until 1683. These new Formosans, led particularly by Cheong Ch'eng-kung2, pirated the mainland coast to such a degree that the Manchu regime made the populations within 10 miles of the coast move inland, to escape the raids. (Ref. 8) Some Ming also lived in Guilin (not far from Canton) and Jesuits, who accompanied the court, converted most of the remaining royal household to Christianity. Even the governor and commanding general of the Ming forces became Christians, chiefly through the efforts of the Italian Jesuit Rica, the German von Bell and the Belgian F. Verbiest. (Ref. 9, 10) Mings, forming the "Rebellion of the Three Feudatories", dominated almost all of south China for about 8 years, finally being suppressed by Chinese generals serving the Manchu Dynasty. (Ref. 11)

The Mongolians and Manchurians of the eastern steppe apparently learned to protect themselves against plague and it was this that allowed their populations and vigor to be augmented to the point that the Manchu could conquer China. (Ref. 13) Some might argue that their habit of eating meat in large slices (as the Mongols before them) might also have contributed. In China proper meat was rare (and thus their proteins deficient?). At any rate, the Manchus set up their own Ch'ing Dynasty which was to rule China until the 20th century. It was these foreign rulers who obliged the native Chinese to wear the Manchu pigtails as a mark of submission. The large robe, of former times, was also altered, but this did not amount to much and otherwise there was basically very little change. (Ref. 14) The invaders forbade intermarriage with the natives, but soon these conquerors, too, became "Chinese". The second ruler of the dynasty, K'ang-hsi, gave China the most prosperous, peaceful and enlightened reign in the nation's history. His realm, which included Mongolia, Manchuria, Korea, Indo-China, Annam, Tibet and Turkestan was the largest, richest and most populous empire of its time. His rule was more wise and just that that of his contemporaries, Aurangzeb and Louis XIV. All the emperors of the Ch'ing Dynasty lived in magnificent style. When Father Verbiest traveled with the emperor in Manchuria in 1682, the retinue was accompanied by 100,000 horses and in a hunt, 1,000 stags and 60 tigers were killed in 1 day. The Manchus were tough and smart. In 1689 when a final treaty was signed with the Russians at Nerchinsk, officially giving the Amur River basin back to China, the city was surrounded by a large fleet of heavily armed junks and 17,000 Manchu soldiers. (Ref. 15)

By the end of the century the population had again risen and stood at about 130 million. (Ref. 16) The Chinese did not give a monetary value to gold and would exchange it for silver at exceptionally low rates. Some historians believe that from 1/3 to 1/2 the silver mined in America between 1527 and 1821 found its way to China. Braudel (Ref. 17) states that in 1695 a traveler reported profits of 300% were made taking Chinese mercury to New Spain.

JAPAN

We have noted that as the last century closed the Japanese hero of the bloody Korean-Japanese conflict, Hideyoshi, died during the peace negotiation. As this 17th century began, Tokugawa leyasu, of royal blood, fought his rival generals and became the new shogun and brought order out of chaos by establishing a new currency, a money rather than a rice economy, a police network of the unemployed samurai and ruled as tyrant, while still giving young Emperor Go-Yozei some of the taxes. At the emperor's request Tokugawa issued an edict ordering the deportation of foreign priests, the demolition of churches and the renunciation of faith by Christians "who seek to change the government and obtain possession of the land". Still, in the first decade of the century Japan was a profitable rendezvous f or Portuguese traders. Every year the Macao carrack brought about 200 merchants to Nagasaki, where they would stay for 7 or 8 months, spending money freely. (Ref. 18) When Tokugawa sought to evacuate the Portuguese and Spanish friars, he was influenced by Will Adams, an English pilot of a Dutch ship, whom the shogun had kept as a prisoner but finally had him build 2 European ships. For this Adams was made a samurai and given an estate. Although against Portuguese and Spanish aggression, Tokugawa was not against all Christians and did not want to stop profitable trade with Protestants from Holland and England. But after his death in 16163, Catholic Christians were further persecuted and between 1620 and 1635 some 6,000 were crucified, some of them upside down like St. Peter. By that time 1 out of every 50 Japanese had been converted to Christianity and there were some Christian clan lords with armed infantry. The Emperor G-Mizu-no-o felt that his shogun was not doing his job of expelling those Christians, so he abdicated in 1629, putting a 7 year old girl on the throne, the first empress since 769. That was a sign to all that the Tokugawas were infringing on the imperial power and were fit to manage no one but little girls. Soon the shogun went to Kyoto to parley, with a great show of pomp and power, taking 307,000 retainers. After the meeting the shogun clamped down on all foreigners and closed the country except for a small Dutch trading post on a tiny island in Nagasaki harbor. Every time a Dutch or Chinese vessel did arrive there "on permission" a kind of fair was held and in the exchange Japan could export its silver and copper. Thus Japan still had some impact on world economy. It was the merchants of Osaka who were in charge of the internal trade. Japan would not be open again for 211 years. (Ref. 19, 20)

In 1657 fire destroyed most of Edo and killed more than 100,000 Japanese. (Ref. 22) The shoguns of the late part of the century were on the whole only mediocre. The so-called Genroku Age of letters and art developed between 1688 and 1703. During this time of isolation from the rest of the world, Japan kept her population stable by various devices, chiefly infanticide. Although rice had been grown some since the 1st century of the Christian Era, it was only in this century that it began to play a large part in the Japanese diet. Yedo (also Edo and later to become Tokyo) began to be the largest city, with over 500,000 citizens plus an enormous garrison of soldiers, with their families. The old capital of Kyoto sunk to second place. Merchant dynasties became established and some such as the Mitsui family have survived until today. They were sake manufacturers in 1620 and became the financial agent of both the shogun and of the imperial household in 1690. (Ref. 23, 24)

KOREA

Following the great war with Japan, in which the Koreans defeated the invading Japanese by cutting their supply lines at sea, Injo was put on the throne by the so-called "southern faction" of Confucianists. In 1637, however, the Manchus overran Korea and within 10 years it was simply a vassal state of the Manchu Ch'ing Dynasty and, isolated from the non-Chinese world, became known as "The Hermit Kingdom". The court and the people remained loyal to the Ming and in the last quarter of the century the western faction of Confucianists returned to power, under Sukchong.

SOUTHEAST ASIA

Under the Ming Dynasty of China there was a kind of colonial capitalism among the emigrant Chinese to the East Indies. This has persisted to the present day, with Chinese merchants and bankers among the most prominent of the entire Southeast Asia region. (Ref. 25)

MAINLAND SOUTHEAST ASIA

After 1644 much of Indo-China and all of Annam became part of the Manchu Chinese Empire. Towns in Vietnam were little populated on ordinary days as the people were in the fields, but twice a month great markets were held. At Hanoi (then Ke-Cho) the merchants were grouped on different streets according to their specialties. In effect it was a fair or market rather than a town. (Ref. 26) In 1659 Vietnamese armies penetrated Cambodian territory and in 1697 LanXang split into three rival states and wrangled among themselves for 2 centuries, while f ighting off outside invaders at the same time. Burma had broken up into a number of small states at the beginning of the century. Japanese, Portuguese and Eng1ish traders were all active in Siam, along with the ever present Dutch. The European powers also traded in Burma and Malaysia early in the century. When the Dutch attempted to monopolize Siam's foreign trade, King Narai (1661-88) and his Greek adviser, Constant Phaulkon, invoked French aid and the resulting French garrisons at Bangkok and Mergui led both to a change of dynasty at Ayurthaya and complete expulsion of the French, with heavy losses. (Ref. 27, 28)

After the Dutch seized Amaboyna and established themselves at Batavia, the English withdrew from Malaysia, as the Dutch had also captured Malacca from the Portuguese. The latter had introduced pineapples, papaya and sweet potatoes to southeast Asia from America. With Chinese-influenced Vietnam as an exception, houses in southeast Asia were built on piles and made of wood and bamboo, with wood and mud lattices. (Ref. 29, 30)

INDONESIA AND ADJACENT ISLANDS

In the course of this century the Dutch East India Company, by both force and diplomacy, got control of the sources of almost all the valuable spices coming from this part of the world and thus established a virtual monopoly on their shipment to Europe.

Besides their headquarters at Batavia and Malacca, they had a large establishment at Goa to service the Indies' activities. (Ref. 31) Sumatrans, as other far easterners, were basically grain eaters. Only a great lord might have chicken and they could not understand the Westerners love of cattle and poultry. Spanish galleons linked America with Manila, where Chinese junks hurried to trade. Mexican silver in the amount of about a million pesos a year thus went to the Orient. (Ref. 32) Timor, out at the eastern end of the lower island chain, was held by the Dutch East India Company because of its sandalwood, which could be used as an exchange currency in China. (Ref. 33)

1 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

2 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

3 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

4 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

5 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

6 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

7 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

8 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

9 [69] GARRETT, W.E., "China's Beauty Spot", National Geographic 156: 536, Oct. 1979.

10.HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

11 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

12 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

13 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

14 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

15 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

16 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

17 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

18 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

19 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

20 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

21 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

22 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

23 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

24 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

25 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

26 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

27 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

28 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

29 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

30 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

31 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

32 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

33 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

1.  Quotation from page 104, Braudel (Ref. 3) But also see next page re: protein deficiencies

2.  The Europeans called him "Kalinga". (Ref. 12)

3.  Tokugawa's heirs ran the administration of Japan for the hidden emperors for the next 252 years. (Ref. 21)

The Far East: A.D. 1701 to 1800

THE FAR EAST

CHINA AND MANCHURIA

The K' and Hsi reign of Sheng Tsu of the Ch'ing or Manchu Dynasty continued until 1722 as a period of great cultural achievement. Then there was a short reign of Shih Tsung in the Yung Cheng period, which included inconclusive wars against Mongols and western tribesmen. Finally in 1736 Kao Tsung became the Ch'ien Lung Emperor to reign for almost the rest of the century. He was an able and learned man, but he kept the western world away from China by repulsing English attempts at increasing international trade. (Ref. 1) Imperial domination of that type had controlled the economy and general course of industry for many generations and the end result of- that could be seen by 1736 when the once busy blast furnaces, coke ovens and steel plants were abandoned entirely. These basic industries, which later led to the Industrial Revolution in Europe, came to a dead end in China as a direct result of the absence of a free market economy. Officials habitually distrusted successful entrepreneurs and a going enterprise was either taken over as a state monopoly or was subjected to such taxes and artificially imposed prices that continued successful operation was impossible. One exception to this situation appears in the Co-Hong, a group of merchants authorized by the Peking government in 1726 to set up in competition with the Europeans, particularly the Indies Company. Lasting until 1771, the Co-Hong was the source of some huge Chinese fortunes. (Ref. 2)

Jesuit missionaries had been active in China for a long period and in order to get better rapport with the people, they had compromised with some Chinese customs and belief s. This upset the pope and he banned the Jesuit activity in China and eventually disbanded the whole order. But the pope's action infuriated the Chinese emperor and he promptly banned all missionary activities, although Priests were allowed to stay in Peking as astronomers, calendar makers and engineers. Increasing isolation behind monastic walls caused Chinese Buddhism to fade gradually in importance and Confucianism dominated. European intellectuals marveled at a great, prosperous and powerful country without benefit of clergy or hereditary aristocracy. This was one of China's great ages, with striking growth of agriculture, trade and population as well as massive scholarly and artistic efforts. Blue and white porcelain with transparent enamels went to every European city. In 1793 Kin-te-chin had 3,000 furnaces for baking porcelain. Su-Ch'u had between 3,000 and 4,000 silk-looms. It is hard to believe in the light of these accomplishments that both soap and underwear were still unknown in China. Horses were rare and Chinese were still using wooden saddles and ropes instead of reins. Furthermore, much of their equipment was primitive. Although there were textile looms in the towns, the countryside weavers used elementary horizontal looms of a type still used today by certain nomads in North Africa. Was this lack of good mechanization because labor was so plentiful and cheap? (Ref. 3, 4, 5)

The population increased from 130,000,000 to 150,000,000 in A.D. 1700 to 313,000,000 by 1794. (Ref. 6) Maize joined the traditional northern crops of millet and sorghum and allowed the restoration of a demographic balance between northern and southern China. As in western Europe, Chinese merchants now had their shops in one place, their houses in another. (Ref. 7) Merchant and artisan guilds greatly expanded in number and function, with security funds, insurance plans and entertainment programs. Dictionaries and encyclopedias were published. The Ch'ien-lung Emperor was probably the most capable ruler of his time, but his reign was blemished by two things: (1) a literary inquisition in the 1770s to suppress what he thought to be subversive ideas and (2) in his older age he became the dupe of a clever guardsman named Ho-shen, who introduced extensive bribery and corruption in the administration. (Ref. 8)

As East-West contacts became less and less, soon all foreign commerce had to come through the port of Canton (or at Kyakhta for the Russians). The extensive exports of tea, silk and porcelain were under government license at those ports, with silver the standard medium of exchange until very late in the century when foreign powers began to bring in opium instead of silver. By the end of the century everyone in China smoked tobacco, even children. (Ref. 9)

Chinese armies roamed westward over Central Asia and by the Treaty of Kiakhta in 1727 Russia was forced to acknowledge Chinese jurisdiction over that region, the last strongholds of nomadic power. In the meantime, however, the huge Kamchatka Peninsula to the north had been taken by Russia along with the Kurile Islands. (Ref. 10) Old tribal rebellion problems also gave intermittent difficulties throughout the century. There were a number of such uprisings in Yunnan (1726-29), of the Miao of Kweichow (1795-97), of the Yao in Kwangsi in 1790 and of the Chinese Muslims of Kansu in 1781-84 and the most serious of all - the great Chin-ch'uan tribal rebellions of western Szechwan, which simmered from 1746 through 1776. Taiwan had an uprising in 1787, but it was not a major threat to the Ch'ing Dynasty. At the end of the century, however, as indicated above, the government was declining with corruption in the administration and demoralization in the army. (Ref. 11) The tremendous population increase and the limited amount of land for increasing agricultural production combined to produce some serious hardships and impoverishment of the people. This was in part the reason for the White Lotus rebellion in Szechwan, Shensi and Hupeh in 1795, which continued into the next century. (Ref. 12)

One must not overlook the extensive, internal water traffic that was and is so essential for the Chinese life. A witness in 1733 described a perpetual movement of boats, barks and rafts (some 3 miles long) containing permanent homes with wives and children aboard. One could almost believe there were as many people living on water as in the towns and of the world's greatest maritime trades, linking up the small-craft from the interior with the Chinese junks and European three-masters. The ordinary rate of interest between merchants of Canton at the end of this century was 18 to 20%. (Ref. 13)

It was not until this century, long after Vesalius had done human body dissection in Europe, that direct anatomical studies were done in China, since Confucius' doctrines had forbidden violation of the body. (Ref. 14) Because of government pressure, by 1800 maize and sweet potatoes, transplanted from America, made up a substantial part of China's total food and were staples of the poor. (Ref. 15)

JAPAN

The feudal age of the Shogunates continued throughout this era and we pause here to briefly outline more of the nature of this political organization. Theoretically at the head of the nation was the divine emperor, and the apparent ruling house, the hereditary Shogunate, allowed the emperor and his court a certain monetary allowance each year, while the Shogun himself luxuriated in the growing wealth of Japan. The Shogun had a large personal retinue and was advised by a cabinet of 12 members. A Board of Censors supervised all administrative offices and kept watch on the feudal lords (Daimye). The latter formally acknowledged allegiance only to the emperor and some of them successfully limited the Shogun's powers. Below the lords were the baronets and then the squires. Serving the lords were a million or more samurai, sword-bearing guardsmen. Every soldier was a gentleman and every gentleman a soldier and they scorned mere learning. They were exempt from taxation, received pay from the baron they served and performed no labor except occasionally to die in battle. The samurai could keep his sword sharp by splitting a peasant here and there at will. With them the practice of Hari-Kari developed, as the code of the samurai demanded great courage, asceticism and self-control. With decrease of warfare, however, the purely military character of the caste changed and while the samurai remained a pensioned and privileged aristocracy, they then began to perform administrative and judicial functions. Eventually powerful economic political and intellectual forces began to undermine the delicately poised political system of the Shoguns. The dominant samurai class became economically dependent upon the despised merchants and moneylenders. Some samurai manned the learned professions of medicine, teaching and scholarship. But both lords and peasants suffered from the radical fluctuation in agricultural prices entailed by the penetration of a money economy into the countryside. The samurai with the government tried debasement of the currency, price controls, moral exhortations and outright confiscation of merchant fortunes, all of no permanent help. Some lords had to promote new agriculture and mines and industrial enterprises, including a boost in silk output, while others adopted sons of merchants, thus improving the family finances and securing for the merchants the prestige of samurai rank. Through this, class distinctions began to lose part of their sharpness. Osaka, with 500,000 people by 1783, was the meeting place of Japanese merchants and the capital Yedo (Tokyo) was already twice as large as Paris. (Ref. 16) Powerful craft guilds, officially recognized as early as 1721, extended their networks and monopolies and in some instances began to resemble western, privileged trading companies. (Ref. 17)

During this relatively peaceful century Japan's population remained stable at about 30,000,000, kept down by widespread infanticide and occasional famine. An excess of rain and grasshoppers in 1732 reduced 2,600,000 people to near starvation while 12,400 people and still more horses and cattle died. (Ref. 18) But rice production increased as a result of improvement in seeds, irrigation and drainage systems, tools and commercialization of fertilizers made from sardines, colza, soya or cotton cake. In contrast to Europe, changes of fashion in dress did not occur in Japan and it is said that the nation had not changed its costume for over a thousand years. (Ref. 19)

In the intellectual and philosophical realms, it should be mentioned that Japanese scholars completed some 58 years of work in 1715 in the 26 volumes called Dai Nihonshi (The Great History of Japan), but it was in manuscript form and kept out of print, so that only the aristocratic few had access to it. The Buddhist monks became quite degenerate and their religion lost its hold upon the nation, as the Shoguns went over to Confucianism . The civilization of the old Japan, like so many others, had begun with religion and was ending with philosophy. The retreat of Buddhism behind monastic walls was a defensive reaction to foreign cultural and political pressures. The Neo-Confucians sought to inculcate loyalty and obedience in all ranks, but some rejected this Sinification and sought new solutions. In 1779 the main line of the imperial family ended without male issue and a collateral house, the Kanins, took over and they were the one chiefly responsible for the revival of Shinto. The remodeled Shinto seems to have ideas borrowed from ecclesiastical and other notions of Christianity. It attempted to draw men's minds away from the Shogun and back to the emperor. In another direction, a handful of men began to penetrate the secrets of western civilization - chiefly through the Dutch language and books, with then some Japanese publications appearing on medicine, anatomy, astronomy and geography. (Ref. 20, 21)

KOREA

Korea was a vassal of the Manchu Dynasty of China and political activity was at low ebb, while intellectual activity was intensive. For the most part, however, this activity was limited to considerations of moral philosophy and to genealogical research. In 1706 the Hyeonchungsa Shrine was erected near Asan in memory of the famous Admiral Yi on whom the government had already bestowed the title "Chungmu-Kong", meaning "Loyalty-Chivalry Lord". (Ref. 22)

SOUTHEAST ASIA

MAINLAND SOUTHEAST ASIA

Buddhism had become the palladium of both Burmese and Siamese ethnic identities, so that the fate of the religion was intertwined with the fate of those two nations. In Burma the Mons rebelled in 1740, setting up their own kingdom at Pegu and then returning to capture the Burmese capital, Ava, in 1752. But a new Burmese leader, Alaungpaya, continued the fight and finally defeated the Mons with their French allies, founding Rangoon in 1755 and re-uniting Burma. In 1759 the same king defeated the British East India Company on the island of Negrais and the British left Burma. But the nation's problems were not over. Between 1760 and 1769 the Chinese made four abortive invasion attempts and finally succeeded in making Burma a vassal state in 1771. The Burmese also warred some in late century with Siam, in an attempt to expand their territory. (Ref. 23) Siam continued to be a large country and extended down the Malay peninsula almost to Penang.

It was in 1767 that the Siamese capital at Ayudhya was ransacked by the Burmese, with buildings and art work destroyed and the royal family members killed or taken captive. When the Burmese were driven out in 1782 a new dynasty, the Chakkri (or Chakri), was established and it has continued in power to this day. (Ref. 24) The first of that dynasty, King Rama I, built Wat Phra Keo, a fantastic Theravada Buddhist temple in 1785. (Ref. 25, 26)

The area now known as Laos was comprised chiefly in the 18th century by the Kingdom of Lung Prabang, although as early as 1707 the southern part broke away to be part of Vientiene. Annam (Vietnam) got further territory, including the area of Saigon, from Cam bodia, but after 1775 the Vietnamese suffered internal problems, allowing the Thais (Siamese) to also invade Cambodia. (Ref. 27, 28) Annam became a vassal state to China in 1788. On the Malay Peninsula, the British East India Company acquired Penang from the Sultan of Kedah for a naval station in 1786 and at the end of the century the British were beginning to move against the Dutch in the entire area. (Ref. 29)

INDONESIA AND ADJACENT ISLANDS

Malaria arrived late in Indonesia, but practically destroyed Batavia (now Djarkarta) in 1732. (Ref. 30) The Dutch introduced coffee cultivation all along the north coast and the east end of Java, as well as in the Medura Islands, as they extended their political control. Indonesians were required to work in spice groves by local princelings who, in turn, were commanded by Dutch overseers. (Ref. 31) Later the English took Sumatra to hold for the Dutch and by the Treaty of Paris of 1783; they returned all colonies to the latter. But the aggressive English again conquered Sumatra in 1795 and by 1798 the Dutch East India Company was out of business. The British also temporarily occupied Manila in the Philippines between 1762 and 1764 and during that time opened that city to world commerce. When the Spanish regained control, however, they again closed the islands to international trade, although they exchanged American silver for Chinese silk there. (Ref. 32, 33)

1 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES o., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

2 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

3 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

4 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

5 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

6 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

7 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

8 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES o., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

9 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

10 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

11 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

12 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

13 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

14 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

15 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES o., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

16 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

17 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

18 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

19 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

20 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

21 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

22 [11] BELL, i. WILEY, "Admiral Yi and the Turtle Boats", American History Illustrated X11:44-48, June, 1977 .

23 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

24 [262] WARNER, ROBERT, "Thailand hosts a birthday party", Smithsonian, Vol. 13, No. 3: 34-45, June, 1982.

25 [113] Kim, h. EDWARDS, "Seoul: Korean Showcase", National Geographic 156: 770, Dec. 1979.

26 [276] EVERINGHAM, JOHN, "Thailand's Working Royalty", National Geographic 162:468-498, Oct. 1892.

27 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

28 [9] BARTHEL, THOMAS S., "The Talking Boards of Easter Island", Scientific American, 236:116-133, March, 1977.

29 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

30 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

31 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

32 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

33 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

The Far East: A.D. 1801 to 1900

THE FAR EAST

Asians decided that polished white rice (like the white flour in the west) was ideal food, but polishing rice removed the drab-colored, outer sheath, which contains the nutritious germ carrying important foodstuffs. Some people were developing the deficiency diseases such as Beri-beri, which affects nerves, heart and digestive systems. (See also Southeast Asia.)

CHINA AND MANCHURIA (Continued Manchu Dynasty)

The Manchu rulers clung tenaciously to their 2,000 year old institutions but 2 types of pressures hastened the collapse of imperial China. The first was the increasing power and ambitions of the West. English, Dutch, Spanish, French and Portuguese all had colonial empires in Asia as well as America and were calling for free-trade. By 1800 and after, westerners found they could sell the Chinese abundant quantities of opium, even if illegally and get tea, silk, porcelains and silver back. By 1839 this had provoked war with England - the Opium War of 1839-42 - chiefly coastal skirmishes, which went badly for China, nevertheless. Five ports from Canton to Shanghai were opened to foreign residence and trade and foreign influence began to be felt. China's fate in the 19th century echoed that of India in the 18th in regard to creeping western invasion. (Ref. 1)

The second factor leading to the collapse of imperial China was the growing domestic discontent. For 2,000 years China had sustained a highly advanced culture, although static. Regardless of various foreign invader-rulers, the huge majority of its people lived on the land in self sufficient and contained villages, living by ancestral precept. Although at the mercy of nature, in some ways their technology was well advanced with city walls, efficient irrigation systems and grand palaces and they lived-with dignity, rich and poor. (Ref. 2) In the first part of this l9th century travelers reported that the Chinese "have tranquility without happiness, industry without improvement, stability without strength and public order without public morality"1. This was soon to change again. Anti-Manchu secret societies became more active, with the White Lotus Society rebellion, which had actually started in 1793, now really disrupting north China by 1804. More and more uprisings continued until 1850, when the great Taiping Rebellion raged for 15 years, with hundreds of towns damaged or destroyed and some 30,000,000 lives lost. This Taiping (also T'ai-p-ing) started in Chin-t'ien in the far south of China in Kwangsi, with a minority group of half-Christianized peasants under a self-styled Chinese Messiah, Hung Hsiu-ch'uan, who set out to create an utopia of pastoral, puritanical communism in central China. They moved to Nanking and soon had a large area from that city south, including most of Hepeh, Chekiang, Kiangse and part of Fukien under control. In spite of their original ideal they were soon just killing people and before it was suppressed in 1864 it had cost 5 to 10 million lives, statistically the greatest war until World War 1. Their advances included one almost to Peking in 1853-54 and on into Szechwan in 1856-63.

The population of China by 1850 was over 400,000,0002and was beginning again to surpass food production. Corruption and indolence in government made things worse and unemployment increased. In addition there were Muslim uprisings which depopulated large areas in Yunnan between 1855 and 1873 and an area just south of the Great Wall in 1863 to 1873, Miao tribal uprisings in Kweichow between 1854 and 1873 and Nien rebels, who invaded Chihli in 1868 and the Hakka-Cantonese War in Kwantung between 1855 and 1857. (Ref. 4, 5, 6)

Thus began China's modern history. In the last half of the century Manchu and true Chinese leaders tried to respond to economic and military incursions of the West with the so-called self strengthening movement, to adapt western technology without disturbing traditional political and social orders. From 1870 to near the end of the century it seemed to be working fairly well, but this was misleading and the imperial order completely fell a few years later. (Ref. 7)

To leave the political scene for a bit, we should reiterate that by the 1820s Manchu China was the world's largest and most populous empire, directly controlling vast territories in inner Asia and drawing tribute f rom still larger areas including Korea, Indo-China, Siam, Burma and Nepal. A postal service with 2,000 express stations, over 30,000 horses and almost 50,000 foot messengers and 70,000 service people was used basically as a means of control by the imperial government. In 1855 troops were sent across the Salween River into Yunnan province to suppress some rebels in an area where bubonic plague was endemic. The troops not only contracted the disease but brought it back into the remainder of China and by 1894 it had reached Canton and Hong Kong. It was then that teams of scientists were sent in and the bacillus Pasteurella pestis identified and the mode of transmission, by fleas from rodents to men, was established. In the meantime steamships were carrying the disease f rom China around the world. Chinese medicine continued to fascinate the West. The Pharmacopoeia, called Pen Ts'ao, listed many wines. Tortoise wine was good for bronchitis; snake wine was curative of palsy; dog wine helped lassitude and mutton wine was good for the testicles. (Ref. 8, 9, 10, 11)

We must include a few words about Chinese paintings. Japanese collectors have given the impression that Sung paintings are great, Yuan occasionally good, and Ming and Ch'ing increasingly imitative and sterile. This not what the Chinese themselves think, but their traditions are not those of the West. Their paintings of ten have no background at all and they feel no compulsion to fill up the canvas with details. Similarly they do not handicap themselves with convention about perspective. In landscapes particularly, the viewer might consider himself as if suspended in air, shif ting about to view different parts of the scene. (Ref. 12)

In 1894 Japan defeated China in a year of war and incidentally then took control of Formosa, along with a cash indemnity. After that defeat a generation of revolutionary Chinese leaders, of whom Sun-Yat-Sen (d. 1925) was the most imminent, undertook an almost panic search for new talismans of power and national salvation. The obvious models were the great western powers, so in 1898 the young Emperor Huang Hsu issued a series of astonishing decrees which, if they could have been accepted and enforced, would have advanced China vigorously and yet peaceably on the road to westernization. But the Dowager Empress, shocked by what seemed to her the radicalism of those edicts, imprisoned Huang Hsu, annulled his decrees and made herself the government of China, with a reaction against all western ideas. She deftly turned an organization known - historically as the "Boxers", originally formed by rebels against her own dynasty, into a furious movement against foreign invaders. This resulted in a killing of Christians, which in turn caused retaliation by armies of the west, including some from the United States. Those armies moved in on Peking and slaughtered the inhabitants in 1900. As in India, it is little wonder that Christianity has had very little success in China. At the beginning of the l9th century a real Protestant missionary effort had been made by English and American churches, but it has been estimated that there were never more than 1,000,000 converts and few of those were 100% converted. In this l9th century perhaps 12,000,000 Chinese migrated into Southeast Asia and along the Indian coast. (Ref. 13, 14, 15)

Manchuria remained somewhat isolated, kept as the special preserve of the Manchu emperors. It had great agricultural potential but was closed to immigrants. In 1858 and 1860 Russia took back 380,000 square miles of Manchuria from a rather helpless China, claiming that the original Treaty of Nerchinsk (see page 906) had been signed under duress. That area, as well as Korea, then remained under Russian influence until after the war with Japan was concluded early in the next century. (Ref. 16, 17, 18)

JAPAN

Japan exhibited a marked duality under the Tokugawa Shoguns, a separation between political and economic power; moral ideal of Spartan warriors versus sensuous indulgences of the "Floating World". Then in 1850 there was conflict among rival cliques over the succession to a childless ruler and that set the stage so that the rather modest emergency of Perry's "black ships" triggered far-ranging, deep-going transformations of Japanese society. The Age of Military Feudalism of Japan may be said to have terminated at that time when Commodore Matthew Perry arrived in Uraga Bay in 1853 with 2 warships and 2 side-wheelers. The American got nowhere with negotiations at that time, but he returned 8 months later in 1854 with 9 ships, 3 under steam, along with a miniature steam train, which he set up on shore for demonstration. The subsequent dedication of the Japanese to trains may have started with that. Treaties allowing western access to 2 ports, with resident western consular officials followed. But this was still not the end of turmoil in Japan regarding East-West intercourse. The emperor ref used to sign the treaties and political war against the Tokugawas was instituted and Lemochi became shogun. In 1862, at Emperor Komei's order, Lord Shimazu of Satsuma went to - Kyoto, killed a few enemies and, with Prince Ashiko, temporarily got rid of the emperor's chief advisor, Iwakura of the clan of Choshu.

The aims of modern Japan were set at that time. Although the imperial family had always had a goal of expansion to eventually conquer the world, the group who wanted to first start north against Russia were represented by Iwakura and his clan and they were now out of favor. The apostles of the strike south concept, moving against the West through Singapore and Manila, were in the ascendancy and along with that the policy of exclusion of foreigners from the sacred soil was continued. In 1865, as Japan was preparing for civil war between the Shogun Tukugawa and the Lord of Choshu, the Perry treaty remained unfulfilled and the nation came to a standstill. It was not until the old emperor was assassinated in 1868 and the new Emperor Meiji took over that the troops of the Tokugawa Shogun were defeated and a new era of reform, including some breakdown of class distinction, transfer of the capital to Edo (now Tokyo) and the restrictions against westerners were temporarily lifted. The theory was that Japan must grow strong, expand overseas to establish a defense perimeter outside the sacred soil and only then expel the barbarians. Iwakura, back in power as an adviser, went overseas for 2 years to see what Japan had to contend with in the rest of the world, while the homeland began to industrialize. An anachronism is that even in this l9th century sugar cane was still milled by manpower, in Japan. (Ref. 19) Returning from abroad, Iwakura gradually forced Korea to open her ports to Japanese commerce by gun-boat diplomacy and at the same time, by getting hoarded gold from wealthy merchants, he stabilized Japan's economy and established public confidence in his currency and bonds. In a sense Japan became westernized by fiat. Militarism was reinforced, conscription was adopted late in the 1870s after a brief but brutal civil war and the army was organized on the Prussian model. (Ref. 20) Japanese merchants became the shipping magnates, the money lenders the financiers and the cities of Tokyo, Osaka, Hiroshima, Nagasaki and Kokura became great industrial centers. When the strong man Iwakura Tomoni died, Emperor Meiji himself, although remaining in the background, carefully continued the industrialization. His sons were educated in Europe at Sandhurst and St. Cyrl, the Polytechnique,- etc. learning the military physics and western arts of war. Saion ji Kinmochi, a prince of the Fujiwara family had gone abroad to study also in 1871 and remained in Paris 9 years. On his return home, he helped draft a constitution based primarily on Bismarck's for Germany, although he retained all-encompassing power for the emperor. It was presented to the people in 1889; (Ref. 21, 22, 23, 24)

The population of Japan in 1888 was 39,500,000 and the proportion living in cities of over 100,000 was small. This population was to double in the next 30 years, even though the Japanese islands are smaller than California, with only about 1/6 of the land arable. The Sino-Japanese War, beginning in 1894, had developed over the control of Korea and Taiwan and was simply a part of the long range plan of conquering both China and Russia. It started Japan on its course as a great power. Using their adequate coal deposits and their long standing copper industry, Japan launched heavy industry on a large scale after 1895. The ultimate result of all these political and commercial changes was a decline of the shoguns and a regaining of supreme powers by the emperors in a more overt manner. The Shinto religion was revised, the emperor was considered divine by lineage and wisdom and the country underwent an amazingly rapid transformation into a modern nation. There was improved agriculture as well industrialization and an improved silk worm culture allowed independence from the Chinese silk producers. Japanese settlers migrated throughout their empire, including the newly won Taiwan, obtained in the Treaty of Shimonoseki (1895). Universal military service had been introduced in 1872 and the Gregorian calendar had been adopted in 1873. (Ref. 25, 26, 27, 28)

KOREA

Throughout most of the century Korea remained under suzerainty of the Chinese Manchus, although with their own kings. After systemic persecution of Christians under the regent Tai Wen Kun, there were several western expeditions attacking Korea, including a French force and an American naval force under Captain Shufeldt. Three ports were opened to Japanese trade in 1876 and in 1882 a treaty with the United States, negotiated by Shufeldt, allowed certain extra-territorial rights and permission to trade. China and Japan then began to dispute rights of control over the peninsula. In 1894, led by a Japanese underworld strongman sent specifically for the purpose, a group of Koreans, the Tonghaks, known to favor closing the country to Japanese trade, started a revolution. When Chinese troops were being mobilized at the call of the Korean government and Czar Nicholas had massed troops on the northern Korean border, Japanese troops suddenly arrived by sea and occupied Seoul and other Korean cities. The Chinese navy, attempting to prevent reinforcements of the invaders, was sunk by the Japanese navy. The non-entity, who was the emperor of Korea, ran to Russia. China sued for peace, giving Japan the right to "protect" Korea, an indemnity and the island of Taiwan. But Russian influence was still dominant and a Russian-Korean Bank was formed, while timber and mining concessions were given to Russia. On June 9, 1896 Japan and Russia established the Labanov-Yamagata Agreement under which the two countries cooperated in the reform of the army and finances of Korea, but Russian penetration continued, setting the stage for the Russian-Japanese War in the next century. (Ref. 29, 30, 31, 32)

SOUTHEAST ASIA

MAINLAND SOUTHEAST ASIA

BURMA

Burma, having failed to invade Siam in the last century, now turned its expansion policy toward the west, threatening Bengal, seizing Manipur and Assam in 1822. This soon brought King Bagyidaw up against the British East India Company and in the next 62 years there were three Burmese Wars with the British. The latter won the first war of 1824-26 and annexed Assam, Arakan and Tenasserim to British India. After the 2nd war in 1852 the British occupied the Irrawaddy delta region and stimulated great rice production there, as well as opening up the great teak forests. After the 3rd war in 1886 Upper Burma was added to the British domain, although guerrilla activity continued for years, with 32,000 British troops still involved between 1886 and 1891. The Shan states were not subdued until 1887 and the Chin Hills not until 1891. (Ref. 33, 34, 35)

THAILAND: SIAM AND CAMBODIA

After the long conflict with Burma had ended, Siam secured part of Cambodia through division of that state with Annam and finally, in 1844, the whole of Cambodia passed under the protection of Siam's King Mongkut. Rama IV (1851-1868), ruler and monk, philosopher and scientist, who taught himself English and Latin, made a study of western governments and began the work of modernizing Siam. After new treaties were drawn up with Great Britain in 1855, consuls were established and trade agreements initiated. In 1863 the French established a protectorate over Cambodia and Siam gave up its claims to that region. The real founder of modern Siam was Rama V, Chulalongkorn. Under him the old feudal system was abolished, slavery was reduced and there was administrative reform with new taxation and finance methods, better postal service, the telegraph (1883) and the first railway in 1893. But the French had long been trying to extend their dominions westward to the Mekong River and finally, after an acute Anglo-

French crisis and some gunboat activity and blockades, the Siamese yielded and abandoned all claim to territory east of the Mekong. In 1897 the King of Siam paid an extended visit to the European capitals. (Ref. 36, 37)

VIETNAM: FRENCH INDOCHINA

At the beginning of this l9th century most of present day North and South Vietnam and Laos, at one time all together called French IndoChina, was ruled by the Emperor of Annam and the region was predominantly Chinese in culture, with the empire acknowledging the suzerainty of the Chinese emperor. After a long period of dynastic struggles, the domain had been re-united by Gia Long (1802-1820) and he had been supported by the French missionary, Pigneau de Behaine. The French Catholics had freedom of action until after 1820 when a series of anti-Christian emperors came to power and they were then persecuted for 60 years. Because of that the French, with some Spanish, bombarded Tourane on the coast in 1858 and soon the French occupied Saigon in what was then called Cochin China. Subsequently the French explored both the Mekong and the Red rivers. About 1873 Francis Garnier, with a handful of men, attacked and took Hanoi and most of the Red River delta. In 1874, by a treaty signed at Saigon, the Annam emperor was forced to give a promise that his foreign policy would coincide with that of France and that he would recognize the French possession of Cochin China in exchange for the return of Hanoi. But the emperor appealed to China for aid and by 1885 France was at war with China. In the end France won control of all Annam and protective power over Cambodia and by 1893 had acquired a protectorate over Laos, which had long been in dispute between Siam and Annam. Paul Doumer, as governor-general over the vast French Indo-China, inaugurated far-reaching- reforms which modernized the region, but there was continued resistance to the westerners. The opposition in Annam was led by De Tham from after 1895 until well into the 20th century and there were revolts in Cambodia and Saigon in the 1885-1887 period. (Ref. 38, 39)

MALAYA

When Holland fell to French revolutionary troops in Europe, the British usurped Malacca and various southeastern Asian islands from the Dutch. Lt. Governor Sir Thomas Stamford Raffles founded Singapore in 1819 and it was soon to become a strategic and commercial center of the region. The Dutch, of course, were unhappy and all was not settled until the Anglo-Dutch Treaty of 1824, drawing a line through the straits of Malacca, with the English holding Singapore and Malacca, but giving up a west Sumatran settlement. There was a steady influx of Chinese laborers into the peninsula after 1850, with some working in the tin mines and some turning to piracy. The British abolished import duties on tin in 1853 and by 1900 Malaya furnished nearly 1/2 the world's supply. The rule of the British East India Company ended in 1867 and thereafter the Malayan Straits settlements had the status of a crown colony. Rubber was first grown there experimentally in 1894. (Ref. 40)

INDONESIA AND ADJACENT ISLANDS

The British took Java from the Dutch in 1811, although after the fall of Napoleon in 1815 they restored many of the Dutch possessions, as noted above, retaining chiefly Singapore. It was during the English occupation in 1814, however, that the governor of Java, Thomas Raffles, learned of the ruins of Borobudur (see pages 501-2,531 and 567) and he initiated some minor cleaning work that was carried on later on a small scale by the Dutch for the remainder of the century. The first real reconstruction work was not carried out until the 20th century. (Ref. 41) In 1825 the Javanese revolted against the Dutch under the native leader, Dipo Negora, and it took 5 years for the Dutch to quiet things down. They then extended their control into the interior, forcing a new culture system, which involved government contracts, crop control and fixed prices, all very lucrative to the westerners. Quinchona plantations were established in Java in 1854, giving Europeans the first reliable source of the right kind of bark to supply quinine to protect them in their world-wide expansion. In 1,886 the Dutch even sent medical teams to the Indonesian colonies to study Beri-beri and they discovered the essence of the vitamin requirements, although the details were not actually clarified until after the turn of the century.

In the 1840s Great Britain again entered this area with a charter for the North Borneo Company which was to have a protectorate over Sarawak, with James Brooke becoming the Rajah of Sarawak. This upset the Dutch, but eventually by a treaty in 1891 the two European countries defined their respective domains in Borneo, with the Dutch retaining the larger part. (Ref. 42, 43, 44)

The Philippines continued under Spanish control through most of the century, with the Spanish having great difficulty subjugating the war-like Moros. Although the growing of tobacco, sugar and hemp had been promoted, Manila was not officially opened to foreign traders until 1834. The Jesuit priests who had been expelled from the island in the last century now returned and gained much power and property. It was in opposition to that clergy that much sentiment arose for independence, with the rebels being led by Emilio Aguinaldo. When the Spanish-American war broke out, the Americans took Manila while Aguinaldo led a new insurrection. At the war's end, to the Philippine leader's great disappointment, the islands gained only American sovereignty, instead of Spanish. He then led still another revolution against the United States in 1899, but this quickly subsided to merely guerrilla warfare, although it cost 7,000 American casualties by the time of its termination in 1902. (Ref. 45)

1 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

2 [242] PEFFER, NATHANIAL, The Far East. (Univ. of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1958).

3 [242] PEFFER, NATHANIAL, The Far East. (Univ. of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1958).

4 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

5 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

6 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

7 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

8 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

9 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

10 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

11 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

12 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

13 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

14 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

15 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

16 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

17 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

18 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

19 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

20 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

21 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

22 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

23 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

24 [242] PEFFER, NATHANIAL, The Far East. (Univ. of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1958).

25 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

26 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

27 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

28 [242] PEFFER, NATHANIAL, The Far East. (Univ. of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1958).

29 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

30 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

31 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

32 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

33 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

34 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

35 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

36 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

37 [276] EVERINGHAM, John, "Thailand's Working Royalty", National Geographic 162:468-498, Oct. 1892.

38 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

39 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

40 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

41 [286] MORTON, w. BROWN, iii, "Indonesia Rescues Ancient Borobudur", National Geographic 163: 126-142, Jan. 1983.

42 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

43 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

44 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

45 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

1.  Quotation from de Tocqueville (Ref. 3), page 90

2.  Contrasting to 4,000,000 in the United States at 1800 and 30,000,000 in the whole of Russia

The Near East: Beginning to 8000 B.C.

THE NEAR EAST

It has been mentioned earlier in the chapter that before 13,000 B.C. the area now covered by the Mediterranean Sea was in part a land mass with only connected fresh water lakes, fed by the Nile and Adriatic rivers and drainage from the Black Sea area. As the glaciers continued to melt the Atlantic Ocean level rose and spilled over the Gibralter barrier into the Mediterranean basin. It is possible that a great accumulation of men of the dark-white Iberian race had occupied this lush basin and now had to spread north, south and east. In the Near East, as we know it today, there were people at 20,000 B.C. eating snails, river crabs, fresh water mussels, turtles and various nuts. Cooking by boiling could not be well developed before the use of pottery, as one must have fire proof containers for the water. Some other previous methods may have been used in localized areas and on a small scale, such as the use of a large mollusc or reptile shell, animal stomachs, etc.

The eastern Mediterranean shore has been warm and wet enough for human habitation for at least 20,000 years and remains of the classical Neanderthal man have been found there predating that period, particularly in Israel, Lebanon and Iraq, where typical Mousterian Culture tools have been found in both caves and open sites. At about 10,000 B.C. the Natufians (archaeologist term for a particular group studied in digs) were taking their first steps toward building permanent settlements, storing food and similar basic activities. This Mesolithic culture of about 10,000 to 8,500 B.C. was centered in Palestine, but extended north into Syria and Lebanon and west into Egypt and surrounding Africa. Querns for grinding and sickles were used and the people apparently hunted gazelles. Agricultural communities appeared where rainfall permitted.1

1 The now dry wadis must have gushed with water at that time, although they apparently dried up about 15,000 years ago. (Ref. 1)

Upper Paleolithic cultures flourished in caves in Anatolia from 13,000 B.C. onwards and there are cave sites at the southeast corner of the Caspian Sea from 10,500 B.C. on. Seasonal settlements with mudbrick cubicles and plastered floors in the central Zagros Mountains date to the 9th millennium B.C. Tannahill (Ref. 2) says that even back at 40,000 B.C. there was one person for every thirty-one square miles in Iran, and the bones found there are chiefly of wild goats and red deer, although those of hare, fox, leopard and wild cattle have also been found. As the Ice Age ended and the glaciers receded, the seas rose rapidly, particularly where there were wide continental shelves.

The flooding in the Persian Gulf area between seven and ten thousand years ago must have been spectacular, and before the Tigris and Euphrates rivers filled the valley with silt, the sea reached inland over hundreds of miles, undoubtedly giving rise to the flood stories so common in all heritages of the old civilizations of the Near East. Some feel that a sinking of the bed rock under the Mesopotamian plains may have outstripped the opposite effect of silting, and thus contributed to the flooding. (Ref. 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10)

At Eridu, south of Ur, the Iraq government has unearthed ruins of fourteen temples, one above the other, all belonging to the "first Al'Ubaid period", which was before a tremendous flooding of this entire valley occurred, filling the land between the Syrian desert plateau on the west and the Persian mountains on the east, representing some tremendous catastrophe of nature and remembered thereafter in the peoples' legends as "The Flood"- a recurring story throughout Mesopotamian and Near Eastern history. In the excavations of the strata below the flood silt there was pottery, evidence already of far flung trade, and at Ur, Woolly even found two beads made of amazonite, a stone of which the nearest known source is the Nighiri hills of central India' Whether the pre-flood people should properly be called Sumerians is disputed. The famous Sumerian King lists, found later on various tablets, show legendary kings before the flood and the length of each reign was described from 18,000 years back. Then, say the tablets, the flood came. The lists of kings after the flood again are all legendary down to "The First Dynasty of Ur" which we shall discuss later. The flood plain had eleven feet of silt which has been estimated to mean a flood not less than twenty-five feet deep over the flat, low-lying land of Mesopotamia. Ur, today, is 200 miles from the sea, but only fourteen feet above sea level. (Ref. 11)

Sheep were domesticated in northern Iraq about 9,000 B.C., certainly by 8,900 B.C., but it is possible that they were brought from the east around the Caspian Sea by nomads who had domesticated them even earlier.

1 [315] HAMBLIN, Dora Jane, "Treasures of the Sands", Smithsonian, Sept. 1983, pp. 43-53.

2 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

3 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

4 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

5 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

6 [158] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Early Civilizations in the Middle East. Map from Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., Sept. 1978.

7 [224] Van Andel, Tjeerd, Tales of an Old Ocean. (The Portable Stanford, Stanford Alumni Assoc., Stanford, Calif. 1977).

8 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

9 [130] MARSHACK, ALEXANDER, The Roots of Civilization. (McGraw-Hill Book Co., 1972).

10 [226] WAECHTER, JOHN, Prehistoric Man. (Octopus Books Limited, London and Mandarin Publishers Limited, Hong Kong, 1977).

11 [238] WOOLLEY, Sir LEONARD, Excavations at Ur. (Barnes & Noble, Inc., New York and Ernest Benn Limited, London, 1955).

The Near East: 8000 to 5000 B.C.

THE NEAR EAST

The early agriculture of the naturally growing wild wheat and barley in parts of this area allowed the development of communities permanent enough to develop brick and stone for both private and public buildings. The earliest sites were not far from the mountain ranges which had been the original home of the cereals just mentioned and all were within a belt of 300 millimeters (120 inches) rainfall a year, or in a flood plain. Such were Tell es-Sultan at Jericho and Catal Huyuk in central Turkey. The latter covered thirty-two acres with perhaps 6,000 to 10,000 people, with evidence of long distance trade, volcanic glass for tools and blue apatite for ornamentation. This center came to an end about 5,000 B.C., apparently simply abandoned. But the first known pottery and woolen textiles were found there1. Jericho, in Judea, is thought to be the world's oldest city, dating back 9,000 years ago, some 4,000 years before the first Sumerian city. Sitting beside a spring near the Dead Sea, it had stone walls and a tower thirty feet high and a population of perhaps 2,500, all living 800 feet below sea level, whereas its counter-part Catal Huyuk was at an altitude of more than 3,000 feet. In both it appears that women cultivated the crops and looked after cattle while the men went hunting with their newly domesticated dogs.1

1C. (Ref. 2)

Although not yet at the stage of city building, Sumerians in Mesopotamia are thought to have invented the wheel sometime between 65500 and 6,300 B.C. (Ref. 3) Wheat and barley were both grown in southern Iraq by 79000 B.C. Excavations at Tell es-Sawwan, seventy miles northwest of Baghdad indicate a high level of civilization there around 6,000 B.C., with buildings built from unbaked, mortared bricks and houses with access through the roofs and coated with plaster, then bitumen and finally facings of gypsum. This site was occupied for 1,000 years and has similarity to Catal Huyuk although occurring much later in time. It fills in a gap between the new Stone Age and recorded history. Thus the so-called "Neolithic Revolution" appears to have taken place between 7,000 and 6,500 B.C. Some instruments instead of being chipped were now highly polished. The first farm animal tamed was probably the goat, which lives off wild grass. Sheep, pigs and finally cattle followed. The pig is not a ruminant and pig-rearing could not occur until nuts, acorns, meat scraps and cooked grain were available. Cattle, domesticated either in Turkey or Macedonia between 6,000 and 5,800 B.C., offered a difficult task as the originals were fiery and agile, but this was a most important step in man's exploitation of the animal world. They were brought under control by poor feeding, close penning, hobbling and castration of the bulls. The barn yard animal became man's first power tool, but cattle were not used in any other area of the world in this millenium time-frame. Even in this Near East region desert still predominated and man and animals were actually crowded in oases. Eridu was an agricultural settlement of 5,000 B.C. (Ref. 4, 5, 6, 7)

Woolen garments were woven and there is evidence of early trade in obsidian which was ideal for tools. This came from the area of Lake Van and was exported to Mesopotamia as early as 7,000 B.C. Baskets and wooden as well as stone vessels had been invented before the 6th millennium. At Hacilar in Asia Minor, beginning about 5,500 B.C. there is evidence of a Chalcolithic Culture which involves the use of pure copper along with stone. Elam, in southern Iran was settled by the 8th millennium and in the middle of the 6th Iran had farming villages with irrigation agriculture, supplemented by hunting. Animal paintings and imported copper tools have been found.

As we have noted in the last chapter, the Black Sea, up to this time, had been a freshwater lake, connected in turn to the Caspian-Aral system. Now, as the ice cap melted and the sea level rose, salt water in the Mediterranean eventually went over the Bosporan shelf into the Black Sea, killing the fresh-water life it contained. The decomposed remains of this ice-age population still poisons the lower levels of the stagnant Black Sea, which is still devoid of life below 250 feet. (Ref. 8, 9, 10, 11,12, 13, 14)

1 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

2 [315] HAMBLIN, Dora Jane, "Treasures of the Sands", Smithsonian, Sept. 1983, pp. 43-53.

3 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

4 [68] GARRATY, Joh  a. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

5 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

6 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

7 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

8 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

9 [60] ELIOT, JOHN L., "Treasures of Dresden", National Geographic 154: No. 5, Page 702, Nov. 1978.

10 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

11 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

12 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., jr., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

13 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

14 [158] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Early Civilizations in the Middle East. Map from Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., Sept. 1978.

1. Hugh Thomas (Ref. 1) says that the world's first pottery was a monochrome type made in Iraq about 7,000 B.C. with painted pottery appearing about 6,500 B.C.

The Near East: 5000 to 3000 B.C.

ARABIAN PENINSULA

This was the fount and breeding place of the Semitic peoples, although at this particular time only Bedouins and nomad tribesmen existed and there was no true civilization, at least in the western two-thirds of the peninsula. Recent excavations on the Island of Bahrain and adjacent Saudi Arabia have suggested the presence of a vanished empire which the Sumerians referred to as "Dilmun", center of earthly paradise. Excavated objects indicate commercial activity oriented both towards India and Mesopotamia. Surface shards and implements have been dated back to about 4,000 B.C. (Ref. 1) Apparently after the Wet Phase, about 4,000 B.C. there was a progressive dessication of the Arabian peninsula which may have contributed to the northward migrations of peoples into the Syrian Desert which began shortly thereafter. (Ref. 2)1

1C. and their use was extended to Egypt even before the first dynasty, that is, before 3100 B.C. (Ref. 3) Another recent writer, Hamblin (Ref. 4), however, although agreeing that domestication occurred among the southern Arabian tribes, would put the date much later, at 2500 B.C.

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON

The people of the coast in these early millennia may have been of the original Mediterranean race now represented in this part of the world only by the Georgian Caucasians. Timnal, in southern Israel, was a source of large amounts of surf ace ores of malachite, so there was a Chalcolithic Palestinian civilization called the Ghassulian Culture, using the first deliberate alloy, arsenical copper. (Ref. 5) The original locations of coastal towns, and later major cities, was occasioned to great extent by the location of springs and thus there has of ten resulted continuous occupation of the same spots over many centuries, with the consequent rise of debris mounds, or tells (Ref. 6).2

2C., Jemmeh in the northwestern Negev desert was occupied by a small group of Chalcolithic hunting and farming people, but subsequently it was apparently abandoned for some 1,300 to 1,400 years. (Ref. 7)

IRAQ AND SYRIA

Iraq is the area of the ancient Mesopotamia, a word derived from mesos meaning "between" and potamos or "river". The wheel and the plow are thought by most to have been invented or brought here sometime about 3,500 B.C.1. Cattle were used as beasts of burden about the same time. There is evidence of irrigation on a steppe east of Mesopotamia by 5,000 B.C., and classically historians have described three more or less separate civilizations which developed in the river basins of Mesopotamia perhaps as early as 4,500 B.C. The most important of these will be discussed first:

SUMER (On the Euphrates River)All historians seem agreed that the Sumerians were non-Semitic, but their origin is much disputed. Some have suggested Iberian or Dravidian affinities. McEvedy (Ref. 8) thinks they may have been part of the aboriginal Caucasian people and to this is added the opinion of Sir Leonard Woolley (Ref. 9) that their language was that of the early Caucasians. They used copper from 5,000 B.C. onward and their clay tablets give us records back to 3,300 B.C. in the city of Ur, which was then a seaport. The geography of Mesopotamia has changed greatly through the millennia. In addition to the Tigris and Euphrates, the Karun River from the Persian mountains and Wadi al Batin, draining the heart of Arabia, all enter the Persian Gulf, the latter two at almost right angles to the former two. Many millennia ago, the last two rivers discharged a mass of silt across the gulf, which then extended even north of present day Baghdad, and eventually made a bar against which similar silt of the two chief rivers piled up, forming dry land directly across the gulf. The effect was to turn the upper end of the then existing gulf into a stagnant lake which was still fed by the waters of the Tigris and Euphrates, but which then turned from salty to brackish and then to actual fresh water. Eventually, of course, even the lake built up with silt, making the area the most fertile land on earth. Although Ur, then on the sea coast, became the great capital of Sumer, the city of Eridu, south of this, seems older and in a nearby village of al'Ubaid there has been found ancient pottery, in some ways similar to pottery also found at Susa, in ancient Elam and which might have a common ancestry from some foreign place. Could the origin be Bahrain, the island down the gulf where Danish excavations now show a civilization possibly older than Sumer? There is a Sumerian legend which tells how a race of monsters, half fish and half human, came from the Persian Gulf, led by Oannes, and introduced the arts of writing, agriculture and metallurgy.

The Sumerians had wheeled vehicles1, wheel-made pottery, sailboats and animal-drawn plows. The sailboats were of particular interest because recent information indicating a much greater and extensive maritime trade with large, reed, wash-through ships has been made available. Thor Heyerdahl, constructing such a ship from the reeds of the Tigris Euphrates delta region in 1980 has demonstrated that such ships could sail to India and to Africa. The concept that the civilization of Bahrain may have antedated Sumer is compatible with a new theory suggested by Heyerdahl (Ref. 10) and discussed under II,C of this chapter. From the records of Ur there is evidence of the presence of boats of almost one hundred tons and a ceramic boat model in the Iraq Museum with a cylindrical footing for its mast dates back to at least 4,000 B.C. The potters' wheel was invented in Erech about 3,000 B.C., perhaps along with the brick mold.

These same Sumerians developed the duodecimal system of measurement giving rise to our twelve inches to the foot, sixty minutes in an hour and three hundred sixty degrees in a circle. In addition to the island "Dilmun", they mention "Magan" as a distant copper mountain and "Meluhha" which may well have been the great Indus Valley civilization. At 5,000 B.C. they had primitive irrigation systems used to water fields as far as three miles on either side of a river. The resulting larger and richer crops, along with the necessity of water administration systems, probably led to the growth of some of the towns. Eventually, however, this leaching out of the earth's salts led to soil infertility. The food of Sumer included barley, wheat, millett, chickenpeas, lentils, beans, turnips, onions, garlic, leeks, cucumbers, lettuce, cress and mustard. There was plenty of fish and some beef and veal if one could afford it. The beef source, however, was from animals after their useful worklife was over and therefore it was tough. Mutton was common along with goat and pork, the last only until about 1,800 B.C. The Indo-European nomads roaming through the Mid-East may have started the loathing of pork, since they could be herded only with difficulty and had little stamina for movement. Forty percent of the Sumerian grain yield was used for ale production, but since no hops were available there was no true beer.

A temple workman received the equivalent of 2.2 American pints of ale a day and senior dignitaries five times that amount, some of which they may have used as currency. The cultivated grape came to Mesopotamia from the Caucasus about 5,000 B.C. and in later years, as the irrigation soured the soil and grain became more difficult to grow, many people took to either grape or date wines. (Ref. 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18)

AKKADIA-KISH This second center of civilization consisted of a Semitic people living to the north and west of Sumer with a separate culture. There is evidence that their Third Dynasty was in effect as early as 3,638 B.C. More will be heard about them in the next chapter.

IRAN (PERSIA)

A third center of civilization with copper weapons and tools, hieroglyphic writing and domesticated animals appeared east of Sumer, with a capital at Susa. Older writers thought that they might have been a Negroid2 people, some moderns feel that they were probably the ancestors of the Medes, while McEvedy (Ref. 19) writes that they were relatives of the Sumerians, in that they were a part of the original Caucasian race of Georgians. We are speaking of the ancient country of Elam, a part of present Iran. There was much copper around the southern Caucasus, the shore of the Caspian Sea and down to the Persian Gulf. Remains of a Chalcolithic culture have been found at Anau, Tepe Hissar and Rarjy dating to 3,000 B.C. Painted pottery cultures with mixed farming and trade activity existed in central Iran in the 2nd half of the 5th Millennium. Copper lying free had been found and hammered into utensils beginning about 7,000 B.C. and about 5,000 B.C. copper was obtained by firing malachite which releases the flowing metal at a relatively low temperature. Tin ore, of ten found with malachite, soon yielded its metal and the tin-copper (bronze) alloy resulted in some areas by 3,800 B.C. The best bronze, consisting of 15% tin, is three times as hard as copper alone. (Ref. 20, 21, 22)

ASIA MINOR

In this era there were colonies of the Cycladian civilization along the coast and a well developed Chalcolithic culture of basic Caucasian peoples inland. A 1978 study of skeletons from a dig at Kalinkaya in central Anatolia, dating to this period, indicated that the people were relatively short, the men averaging five feet four inches and the women just five feet. 20% of the women had healed ankle fractures or foot bone changes, probably from falls in their rocky country homes. There is some indication of nutritional stress in bowed tibiae, flattened long bones and flattened pelvic inlets. 33% of the limited number of skeletons studied showed vertebral osteoarthritis (compared to 50% in modern United States), and 12% showed extremity osteoarthritis (compared to 29% in modern U.S.) (Ref. 24). Agricultural societies were well distributed and there was trade and migration with other countries of the Near East. (Ref. 25)

1 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

2 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

3 [313] RIPINSKY, MICHAEL, "Camel Ancestry and Domestication in Egypt & the Sahara", Archaeology 36, No. 3: 21-27, May/June, 1983.

4 [315] HAMBLIN, Dora Jane, "Treasures of the Sands", Smithsonian, Sept. 1983, pp. 43-53.

5 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

6 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

7 [295] Van Beek, Gus w. "Digging up Tell Jemmeh", Archaeology 36, Vol. 1: 12-19, Jan./Feb. 1983.

8 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

9 [238] WOOLLEY, Sir LEONARD, Excavations at Ur. (Barnes & Noble, Inc., New York and Ernest Benn Limited, London, 1955).

10 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

11 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

12 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

13 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

14 [238] WOOLLEY, Sir LEONARD, Excavations at Ur. (Barnes & Noble, Inc., New York and Ernest Benn Limited, London, 1955).

15 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

16 [194] SEVERY, MERLE, "The Celts", National Geographic 151: 582-634, May 1977.

17 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

18 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

19 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

20 [21] BRONOWSKI, j., The Ascent of Man. (Little, Brown & Co. Boston, Toronto, 1973).

21 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

22 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

23 [229] WELLS, h.c., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

24 [4] ANGELL, j. LAWRENCE, "Osteoarthritis in Prehistoric Turkey and Medieval Byzantium", Henry Ford Hospital Journal 27: 38, 1979.

25 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

1. As noted in the previous chapter, Trager (Ref. 11) says that the wheel was invented much earlier, just after 6,500 B.C. in Sumeria

2. As for example, H.G. Wells, (Ref. 23)

The Near East: 3000 to 1500 B.C.

THE NEAR EAST

In addition to some new civilizations appearing in this region there were great changes in the old one. We must realize that in this single chapter we are reviewing events spanning 1,500 years or a period equal to that from the time of Christ to the Reformation in Europe. In a few limited ways, there was actual regression in the Near East at this time as the local tin deposits became exhausted and the area slipped back out of the Bronze Age.

THE ARABIAN PENINSULA

Nomadic Semitic tribes continued domination of the central areas of the peninsula, while other Semitic empires controlled the fertile northwestern region of Arabia and present day Jordan. About 2,250 B.C. the Akkadians were extending their influence down into this area and some 400 years later an Arabian tribe of Amorites began their first expansion and began to overflow this entire area of the Fertile Crescent, rolling over into Mesopotamia and beyond.

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON

The ancient basic population of this area were Canaanites, originally Semitic nomads who had early migrated north from Arabia, but in the period under review, two other peoples appeared--the Jews and the Phoenicians. (Ref. 1)1

1C. (Ref. 2)

1. ISRAEL

Semitic speaking people lived a Bronze Age urban life in Palestine from 3,000 to 2,200 B.C. but then for two or three hundred years the city life appears to have been destroyed by an invading nomadic people, probably the Amorites from deep in the Arabian peninsula. After 1,900 B.C. population returned to the urban areas and that period may then be described as the true Canaanite era. The African camel was used in Palestine for caravan trade by 1,600 B.C. The exact time of the arrival of the Jews is debated. Their own tradition says that they came from Ur in about 2,200 B.C., but they probably came up out of the Arabian Peninsula somewhat later. They too, of course, were a Semitic group who rarely intermarried with other stocks, yet some feel that they received their characteristic nose from the non-Semitic Hittites. (Ref. 3) During these early centuries the Jews remained as twelve more or less independent tribes, with a state of civilization developing about 1,800 B.C. Most of them then entered Egypt between 1,800 and 1,650 B.C. perhaps with their "cousins", the Hyksos. It is said that Judaism was founded by Abraham, a prince of Ur, living in Canaan in 1,700 B.C., as he replaced human sacrifice with sacrifice of rams. (Ref. 4, 5, 6)

2. LEBANON (PHOENICIA)

The origin of the Phoenicians who founded the city of Tyre and settled along a strip of coast one hundred miles long and ten miles wide, about 2,800 B.C. is not definitely known, but they may have been simply another Semitic tribe from the region of the Persian Gulf. From 2,600 B.C. on, they were the busiest merchants of the ancient world, manufacturing forms of glass, working metal and producing a famous purple dye from Mediterranean mollusca. The forest of Lebanon supplied the entire middle east with timber and the incredibly durable Lebanon cedar allowed the early Phoenicians, as well as the Hittites, to abandon the earlier papyrus reeds for boats of wood. These people were shrewd traders, stealing from the weak, cheating the stupid and dealing honestly with the rest of mankind. They sailed the seas in seventy feet long, narrow galleys with oars and one large rectangular sail, developing the art of navigation as they sailed from their home cities of Tyre, Byblos and Sidon to develop a great colonial empire. They were known in the Bible as Siddonians. Ugarit was a Canaanite and Phoenician city which has been dubbed the "Shanghai of the mid-2nd millenium B.C.", because it seemed a cross-road of world trade. Texts in Sumerian-Akkadian, Hurrian, Egyptian and Hittite have been found there. The oldest known alphabet was apparently native Canaanite, later improved by the Phoenicians. Some texts show close association of Hebrews to Canaanites before the time of Moses, and much of the moral teaching and ideals of justice of later Hebrew pro- phets were foreshadowed here and there are parallels to the later Biblical psalms, etc. (Ref. 7, 8)

The timber resources of Lebanon were already considerably depleted by 2,000 B.C. but they have continued to be exploited right down to the present time. Olive oil, grain, grapes, sheep and cattle were products in antiquity. Slaves had always been used some, but after 2,000 B.C. large numbers were imported from Egypt, so that it was soon not uncommon for households to have three. (Ref. 9, 10)

IRAQ AND SYRIA

1. MESOPOTAMIA, PROPER

The term "Sumerian" has been coined by scholars from the place name of "Sumer" which by the third millennium was used to mean southern Mesopotamia as apposed to Akkad, the northern part. Sumeria was a city civilization and the important cities of Ur, Uruk, Larsa, Eridu and Kish had populations ranging from 15,000 to 250,000. One or more temple communities constituted a city, with priest administration and work-gangs to operate the irrigation system. The land of the city was divided into several categories, with some fields owned by the gods and worked on their behalf, some fields rented out annually to individuals and others awarded to individuals, rent-free.

The first dynasty of Ur has been dated archaeologically and historically from the King- lists (royal genealogical tablets found on the site) to about 2,700 B.C., but there was a high civilization at Ur before this, perhaps with the city functioning under the suzerainty of the Erech Dynasty. At least what appears to have been a royal cemetery has been excavated, dated prior to the first dynasty of Ur, in which the ritual of burial included human sacrifice, varying from six to seventy or eighty people, sometimes including asses and carts with grooms and various women's bodies. There was no evidence of violence; the men and women sacrificial attendants probably simply drank a drug and went quietly to sleep. Nothing like human sacrifice was ever mentioned from the later Sumeria. At any rate, the actual, historical first dynasty of Ur was that of Mes-an-ni-pad-da of about 2,700 B.C. and it lasted supposedly for 177 years. During the later part of this time, at about 2,600 B.C. it had succeeded in conquering various surrounding areas, under King Urukagina. This was followed by the usurpation of neighboring Umma by King Lugalzaggesi. Situated on the flat lands of the lower Euphrates, Sumer had no natural defenses and the cities became tempting objects of plunder to the barbarous people around. About 2,300 B.C. Sumeria was conquered by the neighboring Akkadians under their great leader, Sargon I. The Sumerian culture seemed to continue in the new, combined empire, however, and a "Golden Age of Ur" resulted. Sargon wrote of ships laden with goods in harbor at his capital and there were caravans of 200 donkeys traveling 12 to 15 hours a day plying between Armenia and Iraq. From 2,112 to 2,015 B.C. Ur remained the capital of this great empire, ruled by the five kings of the third dynasty. Iraq had a population of between four and five million at that time.

One of the characteristic features of each great Sumerian city was the ziggurat and that of Ur has been the best preserved. It has been suggested that if the Sumerians came originally from the Caucasus, one might assume that they felt that their gods had to have a mountain to stand or live on, and so they built the ziggurats, as substitutes. Ur was destroyed sometime after 2,000 B.C. and then for awhile it was under Isin lordship, then under the city of Larsa and finally under the Elamites who came from south Persia. The Elamite prince, Warad-Sin, who became king of Ur, rebuilt and enlarged the temples of the ancient city and his successor, Rim-sin served as king of Larsa also, and during his reign the population of the "old town" of Ur, that is, within the original walls, included an estimated 4,250 houses, probably with 34,000 people. The whole city, then, must have exceeded 250,000 and may have been twice that large. It was a manufacturing center with raw materials imported, sometimes from overseas via the Persian Gulf. Gold, copper ore, hard woods, ivory, pearls and precious stones were all brought by ship and recorded in bills of lading. (Ref. 11, 12, 13)

But Ur was not to last much longer. Although there is still some disagreement about dating, we shall assume that Hammurabi started his rule in Babylon in 1,783 B.C. and then in the 12th year of the reign of his son, Samsi-iluna, the Babylonians destroyed the walls of Ur with a terrible thoroughness and laid waste to the city. Up until that time, all the tablets and texts of Ur (and there were thousands of them) were written in the Sumerian language (Caucasian?), but after that destruction the tablets were in the Babylonian language. The invaders took over the cuneiform writing, but the Sumerian language itself became a dead literary and religious tongue. This fall of Sumeria may have been prepared in part by internal disintegration and class wars within the city-state (Ref. 14, 15)

The conquering Babylonians were actually Amorites and the new combination of Amorite-Akkadian-and non-Semitic Sumerian civilization became known as the Babylonian1, with the Semitic strain the dominant one. Hammurabi had forged out this empire and put his capital at Babylon. (Please note the map below).

NOTE: Insert Map taken from Reference 97.

Agriculture thrived as great new irrigation canals were developed. The Babylonians, of the same basic stock as Abraham and the later Hebrews, or Jews, had the beginnings of astronomy and the ability to predict eclipses. They had a calendar and could handle cubic equations with two unknowns. The Babylonian society demonstrated the development of an imperial political theory, an improved administrative technique, especially through the use of written communication, the development of a bureaucracy and professional army, and finally better methods of inter-city and inter-regional trade, along with the promotion of an independent merchant class. A code of laws, based on Sumerian prototypes, has become famous as the Code of Hammurabi, put into effect about 1,750 B.C. This code covered most ordinary life activities, even condemning ale houses for under-strength, over-priced beer. Forty percent of the grain in some cities went to the manufacture of beer. The code also regulated many medical fees for such things as treating severe wounds, tumors, and broken bones. The fees were high - for example, that for successfully treating a freeman's broken bone was five shekels of silver, a value equal to the yearly rent for a middle-class dwelling. But the punishments for poor medical treatment were equally elevated. (Ref. 17, 18, 19, 20)

Sometime about 1,600 B.C. or perhaps slightly earlier, Babylonia was conquered by a combined force of Aryan (McEvedy, [Ref. 136], says Caucasian) Kassites1 from the east and Hittites from near Asia Minor. The Hittites quickly withdrew, taking the Sumerian script with them, leaving the Kassites to rule Babylonia for about six centuries. Some believe that they brought the horse with them from the Samartian flatlands. On the other hand, Lewinsohn (Ref. 21) says that riding horses were first mentioned in historical records at the time of Hammurabi, about 2,000 B.C., although chariots had been used earlier by Sumerian kings. As mentioned earlier, Mesopotamia was the home of the spectacular, brick-built temple monuments called "ziggurats", many having been built between 3,000 and 500 B.C. Among the first of these was one called the "White Temple", probably dedicated to Amu, god of the sky, at ancient Uruk (Erech of the Bible), capital of several Sumerian dynasties. It was built about 3,000 B.C. on a platform forty feet high. Even the Kassites built ziggurats - the remains of a spectacular one still some two hundred feet high, remains at Aquarquf, the Kassite capital just west of Baghdad. (Ref. 22, 23, 24)2

2 (Ref. 25)  It was in the Mesopotamia area that the two-wheeled chariot was invented about 1,800 B.C. as a result of the development of spoked wheels with a friction-reducing hub and axle design. The compound bow was also developed so that mobility and fire power in war were greatly increased. The steppe people were best able to take advantage of this and between 1800 and 1500 B.C. waves of barbarian charioteers overran the Middle East. At the same time rich merchants were using donkey caravans to move tin eastward and textiles westward, from the Persian Gulf to Anatolia, with profits up to 100% in a year. (Ref. 26)

2. SYRIA AND ADJACENT AREAS

Recent excavations in northwestern Syria between what was subsequently Ugarit and Carchemish, indicate that a great empire with a capital city of Ebla existed prior to and after the 23rd century B.C. Fifteen thousand cuneiform tablets with commercial records, treaties and chronicles have been found, written in a previously unknown Semitic language. This is four times the number of all previously found texts of this period. It is evident that metallurgy, textiles, ceramics and woodworking were well developed. Thirty thousand people in the City were surrounded by about 250 million in the immediate area.

More than five thousand geographic names appear, indicating far greater settlement of the Near East at that ancient time than previously believed. Beirut and Byblos, Damascus and Gaza, as well as Sodom and Gomorrah are all mentioned. Some people named may be the Abraham, Esau and Saul, of the Bible. The language and culture of Ebla may have survived in such later Canaanite centers as Ugarit and even Palestine. Thriving by 2,400 B.C. (or even 2,500), Ebla's kings apparently contended with Sargon of Akkad for domination of the Euphrates area. Sargon's grandson, Naram-Sin, conquered Ebla, but it rose again, only to fall once more about 2,000 B.C., perhaps wiped out by the Amorites. Their language has been identified as a forerunner of all the Canaanite dialects, which include Ugaritic, Phoenician and Hebrew. Translation became possible because of the finding of some dual language dictionaries, containing both Sumerian and Eblaite. (Ref. 27)

At times war and at times periods of cooperation occurred with another powerful city, Mari, about half-way down the Euphrates from Ebla to Babylon. The French excavations at Mari show a royal palace of three hundred rooms and courts and evidence of Egyptian trade. At one time Mari was ruled by Shura-Damu, son of Ebrium who had been probably Ebla's greatest king. These kings were elected and Ebrium had served four terms of seven years each. (Ref. 28)

To the northwest were the Assyrians who began to rise as a militant power by 1,700 B.C. and to the southwest, between the Assyrians and the Egyptians, was another Semitic tribe which was originally a Bedouin group appearing from the Syrian desert and whose descendants are today's true Syrians. They may have been pushed north and east as the Hyksos were expelled from Egypt. They made Damascus their chief city. Of greatest importance, however, was the migration of the Amorites who came out of the desert about 2,100 B.C. to take over most of the entire area, including the city of Babylon and then the entire Euphrates Valley. (Please see paragraphs above on Mesopotamia, proper.)

Finally, coming out of their original homeland east and north of Lake Van (Armenia) as early as the late 3rd millennium B.C. were an Asianic-speaking people called Hurrians, who settled in large numbers in northern Syria and Mesopotamia. Although the Hurrians, themselves, may well have been of the old, original Caucasian race, they apparently had an aristocracy of Indo-European origin called "Mitanni". By 1,600 B.C. they had a series of kingdoms. Some authorities believe that they introduced the horse and chariot to the Near East as war vehicles. What is often called the Mitanni Kingdom was actually a federation of Hurrian states under the kings of Wahukanni. At one period, King Tushratta captured and held the stone capital of Assyria, Nineveh. (Ref. 29, 30)

IRAN (PERSIA)

The Bronze Age on the plateau of central Iran began about 3,000 B.C. A basic agricultural economy was soon augmented by export of lapis lazuli from the northeast and steatite (soapstone) from the southeast. The metal industry followed that of Elam and Babylonia. The Elamite civilization with its capital at Susa continued to flourish in a limited geographical area and their antagonisms and military vigor were manifested in their raids of Sumer. The Mitanni and the Hurrians lived in parts of northern Iran before their migrations into northern Syria. Writings appeared early in Persia, notably in the region of Elam, where the cultural relations were closer to Mesopotamia than to the remainder of Persia. Elamites also had indirect trade with Egypt. (Ref. 31, 32)

The linguist, Pei (Ref. 33), believes that the Indo-European peoples and their basic language originated by about 2,500 B.C. either on the Iranian plateau or about the Baltic Sea, while Wells (Ref. 34) would put the date several thousand years earlier (See also Eastern Europe). McEvedy (Ref. 35) indicates a southern Russia and lower central Asian origin around the Aral Sea, with these early Indo-Europeans, which he labels "Iranians", as beginning migrations from central Asia down into Iran by 2,250 B.C. and even pushing into Syria by 1,600 B.C. Their gray Gurgan pottery is found at the excavation site of Tepe Hissar just south and east of the Caspian Sea. These same Iranians spread across central Asia, becoming the base population of the steppe, while another segment moved south, eventually invading India. As the Iranians stormed into the Middle East at the end of the time period under review, they were accompanied by clans of the Caucasian Kassites and Hurrians, with war chariots. (Please also see Europe: 5000 to 3000 B.C.). (Ref. 36, 37, 38, 39)

ASIA MINOR (ANCIENT ANATOLIA)

Prehistoric copper cultures have been validated by excavations of Troy (3,000-2,400) and Alishar Huyuk (3,000-2,800). As these great copper supplies were developed, the axis of history began to shift to this Mediterranean region and away from Mesopotamia. About 3,000 B.C. there were a series of local early Bronze Age cultures, including the Yortan Culture of northwest Anatolia, which had close relationships to the Cycladic Culture of the Aegean, and the first Troy (Kisarlik). The Trojan artisans learned to toughen copper by alloying it with small amounts of tin by about 3,000 but the source of this tin is un- known. Regional divisions in the peninsula became quite marked with each controlled by a native dynasty and metropolitan centers soon became quite wealthy. (Ref. 40) By 2,000 B.C. the Assyrians had trading posts in the area, such as at Kanesh (modern Kultepe) where the form of certain names in tablets indicates the arrival of an Indo-European speaking people, the Hittites. By 1,750 B.C. the latter had become a dominant military caste, controlling important cities. They may actually have appeared first some five hundred years earlier, settling in the bend of the Halys River, but their origin is much disputed.

Traditionally they have been described as coming down from the region of the Caspian Sea, but more recent studies would suggest that they had origin from the Aegean Sea peoples and came at this period from the shores of Greece and the Aegean Islands, along with their kinsmen, the Luvians (also Luwians). The Hittite migration was only the central component in a trio of displacements. From north of the Black Sea the Usatove were moving into the Balkan area and at the base of the Anatolian peninsula the Caucasian Khirbet Kerak were moving down into Syria and even into Palestine. These people have also been called Hattites and represent the original population of Anatolia.

The Hittite language had declensional and conjugational forms similar to both Latin and Greek and some of their simple words were visibly akin to modern English, such as:

Vadar - water, and
Essa - eat.

The Hittites had sharp, aquiline noses and Wells (Ref. 41) felt that they had fused sufficiently with the early Hebrews to give the latter this nose as a trademark. The basic population of Turkey, today, also has this physical feature. The Hittites had iron and used it.

Their society was probably related in some way to the Sumerian and many of their customs were similar. Politically they had a warrior aristocracy, but they also had art, religion and writing, all exhibiting close affinities with Mesopotamian models. The first known rulers of the old Hittite Kingdom were Labarnas and his son Hattusilis II. In 1,595 B.C., under Muresilis I, they conquered Babylon. The Luvians, related to the Hittites, had penetrated Asia Minor during the latter part of the 3rd millennium B.C. and were soon active in the west with a principal city of Beycesultan on the River Meander. That city was destroyed in 1,750 B.C., perhaps by the Hittite King Labarnas I.

East of the Hittites was the area of ancient Armenia, known in that time as "Urartu" and in some places in the Bible as "Ararat". The people we call "Armenians" today, however, probably did not arrive until at least the 8th century B.C. Even in the early time of the third millennium the overland trade routes of traders to the steppes of Asia crisscrossed this land, and the indigenous population was skilled in the secrets of ancient metallurgy. In at least the later part of the period under survey, the basic population of Urartu was comprised of the non-Semitic, probably Caucasian, Hurrian and Vannic peoples. (Ref. 42, 43, 44)

1 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

2 [295] Van Beek, Gus w. "Digging up Tell Jemmeh", Archaeology 36, Vol. 1: 12-19, Jan./Feb. 1983.

3 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

4 [18] BRITISH MUSEUM, (Personal notes, 1978).

5 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

6 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

7 [95] HEYERDAHL, Thor, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

8 [87] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, The World of the Past. (Two volumes). (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1927.

9 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

10 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

11 [238] WOOLLEY, Sir LEONARD, Excavations at Ur. (Barnes & Noble, Inc., New York and Ernest Benn Limited, London, 1955).

12 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

13 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

14 [238] WOOLLEY, Sir LEONARD, Excavations at Ur. (Barnes & Noble, Inc., New York and Ernest Benn Limited, London, 1955).

15 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

16 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

17 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and Gay, Peter, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

18 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

19 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

20 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

21 [122]  LEWINSOHN, Richard, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

22 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

23 [122]  LEWINSOHN, Richard, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

24 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

25 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

26 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

27 [117] La Fay, Howard, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

28 [117] La Fay, Howard, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

29 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

30 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

31 [18] BRITISH MUSEUM, (Personal notes, 1978).

32 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

33 [168] Pei, Mario. The Story of Language. (Revised Edition). (J.P. Lippincott Co., Philadelphia & New York 1962.

34 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

35 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

36 [168] Pei, Mario. The Story of Language. (Revised Edition). (J.P. Lippincott Co., Philadelphia & New York 1962.

37 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

38 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

39 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

40 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

41 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

42 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

43 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

44 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

1.  As with the Hurrians and Mitannians to be discussed later, it is probable that the Caucasian Kassites were led by an Aryan (Indo-European aristocracy. (Ref. 16)

The Near East: 1500 to 1000 B.C.

THE ARABIAN PENINSULA

There were multiple nomadic tribes in the Arabian Peninsula and very dry areas were opened for settlement by the use of lime plaster for watertight cisterns. In present day Jordan, Ammon became the capital of the Ammonite tribe and legend has it that this city was conquered by the Judean King David. The Aramic-speaking Arameans lived primarily around Palmyra and with their camels they began to attack the "fertile crescent" to the north and east. At about 1,000 B.C. they began to migrate east to Babylonia, north toward Asia Minor and west to Damascus. Their relatives, the Chaldeans, began to emerge from central Arabia and also started toward Babylon, and more particularly toward Ur, in Sumer. (Ref. 1)

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON

About 1,500 B.C. an entirely new type of writing was recorded for the first time, in the Sinai Peninsula. This was an alphabet in which each sign represented one consonant. It soon spread among the Phoenicians and other Semites on the coast. Although originally written in a cuneiform, the Phoenicians later replaced it with letters which could be written faster on paper. The derivation of various mid-eastern scripts is as follows:

Note: Insert chart from p107

ISRAEL: PALESTINE: JUDEA

Peoples of Semitic speech occupied Palestine in successive waves, including Amorites, Hebrews, Israelites and Arabs. Egypt, under Thutmoses III, conquered Palestine in 1,479 B.C. and controlled the area almost continuously thereafter in this period under review. This is probably the time of the "Exodus" of the Jews from Egypt back to the "Promised Land" in the vicinity of Palestine. The true history of their long migration back and the trials and tribulations with other tribes along the way and in the regions of Judea and Palestine are mixed with legend and myth in the Old Testament, which was written much later. Saul became the first king of the Jews in 1,025 B.C. and supposedly David became king in 1,010 B.C. Unfortunately there is no contemporary mention of this in any literature except the Bible and the later Greek historian, Procopius. Throughout this era the Jews were dominated by the Philistines who were probably refugees from the collapsing Cretan civilization, or were Luvians, or both. In one battle, dated at 1,141 B.C. by Trager (Ref. 2), the Israelites lost 4,000 men and later lost another 30,000. The Philistine invasion was a part of the Sea Peoples raids which plagued the entire Mediterranean coast at that period. (Ref. 3)1

1C. was occupied by Canaanites. The city had a very large house or palace measuring 19.2 meters by 16.5 meters, with a paved courtyard. There was a large amount of imported pottery from Mycenaea, Greece and Cyprus.  When the Sea Peoples arrived, they actually occupied and settled many coastal towns, including Ashdod, Ashkelon, Gaza, Ekron and Gath. (Ref. 4)

LEBANON: PHOENICIA

The Phoenicians, as a people, cannot be differentiated from the general mass of Canaanites until sometime in this 2nd half of the 2nd millennium B.C., but by 1,200 they had liberated themselves from Egyptian domination and they soon became the true masters of the Mediterranean seaways, sailing to Italy, Spain and all along the coast of north Africa. They may even have sailed around the continent of Africa. Present day Beirut, however, was still subject to the Amorites at that time. The importance of their alphabetic script is indicated in the chart above.

IRAQ AND SYRIA

BABYLONIA (MESOPOTAMIA)

Babylonia, on the lower two-thirds of the Tigris and Euphrates, remained throughout these five hundred years chiefly under Kassite rule and there was little progress in civilization except during the reign of the Kassite king, Kurigalzu II, who was a great builder. He constructed innumerable monuments, not only in Ur, but in other southern cities. No one knows the reason for this sudden spurt of industry, but the growing signs of strength in neighboring Assyria and Mitanni and in the area of the Hittites may have been a factor. Unfortunately none of the Kassite monuments were particularly artistic. As mentioned in the last chapter, these people were probably a mixed body of warriors with at least two linguistic elements, an original Caucasian and an Indo-European. The Kassites were overthrown by raiding Elamites in 1,157 B.C. and the previously great city of Ur then sank into obscurity for at least three or four centuries. (Ref. 5)

ASSYRIA

To the north and west of Babylonia, proper, the Assyrians were accumulating in an increasing number of city-states, at first just in the area immediately around Nineveh, Memrud, Arbil and Asher. In 1,244 B.C., however, Tukulti-Ninurta took over a great deal of old Babylon and apparently contested with the Kassites for most of Mesopotamia, so that the latter were squeezed between these invaders and the raiding Elamites from the east. By 1,115 B.C. the Assyrian Tiglath-Pileser I had lost some territory on the lower Tigris but had gained a precarious corridor to the Mediterranean north of Damascus, between Arwad and Sidon.

NOTE: Insert Illustration - Map Reference 97

Up to 1,380 B.C. various Mitannian lords had been dominant in that area, but after Shalmaneser I united the Assyrian states under one central rule, the Mitannians were kept in a small kingdom just to the west of Assyria. The Assyrians were a mixture of warrior Semites from the south, non-Semitic tribes of Hittite and/or Mittanian origin from the west and Kurds from the Caucasus. They used a common language taken from Sumer, but modified it to practical similarity with Babylonian. Multiple languages persisted, however, making work difficult for the scribes, so that those of Ugarit1 finally reduced the repertory of signs for their own language down to thirty.

Prior to 1,250 B.C. there had been a great struggle for control of the Assyrian lands, which was the same area that has been known with variations in its borders, throughout history chiefly as Syria, including the cities of Byblos and Damascus. The struggle for control by Egypt, the Hittites, the Ugarits, Babylonians and Mitannis, all using essentially the Babylonian language and chariotry, occurred because Syria was the junction for all trade routes between the East, Asia Minor, the Aegean and Egypt. From 1,500 to 1,400

B.C. the Mitanni intermittently controlled all north Syria and Cilicia but from 1,380 to 1,346 the Hittites cut them off and dominated the region. After 1,200 B.C. there were waves of barbarian invasions which included the Hebrews, Philistines and Arameans, as well as the Sea People, Chaldeans and Medes. By the 12th century B.C. the dominant people in Syria were the Arameans, who became the greatest inland traders and whose language became the paramount commercial tongue. Damascus, at the end of the major caravan route across the desert, became the most important city of the region. (Ref. 7, 8, 9)

IRAN: PERSIA

In the northern and western parts of Persia, cultural traditions were broken about 1,300 B.C. with the appearance of monochrome, polished pottery along with the definitive Iron Age, and the arrival from the northeast of the Indo-European languages, as the Medes and Persians migrated down from areas of central Asia. In the southwest, Elam continued as a more or less independent state with a high cultural level which reached its height from 1,300 to 1,100 B.C., reaching a special peak under Untash-Gal. The largest surviving ziggurat in the world, some 170 feet high with five levels, is at Tchoga Zanbil, some eighteen miles from Susa, the ancient capital of Elam. In the middle of the 12th century B.C. Elam had a brief expansion into the Dujala area and eastern Assyria (old Mesopotamia), when the leaders were probably seeking to gain control of the Zagros trade routes. The Elamites had a glass technology and cast bronze. (Ref. 10, 11, 12, 13)

ASIA MINOR: ANATOLIA

The famous Trojan War, formerly considered only an Homerian legend, probably actually occurred about 1,200 B.C. with Agamemnon leading the Mycenean Greek forces against Troy. Homer said that the Thracians, led by King Rhesus, came to the Trojans' aid, and it is known that at that time the Mycenaeans did assume power over all the eastern Mediterranean. Hittite and Egyptian chronicles seem to confirm this. Farther inland the Hittites, under their greatest king, Shubbiluliu (also Suppiluliumas) reconquered central Anatolia and northern Syria and reduced the Mitanni to a small vassal kingdom by about 1,350 B.C. and all north Syria was under their control by 1,340. In 1,250 they forced Ramses II of Egypt to acknowledge their king as his equal. Carchemish, in Syria, was one of the more important of the smaller Hittite states, and the people were the Hittites mentioned in the Bible. At that time, what little iron was available in the world was in the Hittite Anatolian kingdom, but it was worth forty times its weight in silver. In fact, it is said that the Chalybes, a sub-tribe of the Hittites, even made steel bars by about 1,400 B.C., using them in limited quantities for knives and swords. (Ref. 14, page 282) The Hittite language is the earliest documented Indo European tongue and was written usually in cuneiform script borrowed from Mesopotamia about 1,500 B.C. The capital city, Hattusas, was protected by a massive, dry stone wall three and three-quarters miles around. Some of the stones were as large as twenty-six by twenty feet. When this capital was mysteriously sacked about 1,190 B.C., the brick houses of Hattuses were subjected to such intense heat that the bricks fused. It should be realized that the Hittites had access to the same Lebanese cedar forests as the Phoenicians and that they built elaborate wooden ships even before the latter. Ancient Hittite seals indicate that they also built reed ships. Remarkable conformities exist if one compares the early Hittite civilization and the early Olmec civilization at La Venta, Mexico. The similarities include motifs and technique of highly specialized ceramic effigy jars, stone statues with inlaid shell and obsidian eyes, adobe mounds, a solar deity sculpted with a feather crown and a body half serpent and half bird (plumed serpent) and some hieroglyphics - completely different from other middle eastern scripts. (Ref. 15, 16, 17, 18)

At the end of the 13th and in the 12th century B.C. part of the Hittite territory was taken over by the upsurging Sea People and in the 11th century, the Assyrians took over the rest, so that the Hittite civilization, as such, died out or was absorbed in the next few hundreds of years. Phrygean invaders from Thrace, and Luvians, may have played a major part in this destruction of the Hittite Empire. As the political entity collapsed, however, these ironsmiths of Anatolia then spread far and wide, taking their iron weapons with them so that their culture actually survived in neo-Hittite kingdoms, particularly in north Syria near Carchemish. (Ref. 19)

Still farther east, in Urartu, also known as the Kingdom of Van and later as Armenia, the Hurrian and Vannic peoples (related to the Mitanni) whose languages were related continued their own high level civilization.

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

3 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

4 [295] Van Beek, Gus w. "Digging up Tell Jemmeh", Archaeology 36, Vol. 1: 12-19, Jan./Feb. 1983.

5 [238] WOOLLEY, Sir LEONARD, Excavations at Ur. (Barnes & Noble, Inc., New York and Ernest Benn Limited, London, 1955).

6 [115] Kuh, MICHAEL, "Saffron Roles in Gilded Thailand", Great Religions of the World. (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

7 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

8 [118] Fay, HOWARD, "Syria", National Geographic 157: 485-511, Apr. 1980.

9 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

10 [18] BRITISH MUSEUM, (Personal notes, 1978).

11 [18] BRITISH MUSEUM, (Personal notes, 1978).

12 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

13 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

14 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

15 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

16 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

17 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

18 [95] HEYERDAHL, Thor, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

19 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

1.  Ugarit, on the Syrian coast, was the great Canaanite capital. Excavated by the French in 1921, the city is thought to have contained about 10,000 people with a highly developed sanitation system. It had a library of cuneiform tablets. (Ref. 6)

The Near East: 1000 to 700 B.C.

THE NEAR EAST

THE ARABIAN PENINSULA

North and south Arabia presented two separate ethnic groups, separated by a vast central desert. The northerners were nomads, but the south had an advanced culture with urban living, a high social organization, a unique irrigational system and a relatively advanced technology. Several kingdoms existed, such as the Minaean and Sabaean (Yemen). The Queen of Sheba, also called Queen Balkis, supposedly came from the latter country. It is generally supposed that this Queen, who has really never been further identified, came from the land of Sheba, or Yemen, yet there is no historical mention of the culture of the nation of Sheba until about two centuries after the Queen allegedly visited Solomon in Palestine. Exploration and excavation of that area of Yemen has been hindered by Islamic attitudes, for Sheba was cursed by the Prophet Mohammed as a pagan land, and all recent attempts at excavations have been totally thwarted by the present Moslem inhabitants. At the time of the legendary visit of the Queen of Sheba to Palestine, Solomon's power was at its peak. His garrisons controlled all the roads from the Euphrates to the Sinai and from the Red Sea to Palmyra. His army included 12,000 horsemen and 1,400 war chariots.

Camels, which had been used by the Arameans for a long time, came into common domestic use about 1,000 B.C. and became more and more important for desert trade routes and war. Four camels can carry a ton of merchandise and go for three days without water, covering twenty-five miles a day. A major camel route from Yemen to Palestine via Hejaz carried Arabia's resins (myrrh, frankincense and balsam) used in perfumes, incense and medicines, but also must have carried re-exported goods from East Africa and India. The trip required nearly three months by the coastal route. The nomad camel drivers of that era enjoyed a dish of camel hair and blood, mixed and cooked. Marib was the capital of Sabaea, one of the city-states of north Yemen which acquired wealth and power from this camel traffic. An irrigation dam, perhaps built there in that period lasted more than a thousand years. The natives of Sheba, Ma'in, Aqtaban and Hazarmoth were Semites from the north, worshiping the sun, the moon and Venus, which they called Ashtar, and their government was similar to that of Sumer. They were geographically isolated and tough. The city of Amman, in Jordan, gained independence from Solomon in the 10th century B.C., but 200 years later Jordan, as a whole, was conquered by the Assyrians. (Ref. 1, 2, 3, 4)1

1C. tell how Gindibu, with 1,000 camel riders from the "Land of the "Aribi" aided the King of Damascus against the Assyrian King Shalmaneser II at the battle of Karkor. Overland traffic with camels north and south in the peninsula became safer than water traffic on the Red Sea, with its off-shore islands and reefs and vicious pirates.  Small cities near oases or spring-fed wells grew into international centers, rich in goods and culture in this first millennium B.C. An example – Taima in the north, where a religious reformer, Nabonidus, moved from Babylon and built a great palace. The city was surrounded by seven miles of wall. (Ref. 5)

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON

The shore line of the Mediterranean assumed great importance in this period of world history, as several separate centers of civilization developed as the probable forerunners of our own civilization. The promotion of Hebrew monotheism forecasted the later development of Christianity, and the rise of the Greek Culture was the dawn of the Greek-Roman world which eventually took over that Christianity and bequeathed it to the western world. Professor Toynbee (Ref. 6) feels that the Phoenicians, Israelites and Syrians of that age, along with the Philistine refugees from the Cretan world and Hebrew nomads from Arabia, all together formed a separate and distinct society which he called the Syriac. He feels that it was the parent society of both western Christendom and the Islamic Society of later years. This is an interesting theory and convenient, but others do not associate these communities in this way. Toynbee dates the beginning of the breakdown of this group to the death of Solomon, but claims that it continued on to the Universal State in the 6th century B.C. under the Babylonian Nebuchadrezzar.

NOTE: Insert Map from Reference 97

ISRAEL: PALESTINE

Solomon slew all rival claimants to the throne of Judea, including his half-brother, and became king of the Jews from 974 to 937 B.C. Rich copper mines found near the Red Sea and Phoenician merchant trade helped the treasury and gold mining in Arabia allegedly promoted through the Queen of Sheba, was an extra boon. The Phoenicians, in exchange for access to the Red Sea and some twenty Galilean towns, brought technical expertise to Israel. At a place on the Gulf of Aqaba (perhaps modern Elat), the Phoenicians constructed the long distance boats which were their specialty and mounted joint trading expeditions with the Israelites. Wood for the boats came from Lebanon's great cedars and was floated by sea to Jaffe. As an incidental note, Solomon amassed several tons of gold each year, so much that he covered the walls of his great temple with it. Although in many ways unprincipled and with an alleged 700 wives (his first was the daughter of the pharaoh of Egypt) and 300 concubines, he had only one God, Yahweh. There is much confusion about the origin of Yahweh - he may have been one and the same with the Canaan god Yahu, dating back in that tribe to 3,000 B.C. who, taken over by the Hebrews was re-created in their own likeness, or it is possible that the "God Abraham" was a house-hold god brought from ancient Ur, while the "God Moses" may have originated separately, with a fusion of these two accomplished later by Jews who did not come from Egypt. At any rate, Yahveh originally was a god of the desert and war, and could never easily be reconciled with an agricultural deity. Shortly after Solomon's death his son, Rehoboam, refused to reduce the terribly high taxes and ten northern tribes revolted to form a new nation of Israel around the city of Samaria. Two southern tribes remained at Jerusalem as the nation of Judah. Ephraim (today this is in Jordan) became the capital of the northern country and Jerusalem the capital of Judea (Judah). (Ref. 7, 8, 9)

Judea was soon conquered by the Libyan rulers of Egypt. A hundred years later King Shab, of Israel, held off the Assyrians at Qarqar (853 B.C.) but in another century the Assyrians destroyed adjacent Samaria and besieged Jerusalem, taking 200,000 Jews captive. These were the so-called "Lost Tribes of Israel". Sargon II actually carried out the deportation which was previously ordered by his predecessor, Tiglath Pileser III1. In this atmosphere of political disruption, economic war and religious degeneration, the Jewish prophets appeared. They were radical, anti-clerical and socialistic. The first was Amos (750 B.C.) followed by Hosea (740 B.C.) who denounced the Israelites for the worship of gods other than Yahweh. Amos and Isaiah, who appeared in 702 B.C., may be considered as the beginning of both Christianity and socialism, the "…spring from which has flowed a stream of Utopias…"2 In this period Judah kept some independence but as a vassal state of Assyria. Biblical Hebrew medical ideas were drawn chiefly from the adjacent Mediterranean concepts. They believed in supernatural causation of disease although they did not envision a world filled with demons and spirits at that time. Hygienic laws were enforced for religious and disciplinary rather than medical reasons, and these regulations reached into almost every corner of daily living. The taboo on pork was probably not hygienic or medicinal but simply because pigs competed with humans for the scarce grain and water, while sheep and cattle drank little water and ate only grass. Many of the alleged leprosy cases of the Bible were probably other skin diseases. Some medicines were mentioned in the Bible - mandrake, balsams, gums, oils, and possibly narcotics. No surgery was mentioned except the ritual circumcision. Physicians were taken from the priestly tribe of Levites, and were apparently held in high esteem. (Ref. 10)

LEBANON: PHOENICIA

(Please see map in connection with GREECE, this chapter)

This was a period of great wealth and territorial expansion for the Phoenicians. King Hiram, of the city of Tyre, had friendly relations with the Hebrew kings and, as we have noted, entered into many trade agreements with them. The Phoenicians developed an overseas empire, including colonies on Cyprus, the Aegean islands, in Spain and at Carthage in north Africa, carrying and teaching their alphabet to the nations of antiquity and disseminating the use of papyrus. Their settlement at Gades (later Cadiz, Spain) gave them access to the gold, silver and copper from Tartessus. They exported ivory carvings, silver-work, colored glass and fine fabrics. They are said to be the first people who were able to navigate by the stars, sail beyond the sight of land and at night and to voyage on the seas in winter-time. It is to be recalled that these people were probably basically Canaanites and their chief object of worship was the goddess Ishtar, who subsequently became the Greek goddess Astarte. The British Museum has some excellent Phoenician ivory carvings of this period. (Ref. 12, 13, 14)

IRAQ AND SYRIA

Just over the mountains from Phoenicia the Semitic Syrians had been developing an advanced civilization with a capital at Damascus. Although dominated during the three hundred years of this time period by the Assyrians, the true Syrians were a separate people, with their own culture perhaps more closely related to the Phoenicians and Israelites than to their neighbors to the north and east. They worshipped Astarte and also Adonis, who regularly arose from the dead. The Assyrian conquests so gutted northern Syria, however, that the area subsequently remained unimportant for the next 400 years. The Assyrians attacked in waves. Under Ashurnasirpal II and his son, Shalmaneser III (883-824 B.C.) they pushed through to take the entire eastern Mediterranean down to Palestine and northward to the Taurus, which was important as a trade route to Europe and as a source of metals, and then south toward Damascus where they came into conflict with the Arameans and their allies in Israel. (Ref. 15) Soon Damascus itself was conquered by Shalmanesar IV, who was followed after an interval by Tiglath-Pileser III. He then reconquered Armenia, northern Syria, Babylonia and overall extended the Assyrian rule from the Caucasus to Egypt. Their military roads actually facilitated trade by the native Aramean-Syrians who spread their language and fostered a cosmopolitan culture in the middle east. The last of the wild elephants of Syria were killed off in this period, although tusks were still imported from Africa and perhaps India, for carving. (Ref. 16)

As implied above, ancient Babylonia passed from Kassite to Assyrian control early in this period, but by about 900 B.C., the Chaldeans, who were simply one group of Arameans, began to infiltrate the region and eventually, with help, the Chaldean aristocracry threw out the Assyrians. *** (Page 1185)2

2 The Assyrians, rather than the steppe nomads, may have pioneered cavalry in the use of paired horsemen, with one rider holding both sets of reins so that the second rider could use both hands for his bow. (Ref. 17)

IRAN: PERSIA

In the early part of this first millennium B.C. the people of western Iran were hassled by Assyria and Urartu as well as by raiding Scythians from the north. At about this time, the Indo-European Medes began to migrate down into Iran from just east of the Caspian and by the ninth century B.C. they started toward Assyria, Babylonia and Elam, as the latter still controlled southern Iran.

ASIA MINOR: ANATOLIA

The Hittite Empire slowly crumbled, pushed from the southeast by the Assyrians and from the west by the Phrygians, newly arrived from Thrace. The last Hittite capital at Carchemish fell to the Assyrians in 717 B.C. But meanwhile the Phrygians with their most famous king, Midas, with a capital city of Gordium (near modern Ankara), contended with Assyria and Egypt for master of the Near East. They worshipped the goddess Cybele and the young god Atys, who like Adoni, annually died and was resurrected, in the inevitable pattern of the mid-east. At the close of the 8th century B.C., bands of Cimmerian horsemen from the steppe of southern Russia raided far and wide in Asia Minor, eventually destroying the Phrygian nation. The Lydians, living between the Cayster and the Hermus rivers were able to repel the invaders and soon took over the entire area. (Ref. 18)

In Urartu in the east, the Hurrian (Vannic) nation recovered from earlier waves of Assyrian attacks and about 800 B.C. became a very powerful nation known as the Urartian Kingdom with Mount Ararat as its center. Recent excavations near Altinepe, Turkey, have revealed architecture and art that have left heritages in later public buildings in Persia and metallurgy that perhaps had influence as far away as the Etruscan civilization of Italy. (Ref. 19) They demonstrated great engineering skill in irrigation works. Prosperous under a succession of kings from Sarduri I (840 B.C.) to Rusa I (714 B.C.), Urartu attained its greatest geographical extent in the reign of Sarduri II (764-735 B.C.), with territory from the Black Sea to the Mediterranean. The "Golden Age" may have occurred under Argistis II (708 B.C.) when the country grew rich by mining iron and selling it to Asia and Greece. Some authorities feel that this was the century when the Armenians, who eventually gave their name to this area, migrated across the Euphrates and intermarried with the indigenous Vans and Hurrians. Ozguc (Ref. 20), however, dates that migration to the next, 7th century B.C. At the end of this period, the Hurrian nation was weakened by combined Assyrian pressure and invasion of migrating Cimmerian hordes from east of the Black Sea. (Ref. 21)

1 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

2 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

3 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

4 [83] HALLETT Robin, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

5 [315] HAMBLIN, DORA JANE, "Treasures of the Sands", Smithsonian, Sept. 1983, pp. 43-53.

6 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

7 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

8 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

9 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

10 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

11 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

12 [18] BRITISH MUSEUM, (Personal notes, 1978).

13 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

14 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

15 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

16 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

17 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

18 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

19 [161] OZGUC, TAHSIN, "Ancient Ararat", Scientific American, Mar. 1967, page 44.

20 [161] OZGUC, TAHSIN, "Ancient Ararat", Scientific American, Mar. 1967, page 44.

21 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

1.  Biblical reference II Kings XV, 29 on 134

2.  Durant (Ref. 11), page 319

The Near East: 700 to 601 B.C.

THE NEAR EAST

THE ARABIAN PENINSULA

Northern Arabia and the region of present day Jordan were completely under the control of the Assyrians, but independent civilizations continued in the south, with regular camel caravans traveling to Egypt and to other parts of north Africa. As noted above, Yemen was actually overpopulated and many families migrated to Ethiopia. (Ref. 1)1

 1 The rich, well watered area of Yemen, which was then called "Arabia Felix", produced a distinctive Arabic script about 700 B.C.

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON

For a short time the Assyrians controlled the entire eastern Mediterranean shore, but after losing thousands of men with a disease (see Iraq), they retreated to the region of Syria. In Palestine Josiah became king in 639 B.C. and launched a campaign to purify the religion of Yahweh and to repress all traces of other cults. The Pentateuch, a code of laws designed to re-invigorate the moral life of the nation, was started in 621 B.C. This code supported the prophets by embodying the less extreme of their ideas. To facilitate the acceptance of this, according to Durant (Ref. 2), the elders, with Josiah's permission, conveniently "found" a scroll allegedly from Moses himself. This was the Book of the Covenant which is probably part of the Biblical book of Exodus or Deuteronomy. It is interesting to note that the prophets Amos and Isaiah had never mentioned Moses.

At the end of the century Judea was overrun by the Egyptians, under Necho, as they started to attack the Assyrians. Only four years later, in 605 B.C., however, the Chaldeans of the second Babylonian Empire soundly defeated the Egyptians at Carchemish, Syria, and Judah then passed under Babylonian rule. (Ref. 3)

IRAQ AND SYRIA

The Assyrians, under King Sennacherib, sacked and destroyed Babylon in 689 B.C. and then proceeded under their General Esarhaddon to the borders of Egypt where, according to the Bible (Il Kings), a pestilence struck producing "an hundred four-score and five thousand" corpses, and the survivors retreated to Nineveh. Ashurbinipal became king in 669 B.C. and led Assyria to the climax of its wealth and prestige, destroying Elam in the process. In this reign, the governor of Ur was one Sin-balatsu-iqbi who decided to restore the ancient city, and much was accomplished even though later archeologists say that his brick work was the worst that they encountered in the many strata at Ur. (Ref. 4) King Ashurbanipal was also the first book collector of history, accumulating in this 7th century B.C. a library of 25,000 clay tablets, some of them already 3,000 or more years old, including some medical "books" of ancient Sumer and Akkadia, written in primitive ideographs. In many ways the Assyrians had an advanced civilization, producing, for example, many great engineering feats for that time. Their military might was in great part based on iron weapons, particularly the iron-capped battering ram. They had excellent roads and communications. King Sennacherib had constructed a 919 feet long stone aqueduct to carry a canal across a valley and then continued with a six mile long canal to bring water for his orchards and parks. Palaces had lavatories and bathrooms as modern as some even today in parts of Europe. (Ref. 5) In the end, however, the military activity consumed so much manpower that local production atrophied and all vitals had to be imported. The constant warfare had also killed off the strongest and bravest men, and the biological type was undermined. The captive peoples bred and became a disintegrating force from within. In 612 B.C. an army of Chaldean nomads (an Aramaic people) under General Napopollaser, with the help of some Scythians and Medes, defeated the Assyrians in a great battle at Nineveh and the latter disappeared from history. These Chaldeans founded the second Babylonian Empire which controlled Mesopotamia until well into the next century. It was their General Nebuchadrezzar who defeated the expanding Egyptians at Carchemish in 605, giving them access to all the old Assyrian lands in Syria and Palestine. By 600 B.C. Babylon was the greatest walled city that the world has ever known, and Nebuchadressar had built it.

In this same period, between about 630 and 610 B.C. still another people appeared in this area. These were the Indo-European Scythians who raided down through Syria, destroying and killing as they went. Their raids were for plunder only and no settlements were made. (Ref. 6, 7, 8)

NOTE: Insert Map from Reference 97. (7. THE EAST)

IRAN

In eastern Iran the Indo-European speaking Medes were growing in numbers and power in an independent kingdom. Their greatest king, Cyaxares, started his reign in 640 B.C. but he had his hands full fighting off the Assyrians in the west and the horse-riding Scythians who periodically descended on them from central Asia, often defeating them

ARMENIA

In the eastern part of the Anatolian peninsula, Urartu (or the Kingdom of Van), after being conquered by the Assyrians, made common cause for awhile with the Scythians and under Rusa II (685-645 B.C.) successfully raided for slaves along the Assyrian frontier as these slaves were the essential foundation of their economy. The kingdom continued to prosper under Sarduri III and briefly under Rusa III until 609 B.C. when the Scythians turned on them and sacked the imperial city on Lake Van, while the Medes crushed the Assyrians nearby. Thus the Kingdom of Urartu came to an end about 600 B.C. The true Armenians were probably a Phrygian tribe which gradually occupied the territory of Urartu perhaps not until after 612 B.C. They initially adopted the religion of the Persians and were under the kings of Media for a time. (Ref. 9, 10)

1 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

2 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

3 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

4 [238] WOOLLEY, Sir LEONARD, Excavations at Ur. (Barnes & Noble, Inc., New York and Ernest Benn Limited, London, 1955).

5 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

6 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

7 [238] WOOLLEY, Sir LEONARD, Excavations at Ur. (Barnes & Noble, Inc., New York and Ernest Benn Limited, London, 1955).

8 [15] BOOKS AND MEDICINE, (Editors), M.D. Medical News Magazine, Vol. 3, No. 8, Aug. 1959.

9 [160] OXENSTIERNA, Eric, "The Vikings", Scientific American, May 1967.

10 [18] BRITISH MUSEUM, (Personal notes, 1978).

The Near East: 600 to 501 B.C.

THE NEAR EAST

Three peoples of the Near East had absolute monarchies in this century - the Lydians, Medes and the Babylonians. Please see map this section, last chapter.

THE ARABIAN PENINSULA

Incense and myrrh (made from gum resin) were now fashionable as offerings to the gods, and they were produced in south Arabia and sent to the Mediterranean. The Sabeans of Yemen and Hadramaut took over dominance from the Mineans and promoted advanced engineering projects, including a large dam near Marib. Still later the Himyarites became paramount in the area. Northern Arabia was conquered by Darius, the Persian, at the close of the century.1

1C. This was the alleged retreat of Moses, where he met the Biblical Reuel at the well. (Ref. 1)

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS

ISREAL (JUDEA: PALESTINE)

As the century began, internal strife and decay seemed imminent in Palestine. The prophet Jeremiah, writing at about 600 B.C., deplored the status and wrote like an undercover agent of Babylonia, seeming to hope that the Babylonians would conquer the Jews. If so, his hopes were soon fulfilled and Nebuchadrezzar took thousands of Jews as captives, to Babylon. While there, the prophet Ezekial, like Isaiah and Jeremiah before him, made fierce denunciations of idolatry and corruption of Jerusalem, but at the same time tried to keep the Jews from being absorbed by their captors. Even in bondage they stayed more or less intact, and they prospered and multiplied. But they did take over many Babylonian legends, which appeared later in the Old Testament, intermingled and fused with the true Hebrew stories. (See also Syria).

The Jews were finally liberated from Babylon by Cyrus, the Persian, in 540-538 B.C. and they migrated back to their homeland. The prophet, the "2nd Isaiah" (actual author unknown), whose writings may actually be a mixture from several men, began to lift the Judaic religion to a lofty state, re-emphasizing the coming of God and the Messiah. The Jewish Temple was rebuilt in Jerusalem. (Ref. 2)

LEBANON: PHOENICIA

Phoenicia was ruled from 586 to 538 B.C. by the Chaldean Nebuchadrezzar although the city of Tyre did not fall until 573 B.C. after a thirteen year siege. Later the country was divided into four vassal kindgoms, under the Persians. Extensive sea activity continued, however, and it is possible that a Phoenician ship circumnavigated Africa about this time. (See Israel). (Ref. 3)

IRAQ AND SYRIA

Seeming to foretell the future importance of Iraq as a source of petroleum, even in this 6th century B.C. oil was found on the surface in various parts of the country and was called naphtha. Bitumen was used to calk ships. (Ref. 4) An independent Babylonia prospered under the reign of Nebuchadrezzar II, the Chaldean, and Babylon became a famed metropolis, known particularly because of its famed hanging gardens. Ass-drawn wheeled carts, oar driven river boats and camel caravans all brought a mixture of food, precious metals, dyes, glassware and textiles to the city. The traffic also brought an occasional plague. (Ref. 5) This second Babylonian Empire was essentially a Semitic civilization. After an initial attack on Judea, Nebuchadrezzar carried about 10,000 Jews back to the capital, but later almost all the population of Jerusalem was brought in bondage to Babylon, with the captivity period running from 586 to 538 B.C. Nebuchadrezzar supposedly built the ziggurat of Etemananki, thought to be the infamous Tower of Babel, which has since been destroyed. The base of this tower measured 300 feet on a side. Near the end of his life he also tried to reconstruct the entire city of Ur, making the reconstructed ziggurat a seven-stage one. Even these ancients did not escape periods of severe inflation, and the wars and building activities of Nebuchadrezzar resulted in a 50% rise in prices between about 560 and 550 B.C. (Ref. 6) After the famous king's death, the empire crumbled rapidly, hastened by the aberration of the priests of Marduk, and subsequently the Achaemenid Persians had no trouble taking control of the area. The contributions of Babylonia to posterity include the legends, carried through the captive Jews, that became a part of Europe's religious lore, foundations of mathematics, astronomy, medicine, grammar, lexicography archeology, history and philosophy, as well as the design for the ziggurats, leading later to the Moslem towers. The Persian Cyrus became king of Babylon in 539 B.C. and the city lost its importance for evermore, as the ruler lived in Persia. Cyrus did complete some reconstruction work in Ur, however, restoring a gate in the great wall and probably working on one of the temples. This was done in spite of the fact that there was then little trade to this city. (Ref. 7, 8, 9)

IRAN: PERSIA

As Assyria fell, Cyaxares, king of the Medes, extended his rule on west across Iran, but in 550 B.C., Cyrus, prince of Persia, rebelled against the Medes and defeated their then king, Astyages, joining the two peoples together to make Iran a dominant south- west Asian power. They had iron technology and were able to exploit the horse for communication and warfare. The word "Iran" in Persian is the same as the word "Aryan" in English. Cyrus proceeded to capture Babylonia and almost all of Syria and Sardis, in Asia Minor. This Persian Empire became one of the best governed in history. It soon reached the natural limits in size and extent which were set by the condition of the soil and climate restricting peasant agriculture, abutting on the steppe in the north, the desert in the south and limited on the Aegean only by their long supply line as they came up against the Greeks. (Ref. 10) Cyrus' son, Cambyses, extended the empire into Egypt and then went mad and committed suicide. Darius 1, of the junior Achaemenid line, became king in 521, then conquered the sick Scythians in Russia and carried the Persian Empire to the Indus River in Pakistan. The official religion of the Achaemenid Dynasty was Zorastrianism but in the western areas Judaism co-existed as a competing faith, and in some areas this resulted in a complex fusion of both religious themes. Toynbee (Ref. 11) considers this empire the beginning of the "Universal State" of the old Syriac Society, but one must realize that the Syriac state was Semitic and the Persian conquest ended the Semitic rule in western Asia for a thousand years. (Ref. 12, 13)

We should mention that still another Iranian tribe, the Parthians, existed at this time around the southern shore of the Caspian Sea. In this century they fell under the control of the Medes and then the Persians, but as we shall see they will be heard from again in the future.

ASIA MINOR

TURKEY

Although Greek lonian cities continued to prosper along the coast, the country of Lydia expanded to occupy almost all the remainder of the peninsula. The fabulous wealth of these people and their famous King Croesus (570-546 B.C.) was based on a natural alloy of gold and silver called "electum", and coins were invented to act as a standard measure of this substance. Between these Lydians and the Medes, the Phrygian and Cimmerian peoples of Asia Minor were absorbed, although a fragment of the latter people survived in the Crimea as the "Tauri". By mid-century, just after Croesus had subdued lonia, on the coast, even Lydia was engulfed by Persia and disappeared as a nation. (Ref. 14, 15)2

2C. Ephesus, on the coast of Turkey, was a world-class lonian city, but thereafter silt began to fill up the harbor and it deteriorated. Now the Aegean is 11 kilometers away. A similar fate overtook Troy. (Ref. 16)

ARMENIA

The Medes drove the Scythians out of Armenia by 590 B.C. and the newly arrived Armenians of probably Phrygian origin continued to live there as a vigorous race. Although technically under the dominion of the Persian Empire in the last half of the century, they remained essentially independent in action because of their remoteness from the Persian center of government. The Armenians retained the Anatolic or Hittite nose.

1 [315] HAMBLIN, Dora Jane, "Treasures of the Sands", Smithsonian, Sept. 1983, pp. 43-53.

2 [45] DANIEL, Glyn (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

3 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

4 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

5 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

6 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

7 [238] WOOLLEY, Sir LEONARD, Excavations at Ur. (Barnes & Noble, Inc., New York and Ernest Benn Limited, London, 1955).

8 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

9 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

10 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

11 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

12 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

13 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

14 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

15 [136] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

16 [281] Gore, Rick, "The Mediterranean: Sea of Man's Fate", National Geographic 162: 694-737, Dec. 1982.

The Near East: 500 to 401 B.C.

THE NEAR EAST (THE 1ST GREAT CENTER OF CIVILIZATION)

ARABIA AND JORDAN

Between the Gulf of Aqaba and the Dead Sea on the trade route between south Arabia and Syria the Nabataean Kingdom developed with a capital at Petra. Because of its location it was influenced by the Aramaic (Syrian) civilization and still later by the Greeks. The Nabataeans migrated up from the south to settle in this cliff area, levying tolls on all caravan goods passing through. Petra had a theatre, thermal baths, palaces and a system of canals for water. This once thriving city, about ninety miles southwest of present day Amman, Jordan, was buried for centuries and only recently excavated by the Swiss Burckhardt. Qataban and Hadramaut were two new kingdoms which appeared on the south coast of Arabia. (Ref. 1, 2)

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON

Many Phoenician ports which were constructed at this period of low sea levels are today below the water line. Both Phoenicia and Judea remained under Persian rule, but their separate reactions differed. While Phoenicia faded away as a country, living in the future only in its colony of Carthage, the Jews strove to keep their national identity.

The priest, Ezra, called the Jews together and they read and adopted the Book of the Law of Moses, which was probably the first five books of the Bible, the "Torah' or the "Pentateuch". Those stories were drawn from a storehouse of Mesopotamian legend as old as 3,000 including the legends of Paradise, the Flood, etc. Nehemiah rebuilt the walls of Jerusalem (445 - 433 B.C.) and enforced the observance of the law. (Ref. 3, 4)

IRAQ AND SYRIA

This entire area was a part of the Persian Empire, but there was a revival of Damascus as a cultural center. At the end of the century Darius II died (405 B.C.) and his son Artaxerxes II became emperor while a brother, Cyrus the younger, became Iranian viceroy in the west. The latter recruited a force of ten thousand Greek mercenaries and marched them across Asia Minor into Syria and Mesopotamia to revolt against his brother. in a great battle at Cunaxa in 401 the Greek troops defeated the Persians, but Cyrus was killed and the mercenaries retreated with some difficulties back to the shore of the Black Sea and then home. The Greek's victory, however, gave them renewed confidence and helped set the stage for Alexander 's later Asiatic invasions. At that time many Jews still lived in Babylonia and some in the Persian controlled city of Ur.

NOTE: Insert Map from Reference 97. 24. THE RETREAT OF THE TEN THOUSAND

401-399 B.C.

IRAN: PERSIA

As the century opened Darius I was continuing his conquests into-a part of northern Greece, being finally stopped at the famous battle of Marathon. The Persian Empire now included thirty satrapies (provinces) each ruled by a satrap appointed by the king. In each, also, was a general and a financial officer responsible only to the king. These territories included Egypt, Palestine, Syria, Phoenicia, Lydia, Phrygia, Ionia, Cappadocia, Cilicia, Armenia, Assyria, the Caucasus, Babylonia, Media, Persia proper, Afghanistan, Baluchistan, India west of the Indus, Bactria and other regions of several central Asiatic tribes. The official language was Old Persian, closely related to Sanscrit, and written in cuneiform. The more generally used lingua franca of the empire, however, was Aramaic, written in alphabetic form. The Persian conquests were made possible by mounted bowmen and Bactrian camels. The latter made the long lances of the Scythians and other enemy tribes ineffective. (Ref. 5, 6)

That Darius was a true "Grand Monarch" is evident from the story that a thousand animals were slaughtered each day for the royal table in Persopolis1. Upon the death of Darius in 485 B.C. his son, Xerxes I, inherited the great empire. He was a sensual man and with him the "mob of nations", contaminated with drunkenness and immorality, began to fall apart. Xerxes dispersed the Babylonian priesthood and destroyed their temple of Marduk, but when he made another attempt to take the remainder of Greece his troops were turned back at Thermophylae and his fleet was defeated at the naval battle of Salamis2. Still lesser kings followed - Artaxerxes I and Darius II, etc. The later Achaemenid kings demonstrated great brutality, in spite of their Zorastrian religion.

The metal workers of the Achaemenid dynasty period have left numerous small objects of art made of gold and silver. The use of animal shapes was common and the lion, symbolizing royalty and power, and the bull, symbolizing strength, vitality and loyalty being two of the more popular. Later Christian iconography used the same symbols for two of the evangelists - Mark being represented by the lion and the physician, Luke, by the bull. The Iranian artists had the ability to develop light reflection which is said to be a characteristic of the light on the landscape of the Iranian plateau itself. (Ref. 9)1

1 Once in Greece, however, he eventually had to withdraw because there was no way he could feed his entire army over the winter. He had exceeded the practical limit of imperial expansion.  In this and the next few centuries Iranian warriors bred a large, powerful horse capable of carrying a fully armored man and the horses, too, were protected by metal. Although this heavy cavalry was slower than that of the steppe, it was more or less arrow proof and capable of use with either bow or lance. To feed these great horses alfalfa was supplied by the local peasants as pay for the protection given by those "cataphracts". (Ref. 10)

ASIA MINOR

In the early century this entire area also was merely a part of the Persian Empire, but in the far eastern portion the Armenians retained some measure of autonomy. In 499 B.C. Ionian cities along the coast, led by Aristogoras, revolted against Persia. This so-called "Ionian Revolt" was helped by ships from Athens and Eretria and they succeeded in burning the old Lydian capital of Sardis. Within five years, however, the revolt was crushed, and it was mid-century before the Greeks could again control the coastal cities. (Ref. 11, 12)

1 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

2 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

3 [224] Van ANDEL, TJEERD, Tales of an Old Ocean. (The Portable Stanford, Stanford Alumni Assoc., Stanford, Calif. 1977).

4 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

5 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

6 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

7 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

8 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

9 [197] SOUTHGATE, m. THERESE, "Explanation of Cover - Rhyton with Kneeling Bull", Journal of the American Medical Association 239: vol. 1, page 4.

10 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

11 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

12 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

1.  Trager so quotes the historian Xenophon. (Ref. 7, page 15)

2.  Xerxes' army crossed the Hellespont by joining about 700 ships, anchoring them and tying the end ships to land, laying planks, brushwood and earth across them. (Ref. 8, page 193)

The Near East: 400 to 301 B.C.

THE NEAR EAST

ARABIA AND JORDAN AND MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS

Nomadic tribes roamed the deserts of Arabia and in the south there was the Himyarite civilization, as previously described. Otherwise this entire area shared a common fate under first the Persians and then Alexander.

IRAQ AND SYRIA

In this century Xenophon remarked on the size and succulence of the dates from the date trees of Mesopotamia. Palms had flourished there since 50,000 B.C. and the net- work of canals that were built were ideal for the palms which lined them, and they did not impinge on the grain growing land. An average date palm produces one hundred pounds of rich, sugary fruit each year for sixty years or more, and a very good tree may produce one-half as much again. Figs were also grown and eaten in these ancient days. (Ref. 1)

Iraq and Syria were completely dominated by the Persians until the excursions of Alexander late in the century. He destroyed the Persian army at Gaugamele on the upper Tigris in 331 B.C. and brought an end to the Persian Achaemenid rule. It is said that in the same year Alexander tried to rebuild the Tower of Babel, but the initial clearing of the land alone took 10,000 men some two months to complete, and he had to give up the task.

As others, the ancient city of Ur was dying and the final blow came at the end of the century as the Euphrates changed its course to run some ten miles to the east of this city and there was no more river traffic. (Ref. 2, 3, 4) More detail concerning Alexander's conquests will be given under the section on the UPPER BALKANS later in this chapter.

IRAN: PERSIA

As noted in the last chapter the state religion of Persia was Zorastrian monotheism and the ancient gods were out of favor. As the century opened the Persian Empire was deteriorating under a series of weak rulers. Finally Darius III, the last of the Achaemenids (338 - 330 B.C.) lost the empire to Alexander of Macedonia. We shall give more details a little later in this chapter, but a point not often emphasized is that every Persian grandee had bodyguards and troops of Greeks as mercenaries, and this meant that Alexander's chief opponents were of ten Greeks, and they may not have resisted too well ' After Alexander's death Persia was administered from Syria by General Seleucus, who soon became orientalized and founded the Seleucid Dynasty. (Ref. 5)

ASIA MINOR

As the Persian influence waned, Greek domination increased and the bulk of Asia Minor easily became part of Alexander's empire. In the east, but still west of Armenia, in the regions known as Pontus and Cappadocia, a Persian noble, Mithridates, independent of his cousins in Iran, carved out his own empire. The same occurred in Armenia at the end of the century when a Persian satrap made the country independent of the Seleucids (317 B.C.) and founded a dynasty that ruled for a century. In both of these satrapies, as well as in Bithynia, farther west, the basic population was still Phrygian. (Ref. 6)

1 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

4 [238] WOOLLEY, Sir LEONARD, Excavations at Ur. (Barnes & Noble, Inc., New York and Ernest Benn Limited, London, 1955).

5 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

6 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

The Near East: 300 to 201 B.C.

THE NEAR EAST

ARABIA AND JORDAN

In Yemen, Sheba absorbed Maan about 250 B.C. but otherwise there was no significant change from the previous century. (Ref. 1)

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON

This was a part of the Egyptian Ptolemaic Empire until the very end of the century, when it was taken by Antiochus III the Great, of Syria, for the Seleucid domains.

IRAQ AND SYRIA

As the center of the Seleucid Dynasty, this area maintained a Greek culture with an oriental twist. Through the use of records of the movements of the heavenly bodies kept from the 8th century B.C. the Babylonians discovered the periodicity of the eclipses and the mathematical coordinates defining the exact paths of the moon and the sun. The power of the Seleucids began to wane in this century and much of their empire fell away, although at the very end of the period King Antiochus III, called the Great, restored the Syrian fortunes by reconquering their far eastern realms and adding to the domain along the Mediterranean coast from Asia Minor down to the borders of Egypt. He established a library at Antioch and promoted literature. (Ref. 2)

IRAN: PERSIA

After Alexander's death the Parthians in the north had revolted against the Greek domination and had formed a separate kingdom under Arsaces1. These people and the

Persian tribes farther south, gradually eroded a good deal of the Seleucid power. The Parthian King Tiridates (247 - 212 B.C.) transferred his capital to Hecatompylos on the southeast corner of the Caspian Sea, to be on the caravan route from Seleucia to Bactria and at the same time he evacuated Seleucus II. At the end of the century, however, Antiochus III reconquered most of this territory temporarily for the Syrian Dynasty, reducing the Parthian Arsaces III Priapatius to vassalship. (Ref. 3, 4)

ASIA MINOR

Although most of Asia Minor was nominally under Greek control, divided between the Ptolemies and the Seleucids, several states maintained more or less independent kingdoms. In the south the small but fine and powerful kingdom of Pergamum had developed as a Grecian city under Seleucus but it broke free under Eumenes I as he allied with the Ptolemies in 262 B.C. Other non-Greek but Hellenized kingdoms were Bithynia, Cappadocia (Pontus), Armenia and Media Atropatine. Pontus and Bithynia invited some wild Celts, who had just devastated the Grecian peninsula, to come to Asia Minor and settle, hoping that they would act as a buffer between the northern states and the Seleucids. But these Celtic Galatians, once established in central Anatolia, terrorized the cities along the coast. The kings of Pergamum, however, with Ptolemaic help, stood off both the Galatians and the Selucids.

Pergamum had been founded by the eunuch, Philetairos, former treasurer of the Diadoch Lysimachos who had absconded with the treasury, gone over to the rival Seleucus and used this fortune to finagle a new state of his own. His army was madeup of hired mercenaries. Upon his death his nephew, Eumenes, defeated Antiochus and became the most powerful man in Anatolia. Using his inherited money he further built up his army, founded cities, pushed out his borders and paid high tribute to the wild Galatians to keep them at a distance. (Ref. 5) Eumenes' nephew and successor, Attalos1, actually defeated the Celtic Galatians and then set about establishing libraries, arts, museums, etc. with some of the great artistic treasures of mankind, and the capital city rivaled Alexandria as a center of learning. An example of the architecture is shown in the picture on the next page - a temple altar of Pergamum, now reassembled in an East Berlin Museum. The pharaoh of Egypt jealously forbade the export of the papyrus plant or its products, so Pergamum had to develop a writing material of its own from animal skin, subsequently called "pergamentum" or "parchment". With this they accumulated some 200,000 books1. Unfortunately this fabulous little nation lasted little more than a century. (Ref. 6, 7, 8)

In the far eastern part of the peninsula Armenia remained under its own dynasty until 211 B.C. when Antiochus III of Syria took control and divided the country into two satrapies.

1 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

2 [47] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part II - The Life of Greece. (1939).

3 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

4 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

5 [91] Herm, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

6 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

7 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, r. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

8 [15] BOOKS AND MEDICINE, (Editors), M.D. Medical News Magazine, Vol. 3, No. 8, Aug. 1959.

9 [15] BOOKS AND MEDICINE, (Editors), M.D. Medical News Magazine, Vol. 3, No. 8, Aug. 1959.

1.  Between 10 and 30 "books" of antiquity would comprise 1 book today, because either papyrus or parchment made a very thick roll. (Ref. 9)

The Near East: 200 to 101 B.C.

THE NEAR EAST

ARABIA AND JORDAN

Arabian dromedary caravan traffic was now the monopoly of the Nabataean Arabs who maintained a series of caravan stations. Upon the collapse of the Seleucids late in the century these Arabs then acquired Damascus itself. (Ref. 1)

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON

The Book of Daniel was written about 165 B.C. and the Book of Enoch perhaps slightly later. In the former year Judah Maccabee and his brothers, after taking Jerusalem back from the Syrians, restored the monotheistic religion. It was later said that they found only enough oil left in the temple to keep a light burning for one day, but somehow it lasted eight days and this is the event celebrated annually as the Hanukkah. By 143 B.C. Simon Maccabee had freed Judea entirely, beginning the Hasmonean Dynasty of priest kings which ruled Judea and some lands east of the Jordan until 104 B.C., after which Aristobulus I and his brother, Alexander Jannaeus, ruled savagely until well into the next century. (Ref. 2)

IRAQ AND SYRIA

Near the Mediterranean coast there was a thriving Hellenic culture centered on the large city of Antioch and the supporting cities of Laodicea and Apamia. The great Seleucid King Antiochus III invaded Greece in 192 B.C. but was soon pushed back by Roman armies and the Roman fleet. In 190 two of the Scipio brothers crossed the Hellespont and defeated Antiochus in the great battle of Magnesia, near Smyrna in Asia Minor. The result was that the Seleucids lost all European and Asiatic possessions as far as the Taurus Mountains and from then on the old Syrian Dynasty continued to decline. By the end of the century almost this entire area was taken over by the Parthians.

IRAN: PERSIA

Eastern Persia was ruled by the Parthian Arsacid Dynasty and they continued to develop a powerful empire, keeping the administrative structure of the preceding Seleucid government. In 141 B.C. Mithridates I of Parthia entered Seleucia, itself, on the Tigris River and for the next 775 years, with only a few minor set backs, Persia remained one of the richest and most powerful regions of the ancient world. (Ref. 3) Their military system was based on an Iranian nobility but they accorded the Hellenic cities full autonomy and did nothing to weaken the Hellenic stamp.

The western spread of the Parthians was the result, in part at least, of pressure on their northeastern frontier by migrating peoples from the Asian steppes. Some of these may have been a Mongolian people called "Hsiung-nu" by the Chinese, but probably the chief offenders were the Yue-chi, another Iranian tribe returning from a previous expansion into Asia proper. Their immediate descendants were called "Kushans" and they pushed their cousins the Shakas and Samartians ahead of them toward southern Russia and the Parthians down into Persia. (Ref. 4)

ASIA MINOR

TURKEY

Early in the century the Roman armies began to be active in Asia Minor, driving the invading Celts from the north back out of the peninsula, and defeating the Seleucid Antiochus, in the battle of Magnesia, thus inaugurating the Roman conquest of the Hellenic East.

Meanwhile in northeastern Asia Minor activity was rampant in the regions of Bithynia and Pontus. The people of both were mixtures of Thracians, Greeks and Iranians, overlying an antique Hittite stock. Mithridates VI, who now inherited the throne of Pontus, was a strong, educated man, speaking twenty-two languages and with the help of Greek officers and mercenaries he conquered Armenia and the Caucasus and entered the Crimea of southern Russia, controlling the Black Sea on all sides except the southwest. He then invaded Bithynia, arousing fears for the Bosporus Straits in the minds of the Roman military. So the latter ordered Mithridates out of Bithynia, setting the stage for actual war in the next century. The Galatians continued to oppose Pergamum, sometimes allying themselves with Bithynia, but they received a crushing defeat by Eumenes II in 166 B.C., and had great difficulty holding Pontus off their territory. When the Pergamum King Attalus died in 133 B.C. he left his kingdom to Rome. It was at this period that Hipparchus of Nicaea elaborated the scheme of spheres and epicycles that became the classical construction of the universe. (Ref. 5, 6)

NOTE: Insert Map: 26: ASIA MINOR IN 189 B.C

ARMENIA

We noted at the close of the last century that Armenia was conquered by Antiochus III and divided into two satrapies. The western one, Armenia Minor, was given to Zadriades and the eastern one, Armenia Major, to Artaxis. After Antiochus' defeat at Magnesia in 190 B.C. the two governors made themselves independent rulers, founding two separate dynasties. At the end of the century the area was temporarily overrun by Mithridates VI, the ambitious king of Pontus. (Ref. 7)

1 [136] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

2 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

3 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

4 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

5 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

6 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

7 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

The Near East: 100 B.C. to 0

THE NEAR EAST

ARABIA AND JORDAN

During the Hellenistic era the Himyarites of southern Arabia had lost their chief source of prosperity when part of the Indian trade was diverted through Egypt, but in 24 B.C., they were still strong enough to defeat the Roman General Gallus, who had been sent to conquer them and the invaders were driven into the desert where many died from heat and thirst. The Nabataean kingdom, in present day southern Jordan, became powerful at this time, with a capital at Petra. Amman, in northern Jordan, was first destroyed and conquered and then rebuilt by the Romans. (Ref. 1)

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON

By 78 B.C. in Judea the Hasmoneans had enlarged their realm so that their territory was as extensive as it had been under Solomon, but the rulers began to lose their religiosity and yielded to Hellenizing elements. Toynbee (Ref. 2) says that the Jews' Canaanite culture was not a backward one and was probably equal to the Hellenic in achievement, but it was different in ethos and the Hellenic was the more potent and soon dominated.

In 63 B.C., however, Judea was conquered by Pompey for Rome. As he laid siege to Jerusalem, the Jewish King Aristobulus took refuge in the walled precincts of the Temple and held out for three months. When the ramparts finally fell 12,000 Jews were slaughtered, with some leaping to death from the walls. None surrendered. Pompey left the Temple untouched but exacted 10,000 talents ($3,600,000) from the nation and transferred all Hasmonean cities to the Roman power. Hyrcanus II was made high priest and nominal ruler of Judea, but as the ward of Anatipater the Idumean, who had helped Rome. The independent monarchy was ended and Judea became part of the Roman province of Syria. Herod the Great became subject king in 37 B.C. and using Roman funds, financed a local army to drive the invading Parthians back out of this territory. Herod was also an Idumean and not a Jew either by origin or conviction1. (Ref. 3) He, like other rulers of his time, had loose morals, ten wives, nine at one time, meted out cruel punishments and had an Hellenic leaning. The Pharisees2 were against Herod and by the time he died in 4 B.C. he was hated by all the people. His realm was divided among his three sons. On our present calendar Jesus appears to have been born between 7 and 4 B.C. (Ref. 4)

There were about 2,500,000 people in Palestine in this era and most of them spoke Aramic, although the priests and scholars knew Hebrew and the officials and foreigners used Greek. There was constant strife between the Jews in the interior of Palestine and Gentiles on the coast, and there was strife within the Great Council of the Elders of Israel who ruled over the people for religious offenses. The higher priests and Sadducees were a conservative element holding for the written law of the Hebrews (Torah) and the Pharisees and Scribes3 were a liberal element voting to accept oral traditions as well as the Torah. The Psalms of Solomon and the Book of Joshua (Ecclesiasticus) were written in this century, although the latter is not accepted by the Jews. (Ref. 6)

IRAQ AND SYRIA

During this century Syria and Iraq became primarily a battle ground between the two formidable forces of the Romans in the west and the Parthians in the east. Although Antiochus VIII and IX and Seleucus VI each reigned briefly, in 83 B.C. the shrunken Seleucid Kingdom was taken over by Armenia and twenty years later it became a Roman province. (Ref. 7) (Please see map in the ITALY section, this chapter). At the ancient Mesopotamian city of Carrhae, just north of the upper Euphrates, the Roman General Crassus met the Parthians and was defeated and killed by the Shaka bowmen of the Parthians' Suren ally. (Ref. 8, 9)

IRAN (PERSIA)

The Parthians were in control of Iran and were pretty well able to contain the Romans in Syria on their western flank, but they were now having additional troubles on their northern and eastern borders. In 88 B.C. Tigranes II of Armenia invaded Parthia, overrunning four vassal states, reducing the size of Parthian controlled territory. (Ref. 10) In addition the Yue-chi and the neighboring Iranian Shaka had already taken Bactria and were starting to move into the Middle East, attacking eastern Iran. To hold off these attacks the Parthians used very large, heavily armored horses and men in cavalry units called "cataphracts", against the invaders' light, nomad, bow cavalry.

ASIA MINOR: ANATOLIA

TURKEY

We noted in the last chapter that King Mithridates IV of Pontus had launched an imperialistic campaign which had brought him into contact with the displeased Romans.

The First Mithridatic War broke out in 88 B.C. and Mithridates surged out of Asia Minor to take the Cyclades, Thessaly, Macedonia and Thrace before he was stopped down in Greece, proper, by the Roman Sulla. The king was given a lenient peace and returned to Pontus to raise another army and fleet. The Roman legate in Asia, Murena, realizing that the king was rearming, attacked Pontus in the Second Mithridatic War between 83 and 81 B.C., but was defeated. The Romans returned to the attack in the Third Mithridatic War of 75 to 63 B.C. and this time all Asia Minor became Roman. Wells (Ref. 11) states that

100,000 Roman Italians were massacred during this war. The Roman conquest was complete when King Nicomedes III gave his country of Bithynia to Rome in 75 B.C. About 350 miles south of present day Ankara was the small country of Commagene, ruled by Ceniochus I, who claimed descent from both Greek and Persian kings. He had colossal statues made, including one of himself, and some of these thirty foot high constructions have survived earthquakes, storms and wars, remaining erect at the present time. (Ref. 12, 13)

ARMENIA

Tigranes the Great, actually a son-in-law of Mithridates, united Armenia once again in 95 B.C. and added territory from Syria and Cappadocia, making Armenia the most powerful nation in western Asia. By 70 B.C. his empire extended from the Ararat Valley to the Phoenician city of Tyre on the Mediterranean coast, much of this territory having been taken from the Parthians. By 66 B.C., however, Tigranes had fallen into the hands of Pompey as the latter was driving Mithridates of Pontus to the eastern edge of the Black Sea. Thereafter the Armenian king ruled merely as a vassal of Rome. (Ref. 14) By the end of the century when emissaries of the Han Dynasty of China reached the eastern shores of the Caspian Sea, they found only stories of a civilization that had receded. The memory of Alexander remained, but of Rome men knew only that Pompey had come to the western shore of the Caspian and then gone away and that Crassus had been destroyed.

1 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

2 [221] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., Change and Habit. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1966).

3 [48] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

4 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

5 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

6 [48] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

7 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

8 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

9 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

10 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

11 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

12 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

13 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

14 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

1.  Trager (Ref. 5) claims that on the contrary Herod converted to Judaism in his youth and at the time of his death was rebuilding the great Temple at Jerusalem. He does not give the source of this information

2.  The Pharisees were a group of Jewish Elders

3.  The Scribes were scholars of the Law

The Near East: 0 to A.D. 100

THE NEAR EAST

ARABIA AND JORDAN

As direct voyages across the full width of the Arabian Sea had become routine, trade across the peninsula increased, linking Alexandria with India. The Himyarite Arabs absorbed Oataban about A.D. 50 and the Hadramaut about A.D. 100, while farther north the Nabatean Empire was conquered by Rome. Across the gulf from Ethiopia the Kingdom of Axum developed as a part of its Ethiopian counterpart, but on Arabic soil. At the end of the century Christianity gradually filtered into the peninsula. (Ref. 1)

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON

Rome formally annexed Palestine in A.D. 6 and in A.D. 44 Judea was finally placed under direct rule of Roman procurators. The early century is the period of Jesus' teaching of universal love and forgiveness, but in general the Jews were not won over. The first of the Romano-Jewish Wars occurred in the last third of the century (A.D. 66) when the Jews, under John of Giscala, revolted against Roman misrule. It ended in a great battle (A.D. 70) with 600,000 to 1,000,000 Jews killed, their temple destroyed and the survivors forced to undergo another "dispersion". When the new Christians had failed to support this Jewish uprising, anti-Christian riots also broke out. After the Roman victory, the Sadducees disappeared entirely and the Pharisees, previously a sort of priest-elder group, now became the Rabbis, or teachers of the people. Overall at that time there were in the Roman population Jews in the ratio of 7%, a number twice that of the Jews in the United States in the Mid-twentieth century. (Ref. 2, 3)

IRAQ AND SYRlA

This century was one of relative stability along the frontier dividing the Parthian and Roman Empires. Syria (although perhaps it was Egypt) was probably the site of the invention of a technique of glass blowing so that soon glass utensils were in general use all over the Mediterranean. Christianity came to Malula in the mountains just north of Damascus and still today some 1,500 Christians live there, speaking Western Aramic, the language of Jesus. Adjacent caves may have been used in this first century as places of refuge. (Ref. 4, 5)

IRAN: PERSIA

Persia was the hub of the Parthian Empire. The people spoke Pahlavi and wrote in Aramic on parchment, but unfortunately not a line of the Parthian literature has been preserved. They were either too rich or too poor to indulge in literature, but they did excel in self-adornment, with both sexes curling their hair and enjoying elaborate clothing. They hunted, ate and drank abundantly, were brave warriors and usually honorable foes. Polygamy was practiced and women were veiled and secluded, with divorce easy for either sex. They were perhaps less civilized than the Achaemenid Persians but more honorable gentlemen than the Romans. They were tolerant of religions while they worshipped the sun and the moon and preferred the God Mithras to Ahura Mazda, much as later Christians preferred Christ to Yahveh. The Arsacid Dynasty ruled from just before the beginning of this century for two hundred years. (Ref. 6)

ASIA MINOR

Most of Asia Minor was firmly under Roman rule with Commagene falling to them by A.D. 17. Armenia was divided and actually was another frontier between the Romans and the Parthians while the cultural orientation of that country was definitely toward Persia and Parthia. In the middle of the century, in Nero's reign in Rome, his legions had a ten year war with Parthia over Armenia. This ended in A.D. 63 with a scion of the Parthian royal house recognized as king of Armenia, although under Roman suzerainty. Seven years later Vespasian moved some eastern troops from Syria to forts on the upper Euphrates to consolidate the eastern frontier against Armenia and Parthia, thus paving the way for later expansion by Trajan. (Ref. 7, 8)

1 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

4 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

5 [118] Fay, Howard, "Syria", National Geographic 157: 485-511, Apr. 1980.

6 [48] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

7 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

8 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

The Near East: A.D. 101 to 200

THE NEAR EAST

The increasing land and sea trade between the Mediterranean, India and China increased chances of unfamiliar infections spreading to susceptible populations and severe epidemics are known to have hit the Mediterranean populations and probably China too in this century. (Ref. 1)

ARABIA AND JORDAN

The trade routes across the Arabian peninsula were very active at this time. The citizens of Palmyra owned and escorted caravans between the Roman Empire (controlling Jordan and some of northern Arabia) and the Persian Gulf ports of Charax and Apologos, thus accumulating great wealth which permitted the financing of spectacular public buildings. Petra performed the same functions farther south between the Persian Gulf and the Red Sea ports. (Ref. 2)

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON

The industry and trade of Judea and the area of Lebanon were intimately connected with the whole of Syria and Iraq. Although the entire region remained under Roman control, the basic people of these lands remained Jewish and Phoenician in derivation, as always. The dye industry, inherited from old Phoenicia continued to function along with schools of medicine and law at Beirut. The upper classes were of Hellenic culture and the Greek language was used in literature and government, while the lower classes remained oriental and spoke Aramaic.

In A.D. 132 under the leadership of Simeon Bar Cocheba, who claimed to be the Messiah, the Jews made their last effort in antiguity to recover their freedom and their homeland. In the last of the Romano-Jewish Wars they fought desperately for three years against the Roman legions. One-half million men were killed and more starved. After the Jewish defeat, Hadrian forbade any Jewish ritual and the vanquished were shut out of their Holy City and scattered again.

In the next four centuries there were written two Talmuds, one from Jerusalem and a much longer Babylonian version containing a rich collection of medical lore among the other authoritative Jewish traditions. Some of the medical material came from Alexandria where Jews had flocked in the 4th century B.C. Although dead bodies were avoided as unclean, Rabbi Ishmael is said to have boiled and then studied the body of a prostitute. In surgery the Talmud discusses means of reducing dislocations and performing certain other operations. (Ref. 3, 4)

IRAQ AND SYRIA

At the beginning of this century there were ten million people living in Greater Syria, which probably encompassed modern Lebanon and Iraq, and there was great prosperity due to the dye and glass industries. Today there are only three million people living in the same area, most finding only a precarious existence. In A.D. 114 the Emperor Trajan exploited a moment of Parthian weakness and advanced down the Tigres and Euphrates rivers to the Persian Gulf, thus putting the rule of Rome over this entire ancient land. In the Hadrian Principate to follow, however, (A.D. 117 - 138), the Roman troops were withdrawn to the Euphrates which then became the eastern boundary of the empire. In the area between the Red and the Black Seas, a hundred cities flourished in this era of relative Roman peace. The political and military reverses of the Jews in Judea in no way affected the large number of them living in Babylonia and elsewhere in the empire. (Ref. 5)

IRAN

Emperor Trajan also invaded part of Iran and between A.D. 115 and 117 all of Media and part of Parthia, itself, belonged to Rome, but as noted in the paragraph above, Hadrian withdrew all troops to the Euphrates, freeing the main areas of Persia and the Parthian Empire remained pretty well intact. Late in the century Roman generals again attempted to invade this region (165 and 198) but with no lasting effect. (Ref. 6)

ASIA MINOR: ANATOLIA

TURKEY

Even under the years of Roman rule, the Ionian Greek culture still flourished along the coast of Asia Minor. Soranus of Ephesus wrote a treatise on diseases of women, birth and care of children (A.D. 116), a work which marks him as a great gynecologist. Only Hippocrates and Galen rank above him in the medicine of ancient times.

ARMENIA

Armenia was a site of almost constant warfare. Just before the beginning of this century that country and Parthia were allied, but when the Parthian King Chosroes set up a puppet governor in Armenia, Trajan declared war, claiming a treaty violation. In 114, on the death of the Parthian puppet, Trajan annexed the country. After his death, however, Hadrian withdrew the troops to a less advanced position and Armenia was again left alone until Marcus sent General Verus back to the area in 162. Verus cruised through Syria and up to Armenia, where he put a Roman puppet on the throne. The Armenians may gave gotten their revenge, however, because upon Verus' return to the West, his troops brought with them a terrible plague which seriously depopulated the empire in A.D. 166 and 167. (Ref. 7)

1 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [48] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

4 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

5 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

6 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

7 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

The Near East: A.D. 201 to 300

THE NEAR EAST

ARABIA AND JORDAN

Jordan belonged to the Romans, but most of Arabia was untouched by the Roman armies. In the south of the peninsula the cities began to decline and the nomads again assumed rule. By the end of the century the Aksumite kings of Ethiopia were in control of Yemen and the Sassanian King Shapur annexed Oman on the Arabian Gulf shore about A.D. 260. (Ref. 1

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON

Lebanon was a part of Roman controlled Syria and even Judea was non-existent as a separate Jewish state. The common people of most of these areas tended to remain unchanged, century after century, however, and basically only the governments shifted.

At the beginning of the century the Rabbi Judah codified Jewish law, both civil and religious, in a work called the "Mishnah" which became the basis of continuous study in the Middle East and was later preserved in the Talmud. (Ref. 2)

IRAQ AND SYRIA

As the century opened this entire area was dominated by Rome but in the old area of Mesopotamia in western Iraq the Persian King Ardashir invaded about A.D. 230, but shortly withdrew again. This was followed in A.D. 260 by Shapur I with clouds of cavalry that raided throughout all of Syria and returned to Persia laden with spoils and the

Roman Emperor Valerian. who was captured at Edessa, where Syria joins Asia Minor. It was only after this that Odenathus of the Septimii tribe, governor of Palmyra in Syria, crowned himself a puppet king under the Romans and promptly drove the Persians back across Mesopotamia, defeating them finally at Ctesiphon, the ancient Persian capital near present Baghdad. He then declared himself king not only of Syria but of Cilicia, Arabia, Cappadocia and Armenia. After his assassination in A.D. 266 his son took his title, but his widow, Zenobia, took his power. She beautified the capital and brought scholars and artists to her court, but also found time to lead an army into Asia Minor, conquering Cappadocia, Galatia and most of Bithynia. Then, with a great fleet and army she conquered Egypt. The Roman Emperor Domitius Aurelianus soon reconquered this land, however, and then his armies proceeded to beat Palmyra from a great central Syrian city of 30,000 people to a desert village as it had been before and remains yet today. (Ref. 3, 4)

IRAN

Persian cities sat on the silk route from China to the Roman Empire and regardless of the local administration and any hostilities, the Persians controlled this traffic. Rayy (near modern Tehran) as well as Herat (now over the border in Afghanistan) became major cities and enjoyed great prosperity. In about A.D. 224, Ardashir I, originally a feudal lord of Persia, overcame the weakened Parthian Arsacid Dynasty and became king of all the Persians, founding the Sassanian or Sassanid Dynasty. This family strongly identified with the old Achaemenian Empire and Zorastrianism was restored as the state religion. New conquests were undertaken as Ardashir invaded Syria although his main purpose was to dethrone and kill the Arsacid king who was ruling Armenia. Ardashir 's successor, Shapur I, (240-271) built a new city in his home province of Fars, the Sassanian "Versailes", and he also promoted agriculture and several irrigation systems. As mentioned above, however, he is most famous for his extensive cavalry raids throughout Syria and his capture of the Roman Emperor Valerian at Edessa. Thousands were killed in Antioch and Tarsus was about destroyed. Victory may have resulted as the result of the Persian cavalry's use of damask steel sabres, superior to anything made in the West. (See SUBCONTINENT OF INDIA, this chapter). Shapur eventually went down to defeat at the hands of Odenathus, an Arab prince from Palmyra, whose troops chased the Persians back and defeated them at Ctesiphon, as we have noted. (Ref. 5, 6)

In A.D. 242 Mani began his religious teachings, taking Zorasterism as a base but accepting Moses, Jesus and Buddha as prophets. He traveled to Turkistan, India and China and his ideas spread widely, becoming a fruitful root-stock of Christian heresies for almost a thousand years. (Ref. 7) At first Shapur favored Mani, but later he was banished and when Shapur's second son, Varahran I became king in 272 Mani was executed. (Ref. 8)

ASIA MINOR: ANATOLIA

TURKEY

The entire Anatolian peninsula was part of the Roman Empire, but this was an era of multiple raids from both north and south, with the Goths and other Russian tribes coming down to ravage the cities of the Black Sea such as Pontus, Chalcedon, Nicomedia, etc., while the Persians later overran Cilicia and Cappadocia. It was in Edessa, then part of Syria, but near the modern city of Urfa, Turkey that the Persian king Shapur captured Valerian. This was somewhat nullified as the Queen Mother Zenobia temporarily took over additional territory in this region. By the end of the century Roman rule had been pretty well restored and the Emperor Diocletian established his capital for the entire empire at Nicomedia. Greek was written and spoken in this eastern Roman capital except for purely administrative and occasional literary purposes. The great plague which reached most of the empire in the middle of the century struck Pontus particularly violently. (Ref. 9, 10, 11)

ARMENIA

The puppet king, Chosroes, was of the Iranian Arsacid line, and as noted above, he was murdered by the Persian Ardashir I and Armenia came under the Persian wing. In A.D. 284, after Queen Zenobia had finally been defeated, Emperor Diocletian helped Tiridates, the son of Chosroes, to again ascend the throne of this country.

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [48] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

4 [136] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

5 [48] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

6 [18] BRITISH MUSEUM, (Personal notes, 1978).

7 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

8 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

9 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

10 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

11 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

The Near East: A.D. 301 to 400

THE NEAR EAST

ARABIA AND JORDAN

The Abyssinians had conquered the southern angle of the peninsula by 362 and there were still some fairly prosperous towns along the Red Sea. In the north there was an increasing level of civilization with more and more contact with Syria, while in the desert the nomad tribes gradually encroached on the towns. (Ref. 1)

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON & IRAQ AND SYRIA

The eastern portion of Syria, comprising essentially present day Iraq and ancient Mesopotamia was under the domination and actually a part of the new Persian Empire. The western part of Syria, including the areas of Lebanon and Judea, were part of Byzantium, the eastern realm of the fading Roman Empire. Monophysite Christianity, which began a period of extreme ascetism among many monks of the East, became widely accepted in Syria and particularly in the Lebanon region. Judging from the irrigation systems, the population of Mesopotamia may well have reached its peak at this time, while epidemics and other problems were cutting the Italian Roman population (Ref. 2) The Bible and various theological works were translated into Syriac and then a copious original literature was developed. In central Syria, since the cities of Palmyra and Hatra had been destroyed in the previous century, the silk route now went farther north from Antioch on the coast through northern Syria to Seleucia, an ancient city now gone, which was located near present day Baghdad. (Ref. 3, 4)

IRAN: PERSIA

In the first decade of this century Persia was invaded by Arabs from Mesopotamia and Bahrain and Ctesiphon was sacked. At 17 years of age Shapur Il became emperor and he immediately invaded Arabia and exacted a terrible revenge upon the Arabs. Then between 337 and 376 he engaged in three wars with Rome, with neither side gaining any great advantage. When Shapur II died in 379 the Persian Empire was at its peak, controlling all territory that Darius I had ruled a thousand years before. Zorastrianism, tied up with the political destiny of the empire, was winning against both Judaism and Hellenization.

Iranian society in this Sassanian period consisted essentially of three classes:

WARRIORS. The land owners, great and small, furnished the heavy cavalry and the mounted archers who were the effective strength of the army. The infantry consisted of their vassals and serfs. At the top of this class were seven great families dating back to the Achaemenid times and holding hereditary rights to various offices. The king was a member of one of these great families and the internal history of Iran continued to be one of nobles jockeying for power.
PRIESTS: MAGI. The Avesta, written sometime during Sassanian domination, ordered every aspect of life in Persia. The Magi had great authority, including some judicial function. They owned large estates and had considerable political influence when Mazdaism finally became the dominant religion in the next century.
PEASANTS AND CRAFTSMEN. This was the most numerous group but it had no power and no chance to rise in rank. The great majority were peasants, almost at the level of serfdom.

In the ruling class there was much family intermarriage, father-daughter and brother- sister marriages being common. After Shapur II, there began a decline in royal power and many dynastic disputes, raging over 1 1/2 centuries. In addition there were frequent wars with the Byzantine branch of the remains of the Roman Empire and in 395 large hordes of Huns crossed the Don, then the Caucasus and entered Persia, driven perhaps by famine. They took thousands of prisoners for later sale as slaves and drove off many herds of cattle. One group crossed the Euphrates and were beaten back by Romans, another retreated from Ctesiphon as the Persian army approached and a third group ravaged Asia Minor and Syria. (Ref. 5, 6, 7)

ASIA MINOR: ANATOLIA

In this and the next century it is of value to the reader to study the sections on ASIA MINOR, THE BALKANS, AUSTRIA, HUNGARY AND ITALY all together, as the interactions between these areas is almost continuous.

Our paragraph about Byzantium in the last chapter closed with the ascension of Diocletian to the throne of the eastern portion of the Roman Empire, as he gave Maximian control of the western portion. Both of these men abdicated in A.D. 305. The Roman political and military scenes become very complicated from this point on, with the two halves of the empire ruled sometimes by one man, but at other times two or four shared the power as co-emperors, west and east. The designation of various generals as Caesars and prefectures does not help in the clarification. We shall try to give only the salient points, and avoid getting bogged down in minute details. Constantius and Galerius succeeded Diocletian and Maximian, but Constantius died a year later and his son, Constantine, was proclaimed emperor by his troops, while just shortly thereafter Maxentius, son of Maximian, seized power in Italy. Constantine overthrew Maxentius just outside Rome in 312, making himself master of the West and eleven years later he took over the East, also. Thus, by 323 he had become the sole emperor and his inauguration was given in Constantinople in 330 after he had spent four years constructing it on the site of ancient Byzantium. Known subsequently as Constantine the Great this man in the meantime waged war all across southern Europe, in Greece and the East and since many of his soldiers were already Christians, he used their crosses as his battle ensignia. Finally he became an avowed Christian although he attended no rituals and it is possible that his conversion was more of a political maneuver than a spiritual one. Its effects were nevertheless far reaching and promoted the spread and organization of the Church throughout the Roman domain. (Ref. 8, 9, 10, 11)

Constantine gave the Church vast estates and buildings, empowered bishops to make slaves of Roman citizens and permitted civil suits to be transferred to bishops' courts if either party so desired. (Ref. 12)

Besides being constantly at war with Persia under Shapur II, Constantine I had to put up with bitter battles which developed over creeds in his newly recognized Christian hierarchy. He attempted to resolve these differences by calling a council of Nicaea which proceeded to establish the orthodox creed that in essence said that the Lord Jesus Christ, the Son of God, begotten not made, being of one essence with the Father, was made flesh for the salvation of men. Of some 318 bishops present, only two plus the unrepentant Arius, refused to sign the formula. These were exiled and an imperial edict ordered that all books by Arius should be burned. All Christians were agreed that pagan temples must be closed but Arianism remained in Asia Minor and throughout the Near East and "paganism" in the form of Mithraism, Neoplatonism, Stoicism and Cynicism was widespread. Constantine also had serious financial troubles so that he had to confiscate properties of cities and temples and finally impoverished the middle class and the peasants by tremendous taxation and land transfers. By A.D. 350, some years after his death, there were 80,000 people getting free bread in Constantinople. (Ref. 13)

After a few murders of other claimants to the throne, Constantine's son, Constantius II, became emperor in 337 but he ruled for only nine years and accomplished nothing except to choose as Caesar (a top general) the half-brother of Gallus, Flavius Claudius lulianus, soon to be known as Julian. He was given command against the Alamanni and the Franks, but after five years he apparently sought greater things and marched against Constantius. The latter died before Julian reached him so he became emperor in 361 without further difficulty. Known as Julianus, the Apostate, he reversed the trend to Christianity, upholding paganism while attempting to make Mithraism the supreme religion. He was a learned man who devoted much time to books and the study of philosophies, while allowing full freedom to Christians. At his death in 364 while fighting with his armies in Persia, Hellenism and its philosophies disappeared for 11 centuries. After some further juggling of east and west emperors elected by their troops, Valentinianus I became emperor in the west in 364 and he named his brother Valens as co-Augustus in the east. He had his hands full battling Visigoths who won independence north of the Danube. All of the emperors' most dangerous enemy, however, still remained the Sassanid Dynasty of Persia, and this squeezing effect with the Goths in the north and the Persians in the south resulted in Byzantium giving up part of Armenia and Georgia in the Causasus to Persia. Finally in 378 the Visigoths crossed the Danube 80,000 strong, engaged the eastern co-Augustus, Valens, in a great battle at Adrianople and the latter was killed. Gratianus appointed Theodosius, a strong Christian and son of a successful general in Britain, to succeed him as co-emperor of the East. He immediately banned the practice of all current religions except Christianity (although it was still in a minority at the time) and handed over all Christian churches to the Trinitarians (Athanasiasts), being greatly influenced by St. Ambrose of Milan. When Theodosius massacred 7,000 people at Thessalonica in Greece in revenge for an insurrection, however, Bishop Ambrose forced him to do penance, thereby emphasizing the independence of the western church from imperial domination. When the Frank Count Arobast murdered the western emperor, Valentinian II, and set up the pagan Eugenius as Roman Emperor in 392, Theodosius, with Gothic auxiliaries, led by Alaric, defeated and killed both Arbogast and Eugenius at Frigidus in northeastern Italy. Theodosius died soon after this victory and he was the last emperor serving jointly with a western counterpart.

Following the death of Theodocius in 396 the eastern and western emperors were completely separate and served only in their own regions. The East benefited from this split, retaining the taxes and tribute that had previously been remitted to Rome. Egyptian wheat was rerouted to Constantinople and the new capital, which incorporated the city of Byzantium, soon grew to metropolitan size. Theodocius' son, Arcadius, governed the East under the prefect Rufina, but on their return from Italy Theodocius' eastern army assassinated Rufinus and effective rule fell to the eunuch, Eutropius, who in turn was murdered in 399 in part by a conspiracy of Goths in Phrygia. H.G. Wells (Ref. 14, page 414) wrote that this new Byzantium was a damaged resumption of the Hellenic Empire of Alexander, although the monarch had a Roman title. (Ref. 15, 16, 17, 18, 19)

At the base of the Anatolian peninsula, Armenia, under Terdat, a pro-Roman ruler, became the first entirely Christian state as it adopted the Monophysite variation in A. D. 303. Chosrov II reigned from 330 to 338 but by a treaty of 386 following one of the innumerable Roman-Persian wars, Armenia was divided between Byzantium and Persia, the latter getting the larger share. The Armenian alphabet was introduced by St. Mesrop about A.D. 400, such alphabet containing 38 letters and designed to handle the Armenian variation of the Indo-European language. (Ref. 20)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

3 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

4 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

5 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

6 [48] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

7 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, Otto j., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

8 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

9 [48] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

10 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, Otto j., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

11 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

12 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

13 [48] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

14 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

15 [48] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

16 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

17 [221] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., Change and Habit. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1966).

18 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

19 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

20 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

The Near East: A.D. 401 to 500

THE NEAR EAST

ARABIA AND JORDAN

Arabia was primarily a Bedouin land, with social organization pivoting around the tribe. Both Byzantine and Persia tried to protect themselves by supporting new buffer Arab border states and through these buffer zones, foreign customs and ideas filtered into the world of the nomads. Far south Arabia remained a civilized, Christian community with close ties to Ethiopia. In North Yemen repairs were attempted on an old earthen dam stretching some two thousand feet across the Wadi Dhana, using 20,000 men, 14,600 camels and 12,000 donkey teams. The dam diverted flood waters to irrigate about 4,000 acres of land but it lasted for only about a century. (Ref. 1)

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON & IRAQ AND SYRIA

This region continued as part of the Byzantine Empire. Monophysitism dominated in western Syria while Nestorians were prominent in the east until expelled in the later part of this century.

IRAN: PERSIA

The Sassanid Empire continued to flourish and after a treaty with Byzantium there was relative peace and tolerance of Christians. The Nestorians were particularly prevalent in Iran in the latter part of the century after they had been run out of the Byzantine area, proper, and later out of Syria. The city of Bandor Shahpur on the Persian Gulf was the site of a great hospital and translation center of Greek texts to Arabic. The Nestorians were active in these translations and in founding the hospital. Particularly famous was Jurgis Bukht-Yishu, first of six generations of translators.

The century began with Zorastrianism continuing as the major religion with taints of Hellenism still remaining, but now appeared Mazdak, a new preacher, reviving a kind of Manichean doctrine, which was translated into a kind of communism. It caused much political trouble for Kavadh I, who originally had supported the doctrine. This king married a Hepthalite (also spelled Ephthalite and sometimes called "White Hun", probably erroneously1 princess of the tribe that had taken over the old Kushan territory and who were beginning to absorb much land from Persia. These people, as well as Chionite nomads were threatening from the north most of this century. One of the most famous of the Sassanian kings was Vahram V (also Varahran), surnamed Gor, great hunter, poet and musician, who left the administration of the country to his chief magus, Mihr Shapur (A.D. 420-440).

In A.D. 484 the Persian army was finally annihilated and their king killed by the Hepthalites. During their period of control of Persia in the remainder of the century an exiled Persian, Kobad, who had been living among the invaders, took the throne, only to be driven off again by his own nobles in 489, perhaps because he supported the priest Mazdak's theories. (Ref. 4, 5, 67)

ASIA MINOR: ANATOLIA

TURKEY (BYZANTIUM)

As in the previous chapter, the reader is advised to study the sections on THE BALKANS, CENTRAL EUROPE and ITALY along with this section. For the two centuries just preceding, the Byzantine monarchy had kept up Roman institutions and had continued to use Latin in its courts, but in this century the central administration stopped the use of Latin in favor of Greek. Little was accomplished from the political and social standpoint during the entire century. For the sake of completeness only, the rulers of Byzantium are listed as follows:

The Dynasty of Theodosius   | The Dynasty of Leo
395 - 408 Arcadius   | 457 - 474 Leo I
408 - 450 Theodosius II   | 474 - Leo II
450 - 457 Marcian   | 475 - 491 Zeno
  | 491 - 518 Anastasius

Table 1

As this century began Goths, under a former Roman army general, Gainas, occupied Constantinople. They were soon eliminated, however, by mobs and the imperial army and thereafter Goths were not allowed to serve in the imperial forces as units, but only as individuals. When Theodosius II began to rule he was young and weak and the empire was actually controlled by his Empress Eudoxia. The reign was a tranquil period, however, and even the wars with Persia ceased. An official collection of imperial legislation was published as the Codes Theodosianus. The great issue of the administration was Nestorianism versus Monophysitism. In 428 Theodosius made Nestorius the patriarch of Constantinople and the latter then startled the Christian world by preaching that Mary was not to be considered the Mother of God, but only Mary, mother of the human Christ, and thus another heresy was started. At the third Ecumenical Council of Ephesus of 431 Monophysitism triumphed and Nestorius was excommunicated and banished to the Libyan desert where he subsequently died. His followers established the Nestorian Church and fled to eastern Syria and later to Persia, eventually founding communities in Balkh and Samarkand, in India and even China. Scattered through Asia a few survive to this day, still denouncing Mariolatry. (Ref. 8, 9, 10)

The one thorn of Theodosius' otherwise peaceful reign was the invasion of the Balkans by Asiatic Huns which had begun in the winter of A.D. 404-405 under the leadership of Uldin. By 408 they were terrifying the Balkan population. When many of the Huns defected to the Byzantine troops in the area, however, Uldin retreated for the moment. Periodic invasions of Thrace recurred, however, through the fourth decade of this century, requiring large tribute payments from the Byzantine government. There were still more an attack in 441 and 442 and the eastern Roman army, under a Goth General Aspar, was beaten time and again. The Huns broke off the engagement only after arrangements for large tribute payments by Theodosius. After the Huns retreat Theodosius stopped the agreed upon payments, probably not because of a lack of funds. It has been estimated that the average yearly revenue of the Eastern Empire at that time was about 170,000 pounds of gold, with only 45,000 pounds of this spent on the army. At any rate, because of the lack of payment the greatest Hun invasion of all in Thrace was launched in 447 with Attila at its head. Theodosius begged for terms and Attila got 6,000 pounds of gold due as back payment as well as a promise of 2,100 pounds annually in the future. At today's value, this would be in the neighborhood of $29,000,000 and over $10,000,000 respectively. In addition, there was to be a "demilitarized zone" from Pannonia to Sistova (north Bulgaria). (Ref. 11)

The fourth Ecumenical Council met at Chalcedon in 451 under Theodosius' successor, Marcian, and this time Monophysitism was condemned as well as Nestorianism, setting the stage for continued religious controversy for another two centuries. On Marcian's death, the barbarian General Aspar was influential in getting a military tribune, Leo I, as emperor. He, too, had Hun trouble as Attila's son, Dengizic, led an invasion into Thrace again. This time, however, many of the Huns did not join him and in 469 the eastern army defeated him, killed him and took his head to Constantinople. This was the last organized Hun expedition but many of those men subsequently joined the eastern army forces where they became known as "Massagetae". (Ref. 12)

When Zeno became emperor in 474 he followed policies which increased the schism between the eastern and western domains of the old Roman Empire and the western position completely collapsed in 476.

ARMENIA

The Monophysite Christians of Armenia now formed their own church, independent of Constantinople, and called it simply the Armenian Church. Whereas they had formerly used the Greek language, they now got a national alphabet and had the Bible translated into Armenian. This country had a fully developed feudal system from royal families down to peasants, but at this time the nation was nominally subservient to Persia. The people revolted against Persia when heavy taxes were levied and there were some religious persecutions, but the revolt was not successful. In 455 and 456 the Persians forcibly converted Armenia to Zorasterism but near the end of the century the Armenian leader, Vahan, helped the Persian King Volagases in a civil war and in an Edict of Toleration, the Christians were again granted freedom.

1 [82] GROVE, NOEL, "North Yemen", National Geographic 156: 244, Aug. 1979.

2 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

3 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

4 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

5 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

6 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

7 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

8 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

9 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

10 [49] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

11 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

12 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

1.  The origin and ethnic affinities of these people is unknown but they probably have no relationship to the "Attilic" Huns which will be described later in this chapter. The Ephthalites may have been of Tibetan or Turkish origin. (Ref. 2, 3)

The Near East: A.D. 501 to 600

THE NEAR EAST

ARABIA AND JORDAN

By 525 Judaism had gained such a foothold in the Himyarite kingdom in the south that the rulers themselves began to persecute the Christian population. This was the justification which the Abyssinians (Ethiopians) used to invade south Arabia between 525 and 530, conquering the Himyarites and leaving an Abyssinian governor. By about 570, however, the Persians conquered and controlled the whole of Arabia. (Ref. 1, 2)

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON, & IRAQ AND SYRIA

The western portion of this large area continued to share in the fate of Byzantium. Christian vandalism against the Jews and Samaritans1, which had started in the preceding century, now increased with destruction of synagogues and temples. An earthquake of 526 did not help matters when it killed 200,000 to 300,000 people in Antioch. (Ref. 3) The Jews and Samaritans revolted in 529 and again in 560 and finally welcomed the invasion of the Persians as they extended their empire once again about 570. The Jews took this opportunity to destroy a few churches and Christians in revenge. Of course, the entire eastern portion of this Syrian area, that is, most of present day Iraq, belonged to the great Persian Empire throughout this period.

IRAN: PERSIA

King Kobad, previously expelled by his own nobles, returned to the throne in 501 and waged the first war with Byzantium. But his previous friends, the Ephthalites, raided from the northeast and he had to sue for peace with the Christians before he could finally expel the Asian invaders from Persia in A.D. 513. The 2nd Byzantine-Persian War followed from 524 to 531 and at the end of that conflict Kobad's son, Chosroes I (or Khosru or Khosrau), became the greatest of the Persian kings. To insure his dynasty, like many another Asian monarch, he executed all of his brothers and their male offspring with one exception and included Mazdak and all of his followers. It was he who finally completely defeated the Ephthalites in central Asia in 557.

Pahlavi, the Indo-European language of Parthian Persia, was still in use and Zorastrianism was the official religion, with the God Ormuzd and the devil Ahriman. Chosroes' reign was tolerant, however, to Nestorian and other brands of Christians and to Jews. He actually helped the Nestorians to establish a library. The great Persian Medical School at Gondishapur also had a famous medical library containing works from Byzantium and perhaps some of Hippocrates' works came through here to the Arabic world. In this hey-day of the Persian Empire, the University of Judi-i-Shapur became the greatest intellectual center of the world, with teachers and scholars from all over Europe and Asia. Roads and villages were rebuilt and there was reform of the fiscal system and taxation methods. Many irrigation systems were completed and the famous metal-workers of Antioch, Syria were brought to Iran. (Ref. 4, 5)

After the Persians had driven to the Mediterranean coast and taken all of the Arabian peninsula, Byzantine allied with the Turks drifting down from the Eurasian border,- but they still could not defeat the Persians. At the end of the century, however, the Persian Empire became divided into four great satrapies: the east, comprised of Khosasan and Kerman; the west, including Iraq and Mesopotamia; the north, made up of Armenia and Azerbaijan; and the south, which contained Fars and Khuziasan. Wars continued on all borders until the end of the century.

ASIA MINOR

TURKEY: BYZANTIUM

The zenith of the Byzantine Empire was reached under the Emperor Justinian who was born in Sofia, possibly of Slavic peasant parents. He encouraged the oriental conception of royalty as divine, but labored to reunite the western and eastern Christian churches. He was strongly influenced by his wife, Theodora, a woman also of humble origins. The Justinian Code of Laws have remained in history as part of the Canonical Laws of the Catholic Church. Constantinople remained the greatest market and shipping center in the world, with companion harbors on the Black Sea and a direct sea route established through the Red Sea to India. Although the secret of silk was jealously guarded in the Far East, by various means Justinian introduced silk worms, white mulberries, the method of unwinding cocoons and the weaving of the thread, into Byzantium so that he also became the emperor of silk. From this the western Christian empire earned a fortune which it guarded for centuries. (Ref. 6)

On the religious front the church was unrelenting, the Jewish deuterosis was outlawed and there were expulsions of Jews with some massacres in Antioch in 592 and in Jerusalem after the turn of the century. Justinian's General Belisarius reconquered North Africa and southern Spain from the Vandals and most of Italy from the Goths, bringing the empire to its greatest geographical extent. (Ref. 7) Many of the units of the Byzantine army of this 6th century were remnants of the Huns called "Massagetae". They were intemperate drinkers and often difficult to control, although fierce warriors. (Ref. 8)

In the years 542 and 543 a great epidemic, of ten called the "Plague of Justinian" hit Asia Minor. This was definitely bubonic plague, penetrating from an original focus either in northeastern India or central Africa and spreading around the Mediterranean by ship. Necessary to this spread was the appearance of the black rat from its native India, along with its fleas. Procopius reported that 10,000 people died daily in Constantinople at the peak of the epidemic and the disease raged for four months. The political effect was great and the imperial power was weakened. Another epidemic in 655 and famine in 569, along with attacks by Bulgars and Avars from the Balkan area, all contributed to dissolution of the empire soon after Justinian's death. (Ref. 9, 10)

ARMENIA

Armenia was caught up in most of the wars between Byzantium and Persia. For the most of this era it was subservient to Persia, but late in the century both Georgia and Armenia were again partitioned with Byzantium getting a large part of the latter. Because of Byzantine help to the Persian King Chosroes II in an internal fight, this monarch, once reestablished on the Persian throne, ceded Iberia and nearly all of Armenia to the

Eastern Roman Empire in A.D. 591, thus allowing Byzantine troops stationed there to return to defend the Balkans against the Avars. (Ref. 11)

1 [82] GROVE, Noel, "North Yemen", National Geographic 156: 244, Aug. 1979.

2 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

3 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

4 [15] BOOKS AND MEDICINE, (Editors), M.D. Medical News Magazine, Vol. 3, No. 8, Aug. 1959.

5 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

6 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

7 [49] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

8 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

9 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

10 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

11 [49] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

1.  The Samaritans were remnants of Babylonians and Syrians whose ancestors had migrated to Palestine nearly a thousand years before. They were not Jews but used the Pentateuch as their holy book, without accepting any other part of the Bible

The Near East: A.D. 601 to 700

THE NEAR EAST (AN AMAZING CONQUEST OF THE NEAR EAST BY ISLAMIC ARABS)

It was in this century that the people of Kurdistan were converted to the Sunni variety of Islam. The Kurds are a people closely related ethnically to the Persians, who have tried through the ages to keep themselves intact as sheep-raising and rug weaving nomads, without respect to political boundaries. Kurdistan embraces the present day areas of east TURKEY, Soviet Armenia, northeast Iraq and northwest Iran. (Ref. 1)

ARABIA AND JORDAN

Muhammad (or Mohammed) was born in the south of Arabia of poor parentage early in the century. He married wealth and soon began to teach a new religion, taking as basic beliefs the monotheism of the Jews. He accepted Jesus as a prophet and formulated a new creed of behavior for his fellow Arabs. He had the visionary power of a seer, the astuteness of a master politician and a poet's mastery of language. (Ref. 2) By the time of his death in A.D. 636 his followers had already become almost fanatical in their zeal to spread the new faith and their armies poured out of the Arabian Peninsula to sell the religion by force of arms. The Arabs' military success approached the miraculous as they subdued the greatest kingdoms with small armies made up of mounted men on the famed Arabian horses. (Ref. 3)

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON & IRAQ AND SYRIA

The early part of the century was a period of some general decay in this entire area, with Persia and Byzantium more or less splitting control. At the death of Emperor

Maurice of Byzantium at the hands of his own soldiers, Chosroes II of Persia went on a conquering spree, taking Roman Mesopotamia in 607-615, then Armenia and some of Anatolia itself. But the pestilences which had visited the Romans and Persians alike from 542 on may explain in great part the little resistance their forces offered the Moslem eruption in 634. By the time of the Arab conquest Syria, in general, was an impoverished and stricken land. Damascus, as well as Jerusalem, had not recovered from the effects of the previous long and terrible sieges. Palmyra stood empty. In Mesopotamia there is some evidence that many irrigation canals had been abandoned, probably from a lack of labor supply due to the plague, before the Moslems had even arrived and it is doubtful if the Arabs actually destroyed much. (Ref. 4, 5)

The first incursion of Arabs into Iraq occurred in A.D. 633 with forces under Khalid ibn-al-Walid, although the main advance was a little to the west into Syria. They defeated the Byzantines in a last battle at Yarmuk in 636 and Jerusalem capitulated in 638. The chief administrator of Iraq and the coastal region from 644 to 656 was Othman (also Uthman) of the Omayyad (also Umayyad) family. Using his nepotism as an excuse, troops from Iraq and Egypt assassinated Othman in Medina in 656 and he was succeeded by Ali, the prophet's cousin and son-in-law. Mo'awiya, an Omayyad governor of Syria, disputed this succession, proclaimed himself caliph1 in Jerusalem in 660 and went on to establish a capital at Damascus in 661, initiating the Omayyad Caliphate. Descendants of Ali continued intermittent warfare with the combatants eventually ending up as the northern (Omayyad) Arabs against the southern. The latter were chiefly the Shi'ites2 and by the end of the century these partisans were more or less in control of Arabia, Persia and Mesopotamia. In addition, the old line of demarcation between Roman Syria and Persian Iraq or Mesopotamia survived this Moslem conquest. A strong sense of difference between the populations at large in these two provinces, fostered by the differences in their respective administrations easily coalesced with long standing rivalries in the two Arab garrisons. Many civil wars resulted. (Ref. 6, 7)

As the Arab armies overran Mesopotamia and Iran, sizable groups of Jews were pretty well left alone as protected minorities. All aspects of their civil and religious life were administered by Jewish officials in accordance with the Babylonian Talmud. At this time Hindu numerals were in use in Syria and later these became known as "Arabic numerals". (Ref. 8)

IRAN: PERSIA

As the century began Chosroes II ruled the Persians with avarice, suspicion and cruelty and a ruinous taxation to support his own splendid living. His armies fought their way to the Bosporus and to Egypt and came within sight of Constantinople but some 10 years later Emperor Honorius, in alliance with the Khazars just east of the Caspian, struck back, attacking the Persian homeland (623-624). The Persians retaliated by attacking Constantinople once again with Avar help in 626 but the east Roman navy kept the two land forces apart and the attack was a failure. Chosroes II was then murdered by his nobles and his son, Kavadh II, made the final peace, surrendering Egypt, Palestine, Syria, Asia Minor and western Mesopotamia back to the Byzantine Empire. Then pestilence broke out in Persia and thousands died, including the king. There followed a fight for the throne and in this atmosphere of disease and general moral decay and decline came the Arab armies of Islam about 636 and Persia quickly became part of the Moslem realm. The decisive action with the Arabs occurred at Al Qadisiya, Iraq, when the Persian army was literally smashed, allowing Arab capture of the capital, Ctesiphon (very near Selucia in Mesopotamia), in A.D. 635, thus opening the road to the main Iranian plateau. After the take-over a few Persian nobles maintained their independence in the mountains of Tabaristan at the south end of the Caspian. (Ref. 9, 10)

The Arabs did not force their conquered subjects to embrace Islam but did require them to accept the Koran as divine teaching and obliged them to learn Arabic, thus building an empire united by a common tongue. (Ref. 11, 12) There were probably many factors in the easy fall of the great Persian Empire to the surging Arab armies. In addition to the factors listed in the paragraph above, it should be realized that both Byzantium and

Sassanian Persia had exhausted themselves battling each other for many years. But there was also an economic cause of decline as the use of the Silk Route to China diminished. The Byzantines had smuggled silk cocoons from China and could now supply themselves with silk and the economy suffered all along the old route.

Byzantium had become the original heir of classical Greek medicine but during the persecutions of a number of learned heretics they fled to Persia, where, at Jundishapur, they met Syrian, Persian and Hindu scholars and working together, they translated many important works into Syriac, the new language of learning in the Near East. When Persia fell to the Arabs, many works of medicine were then translated from Syriac into Arabic, including large works of Galen. (Ref. 13)

ASIA MINOR

TURKEY

After Emperor Justinian's death at the close of the preceding century (595) the eastern Roman Empire collapsed with nothing left except a few Asiatic ports, some fragments of Italy, Africa and Greece. The capital itself was besieged by the Persians under Chosroes II, helped in the north by an army of Avars. In A.D. 602 the "Roman" army fighting the Avars revolted, returned to Constantinople and murdered Emperor Maurice, while the Avars devastated the Balkans. The cross-bow reached Byzantium from central Asia at about this time, perhaps borrowed from the Avars. (Ref. 14, 15)

The whole of the Asia Minor peninsula had been ploughed and furrowed by Persian armies and the great cities had been plundered and sacked, but the Byzantines still had an unbeaten navy and after 10 years, Heraclius, the new emperor, built a new army, sailed across the Black Sea, marched across Armenia and attacked and defeated Persia from the rear (A.D. 624). The victory was a hollow one, however, as the Arabs soon advanced into this territory with Khalid ibn al-Walid defeating a Byzantine army at the battle of the Yarmuk. The Byzantine frontiers were backed into Turkey, proper, again and after 673 the Moslems even blocked Constantinople both by land and sea, allowing it to be attacked every year for the next five. Only the strength of the city's walls and the appearance of "Greek fire", an explosive of unknown composition, saved the empire.

Although we have used the terms "Byzantine" and "Byzantium" freely in the last few chapters, actually it was not until the second half of this century that earlier historians applied these names in reference to the eastern Roman Empire. "Byzantion" was the old Greek name for Constantinople, and as the language of this eastern empire became chiefly Greek, the term "Byzantium" came into use. (Ref. 16)

ARMENIA

Throughout most of this century Armenia was in the middle of a three-cornered war involving Arabs, Khazars and Byzantines, but they managed to remain virtually sovereign and zealously Christian. (Ref. 17) After first being overrun by the eastern Roman army on its way to Persia, later the Arabs invaded. In the first several decades the higher classes had great prosperity incident to the exportation of manufactured goods and raw mining products. It was also a period of intellectual activity with philosophical, mathematical, astronomical and cartographic studies. Ananias, of Shirak, was a great scientist. Many Armenians served as mercenaries for Byzantium, particularly after the Arabs appeared on the scene and by late century the mainstays of that army were Armenian. (Ref. 18)

1 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

2 [83] HALLETT Robin, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

3 [122]  LEWINSOHN, Richard, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

4 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

5 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

6 [2] ABERCROMBIE, THOMAS J., "The Sweep of Islam.", Great Religions of the World, (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

7 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

8 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

9 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

10 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

11 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

12 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

13 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

14 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

15 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

16 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

17 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

18 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

1.  A caliph is the religious and civil leader of a Moslem state and the region he controls is a caliphate. In contrast an emir may be just an Arab chieftain or a favored descendant of Mohammed

2.  The Shi'ites (or Shiah) represent one of the two great divisions of the Moslem faith. They believe that only the descendants of Ali are eligible to be caliphs

The Near East: A.D. 701 to 800

THE NEAR EAST

During their three centuries of control the Arabs spread citrus fruits and almonds across the Mediterranean, even to Spain, and rice and sugar cane cuttings (from Persia) and saffron to the west. (Ref. 1) In addition they had mastered techniques of spinning and weaving silk and they transmitted seri-culture to the west via Sicily and Spain. Europe, however, was slow to accept silk. (Ref. 2) About A.D. 750 the Arabs brought the decimal system from India, but it was not used in Europe for another 500 years. (Ref. 3)

This entire NEAR EAST, including our four designated territories of ARABIA AND JORDAN, MEDITERRANEAN COAST AREAS, IRAQ AND SYRIA and IRAN, were now all joined as the central area of the giant Arabian Moslem Empire. As a result of military maneuvers the farmlands of Palestine were laid waste, not to be entirely reclaimed for 12 centuries. (Ref. 4) As the Moslem armies went through Spain and into France to be stopped finally at Tours in 732, some dissension appeared at home and by A.D. 749 there was open rebellion and a massacre of the Omayyad family at their capital, Damascus.

The Omayyad caliphs had forgotten their desert origins and had degenerated. Caliph al Walid II, who delighted in swimming and drinking in a pool of wine, was killed in a Yemenite revolt in 744. The last of the Omayyads was Marwan II, defeated and killed in the Battle of the Zab, associated with the general massacre of the family. The caliphate then became hereditary in the Abbasid family, beginning with Harun al Rashid, who changed the capital from Damascus to the newly built city of Baghdad in 763. The Abbasids stayed orthodox (Sunni), in spite of support they had had from Shi'ites while coming into power. Baghdad was a circular city 1.5 miles in diameter, ringed by three lines of walls and its construction involved 100,000 laborers. (Ref. 5, 6, 7)

Harun al Rashid was a great general, administrator and judge, who initiated many changes including the abolition of all distinctions between Arab and non-Arab Moslems. His administration supported any activity that would bind minority groups tighter to the central authority. The main military support came from Persian converts of eastern Iran and they out-fought the Arab garrisons of Iraq and Syria. The Abbasids completed the process of Persianizing the institution of the caliphate. Persians who served under the caliph increasingly filled the high offices of state and the entire administration was reorganized on Persian lines, with an efficient fiscal system, a good postal service from one end of the empire to the other and the establishment of trade routes to India, China, Ceylon and the Mediterranean. The Islamic world was united by a single religion, single language and a nearly unitary culture. The administration, culture and geographical limits in the Near East were about the same as the old Achaemenid Empire of the 6th century B.C. Paper mills were operating in Baghdad and the harem-eunuch system was developed along with purdah (veiled women). It should be noted that large numbers of east African Negro slaves were purchased for agricultural work and they were harshly treated. (Ref. 8, 9, 10)

Arabic, the youngest Semitic tongue, had in those early times a highly developed oral, but virtually no written tradition. There was much poetry depicting the life of the proud Bedouin. In the new Islamic Empire, Arabic became the chief instrument of everyday speech as well as of culture, replacing Aramaic, Coptic, Greek and Latin. Arabic also had enormous influences on other Muslim languages, such as Persian and Turkish. (Ref. 11)

ASIA MINOR

Asia Minor is the one portion of our chosen NEAR EAST classification that was not included in the paragraphs above, as the Christian Byzantines kept a tenuous hold on a part of this region, necessitating a separate consideration.

TURKEY

The Emperor Leo III (717) who announced the Iconoclastic policy, was an Isaurian, the first oriental on the throne. He carved out a brief ghost of the old Byzantine Empire, like Charlemagne's Empire in the West, turning the Eastern Church into a sort of department of state. But this Byzantium was a peculiar post-humous existence of the antique civilization and it was almost sealed off from western Europe, partly by the Greek 456 language, partly by a religious difference but chiefly because it didn't want to get involved in the bloody feuds of the western barbarians. It had its own eastern barbarians to deal with. In Constantinople and other cities a series of plagues and earthquakes had drastically reduced the populations. Bubonic plague killed 200,000 between 732 and 736 and then after a terrible earthquake in 740 there were not enough local people left to repair the damage. Intermittent warfare with the Arabs added to the drain of manpower. The second great siege of Constantinople by the Arabs occurred in 717-718 with attacks by both land and sea. The defenses held and Constantine V actually took the offensive, carrying the war into Syria in 745 and destroying a great Arab armada and reconquering Cyprus in 746.

Another campaign followed in Armenia and there were nine successive campaigns against the Bulgars, with ultimate victory. (Ref. 12, 13)

Still, by 771 the Byzantine Empire had shrunk down to primarily the western 2/3 of the Anatolian peninsula, along with Greece, Sicily, a few islands and a narrow coast line along Dalmatia. Intermittent battles along with pay-offs to the Arabs continued throughout the century and at the end there was much family stress in the emperor's house, with Irene, mother of Constantine VI, eventually having her son killed so that she could reign, herself, as Empress.

ARMENIA

The Byzantium-Moslem wars and the cruel repressions which followed each conquest or revolt had ruined and decimated this country. Under the Abbasid rule from Baghdad the situation became even worse and the population of Armenia was reduced to poverty.

1 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

2 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

3 [21] BRONOWSKI, j., The Ascent of Man. (Little, Brown & Co. Boston, Toronto, 1973).

4 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

5 [118] Fay, Howard, "Syria", National Geographic 157: 485-511, Apr. 1980.

6 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

7 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

8 [49] DURANT, Will, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

9 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

10 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

11 [68] GARRATY, JOHN a. and Gay, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

12 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

13 [119] LANGER,wm. l. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

The Near East: A.D. 801 to 900

THE NEAR EAST

ARABIA AND JORDAN

The original home of the Moslems was no longer the center of their activity, but Muhammed's home area at Mecca remained their religious focal point. At the end of this century this city was controlled by the heretical Shi'ite sect. Moslem states which remained separate from the Abbasid Caliphate were set up in eastern Arabia and Yemen. (Ref. 11

1 Actually it extended even father, to Baghdad, in Mesopotamia. It was lavishly equipped with wells, catch basins, rest stops and hostelries for pilgrims to Mecca. The name "Zubaida" was that of the wife of Caliph Harun al Rashid. (Ref. 2)

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS & IRAQ AND SYRIA

Early in the century, with the Abbasid Moslem administration at Baghdad, there was remarkable growth of that city. By 814 it covered approximately 10 by 9 kilometers, the equivalent of modern-day Paris within the outer boulevards. (Ref. 3) The caliph in Baghdad was the most powerful man on earth and the Arab dhows rode the Indian Ocean from end to end. (Ref. 4) The reign of Mamun the Great (813-833) was probably the most glorious of all. Damascus and Baghdad each had observatories and a House of Knowledge, with a rich library in the latter city. (Ref. 5) Later, even as the administration began a decline there was still considerable progress in the area in science, literature, astronomy and medicine. Translations continued to be made from Syriac, Greek, Pahlavi and Sanskrit to Arabic. Johannitus was one of the great translators of medicine just after 800. The Hellenistic heritage was appropriated with some added original Moslem contributions. The mathematician, Al-Kharizmi, for example, became the first to use Indian (our Arabic) numerals to develop new forms of calculation.

In the west of this region, Syria played its usual role as a border state between two rival empires, this time the eastern Abbasids of Baghdad and the Turkish controlled Egypt. Early in the century the former dominated but about 870 Syria was conquered for Egypt by Ahmad ibn Tulun, one of the Turkish mercenaries originally hired by the caliphs for personal body guards and armies.

IRAN: PERSIA

As the Abbasid Caliphate eventually became corrupt and weakened, it gave way in the last of the century in Persia to the native Saffarid Dynasty, which also ruled part of Central Asia. One spot just south of the Caspian remained separate as the Shi'ite Emir- ate of Alid (Descendant of Ali). (Ref. 6) The Persian language was revived. Windmills with vertical sails fitted to wheels turning horizontally were operating in Persia by this century and possibly much earlier. These mills may have spread from Iran to China as well as to the Mediterranean. (Ref. 7)2

2 (Ref. 8)

ASIA MINOR: ANATOLIA

TURKEY (BYZANTIUM)

Although the Emperor Nicephorus made peace with Charlemagne in 803 so that the eastern empire could retain control of southern Italy, Venice and Dalmatia, he could not pacify the Arabs who resumed raids in 804 through 806. As a result the Byzantines lost control of the seas and African Moslems took Crete and invaded Sicily. The Rus took over the Black Sea and by 860 attacked Constantinople itself. After 867 Byzantine fortunes improved, however, as a capable general, Basil I, founded the Macedonian Dynasty. Although born in Macedonia, Basil was actually of Armenian descent. In the meantime, in spite of the more or less constant and losing warfare, as is so often the case, the Greek Byzantine Empire at the same time enjoyed a brief renaissance as the University of Constantinople was restored and an Alexandrian Age of scholarship developed. Schools of law and medicine, as well as philosophy and mathematics, were promoted. A unique and formidable religious art accompanied the intellectual activity, particularly after the Council of Sophia had allowed the return of iconoclasm and instituted a new period of persecution of certain monks.

ARMENIA

The Christian kingdom of Armenia, which now included the old Georgian kingdom of Iberia, kept independent of the Arabs by paying tribute. The Bagratuni family established a dynasty under the title of "Prince of Princes", built a capital at Ani and gave the country several generations of progress and relative peace. Ashot I was the first independent sovereign, ushering in Armenia's "Golden Age". (Ref. 9)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [315] HAMBLIN, Dora Jane, "Treasures of the Sands", Smithsonian, Sept. 1983, pp. 43-53.

3 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

4 [2] ABERCROMBIE, THOMAS J., "The Sweep of Islam.", Great Religions of the World, (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

5 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

6 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

7 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

8 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

9 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

The Near East: A.D. 901 to 1000

THE NEAR EAST

Beginning about 960 Turkish tribesmen infiltrated the central regions of the Islamic world, seizing power in Mesopotamia and Iran. We shall see that at the same time other Turkish people invaded the Ukraine and on their other flank charged the Chinese borders. (Ref. 1)

ARABIA AND JORDAN

The actual center of the Arab administration and religion had shifted out of the Arabian peninsula. In the south a Shi'ite sect, the Qarmatians (Carmathians) had revolted against the Abbasids in 899 and then remained completely independent as the chief civilization center in that part of the Arab world. (Ref. 2)

It seems appropriate at this time to consider, for a moment, the world effect of the Arabian culture and particularly the Arabic language. Many Arabic words were widely used throughout civilization at that time and have come down to us in English. These include tariff, traffic, magazine, caravan, bazaar, check, cipher and zero. Algebra, an Arabic word, was a subject developed extensively, with both analytical and geometric solutions of equations. Chemistry was almost created by the Moslems.

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREA

These coastal areas, as well as much of western Syria, were now controlled by the Egyptian caliphate, even through the periods of changing administrations.

IRAQ AND SYRIA

The Abbasid Dynasty at Baghdad became weaker and weaker, while the caliph, himself, was at the mercy of his Turkish "praetorians", whose chiefs came and went in rapid succession. One after another of the provinces was lost to the central government and finally, although the Abbasid Caliph persisted as the Moslem religious head (comparable to the pope in the Catholic world), the government of this near east area was taken over by the Buwayhid Emirate, a pro-Shi'ite, Turkish dynasty. (Ref. 3) These Seljuk (also Seljuq) Turks established themselves in Baghdad with a new kind of Muslim state based on a partnership between men of the sword (chiefly their own Turks) and bureaucrats and men of the law (Persians or Arabs), all under the name of the Abbasid Caliphate. (Ref. 4) As Toynbee (Ref. 5), has written, the Abbasid name continued to be used by the usurpers of its power, for seven centuries after the beginning of its decline, just by virtue of its long tenure.

In spite of political decay, science and art continued to advance. Hospitals and medical science were especially good and extensive, with 860 licensed physicians in Baghdad alone, in A.D. 931. The hospital at Damascus had elegant rooms and an extensive medical library. (Ref. 6) We mentioned on page 479 that al-Khwarizmi introduced "Arabic" numerals from India. In this century he used the decimal system and wrote standard treatises on al-jabr (algebra).

IRAN: PERSIA

The Samanid Dynasty continued, ruling the adjacent part of Central Asia as well as most of Persia, proper. The Persian language was used with commercial activity at its height. Avicenna, of north Persia, was the greatest of the medieval philosophers and also an excellent physician, writing the "Canon of Medicine", which was used at Montpellier Medical School of southern France when it was established in 1650. Al Razi (or Rhazes), a Persian who wrote in Arabic, was considered the greatest of all medieval physicians. The medical Arabists (which included Nestorian Christians, Persians and Jews, who were not ethnic Arabs) relied both on writers of the past, such as Galen, and on developing new aspects of pharmacy and chemistry, including techniques of distillation, crystallization, solution, sublimation, reduction, and calcination. They were good clinicians and instructors, describing such things as scabies and mediastinal abscesses, previously unrecognized. Midwives did much of the obstetric and gynecological work, however. (Ref. 7)

The manufacture of astrolabes had already begun in Persia at Isfahan and certain stylistic features of the earliest of these remained typical of eastern Islamic astrolabes throughout their history. These were complicated observational and computing instruments for astronomers. (Ref. 8) The conversion to Islam of the old, heavy horse cavalrymen caused them to abandon their old military ethic and as a result of this decrease in protection, nomad raiding from the steppe began again with the appearance of Turkish invaders. Chief among these were the Ghaznawids, under commander-in-chief Subaktagin, formerly a slave in Khorasan. (Ref. 9)1

1 (Ref. 10)

ASIA MINOR

TURKEY: BYZANTIUM

In spite of being ringed by enemies and having only a small geographical area, this was a time of prosperity for the Macedonian Dynasty. The army was good, there was little religious controversy, the provinces were well governed and Constantinople was the richest city of the world. The emperors continued to have Norse mercenaries as the Varangian guard. There were continued Romano-Bulgarian wars, however, and this caused some break-down in the Greek Orthodox Christian Society and some territory continued to be lost. The great warrior Emperor Basil II began to reign in 976, but Anatolia was soon overrun by great feudal barons who eventually began to rise up against Basil. (Ref. 11)

As a side light of some medical interest, a 1978 study of skeletons dating between the 7th and 12th centuries, from Kalenderhane Camii in Istanbul, indicated good nutrition and general health of the individuals of this region. The average height for males was 5'6" and for women 5'1". Mongoloid features, such as shovel-shaped incisors, pinched foreheads, etc. occurred in 15 to 25%, suggesting mercenaries and merchants either from beyond the Caucasus or from the Russian steppes. 69% of the males showed osteoarthritic changes in the spine and 33% in the extremities. (Ref. 12)

ARMENIA

Sajid Emir of Azerbaijan, on the southwest coast of the Caspian, spent the early century forming a new Armenian kingdom called "Vaspurakan", south of Armenia proper, thus creating a rivalry that actually resulted in Armenians killing Armenians. (Ref. 13) In the original country, however, the reign of Gagik I marked the apogee of the material prosperity and cultural revival of Armenia. The Bagratunis continued to reign until about A.D. 1,000 when the central authority became weak and broke down with the formation of about six virtually independent kingdoms. (Ref. 14)

1 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

2 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

3 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

4 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

5 [221] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., Change and Habit. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1966).

6 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

7 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

8 [173] RAMSEY L.G.G., The Complete Encyclopedia of Antiques. (Hawthorn Books, Inc., New York, 1962).

9 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

10 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

11 [170] PREBBEL, John, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

12 [4] ANGELL, J. LAWRENCE, "Osteoarthritis in Prehistoric Turkey and Medieval Byzantium", Henry Ford Hospital Journal 27: 38, 1979.

13 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

14 [237] WILSON, DAVID, The Vikings and their Origins. (Thames and Hudson, London, 1970).

The Near East: A.D. 1001 to 1100

THE NEAR EAST

ARABIA AND JORDAN, MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS, & IRAQ AND SYRIA

In the last chapter we witnessed the fragmentation of the once great Abbasid Empire. Its breakdown paved the way for the takeover late in this 11th century by a new Turkish power coming out of the east - a new wave of Seljuqs, a clan of mercenary Ghuzz who had revolted from Ghaznavid employ in 1037 and then soon took over entire control of the area, even of the parent tribe. The remaining Ghuzz, as we shall see later, crossed on west, north of the Caspian and were there known as "Cumans". The Buwayhid Emirate was already breaking up as these new Seljuqs arrived. The latter were orthodox Sunnites and they defeated the Shi'ite rulers, established themselves as the protectors of the Baghdad caliph and then went on to the Mediterranean coast. By the time the surviving stragglers of the 1st Christian Crusade reached the area of Jerusalem, intending to drive out those invading Turks, they had already been pushed back temporarily by the Fatimids of Egypt. Nevertheless, the good Christians slaughtered all the Moslems they could reach and did establish a number of small states, including the Latin Kingdom of Jerusalem (A.D. 1099), none of which lasted much more than a century. It was at this time that a group of Italian merchants from Amalfi established an hostel to care for the pilgrims visiting the shrines in Jerusalem, calling themselves "Knights Templar and the Hospitallers", which was to become the most powerful military order west of the Jordan River. (Ref. 1) Antioch was captured by Crusaders in 1098 and was ruled by them for nearly two centuries. The Christians called all this land from northern Syria to the Red Sea "outremer", meaning "beyond the sea". The Druze Muslim sect, descendants of ancient nomads, settled in the mountains by the Jordanian border. Some were tall, fair and blue-eyed, perhaps the remnants of intermarriage with Alexander's Greeks1 (Ref. 2)

Actually the primary interest of the Seljuqs was not the West but the control of Baghdad and the rich lands of northern Syria, as well as the destruction of the Fatimid Caliphate of Egypt, whose power threatened and whose heretic Shi'ite beliefs were an abomination to the rigidly orthodox Turks. (Ref. 3, 4, 5) Merchants in Iraq and adjacent regions had attained greater wealth and social prestige in the 10th century and the first part of the 11th than ever before but this was not to last long. (Ref. 6)

IRAN: PERSIA

At the beginning of this century Mahmud the Turk, leader of a remnant of the Kirghiz from Tuirkistan, who had ruled from Ghazni, Afghanistan for a century or so, took all of Persia and the Punjab in India, becoming the greatest of the Afghan rulers. His realm was short-lived, however, as a rival Turkish power, the Seljuq branch of the Ghuzz came out of Turkistan and Transoxiana and moving west, took the dynasties of Asiatic Islam one by one. The greatest Seljuq sultan was Malik-Shah. By 1055 the Ghaznavids had been expelled from Persia and the Buwayhids conquered. The conquest of southwestern Asia and even Asia Minor had been completed by 1090, although by the following year the sultanate had again broken up into a dozen warring factions. In the northern mountains of Persia (also in northern Syria), one branch of Shi'ites, the Ismailis, doped up on hashish, reigned with terror, murdering generals, viziers and even caliphs. They were called hashshashin (Hashish eaters) and thus our word "assassins". (Ref. 7)

Omar Khayyam, a Persian living in the last half of this century, was one of the greatest mathematicians of medieval times, developing a partial solution of cubic equations.- He was also without equal in astronomy and philosophy, an atheist, or advanced "free-thinker" and rejected all theology. It is ironical that he is known chiefly to us as a composer of quatrains, such as the Rubaiyah (from rubai - composed of 4), but all Persians in those days were poets and this was only a diversionary activity of the great Khayyam. Avicenna2, about whom we made mention in the last century, continued to work until his death in 1037. He was a Persian boy prodigy who is said to have mastered the Koran by age 10. At age 21 he wrote a scientific encyclopedia but his chief renown is as a physician, compiler, commentator and writer. Some of his texts were used as the basis for medical teaching, even in the British Isles, until the middle of the 17th century. It is said that he mentioned coffee in his writings and the word is definitely of Arabic origin, although the drink possibly originated in Ethiopia. Kahwah, originally meaning "wine", was used also to mean "coffee" and the later became kihwah. (Ref. 8, 9)

ASIA MINOR

TURKEY

Early in this century there was again a temporary resurgence of Byzantium, with Emperor Basil II eliminating the west-Bulgarian Empire, then reducing the Serbs to vassalage and conquering the Crimea (A.D. 1016) and annexing the Vaspurakan Armenian Kingdom. (A.D. 1022). Under the Macedonian emperors the structure of Byzantine society came closely to resemble that of Sassanian Iran. Princely landowners with armed retinues arose and there were confused clashes between rural and urban aristocracies. In the end this proved fatal to the imperial bureaucratic power.

One of the decisive battles of history occurred in 1071 when the Byzantine army was destroyed by the Sel juqs at Manzikert, north of Lake Van. After that, western Anatolia was controlled by the Sultanate of Rum and the Eastern Christian Empire consisted only of Constantinople, which had nearly one million people, and Greece. All of Asia Minor was in the control of the Seljuq Turks. Hereafter in this outline, Byzantium will be discussed under the section on GREECE. (Ref. 11, 12)

ARMENIA

Even with fragmentation and multiple kingdoms, the wealth, industry and trade of this area allowed of great prosperity. The people exported beautiful carpets and textiles, furs and leather goods, lumber, fish, minerals including gold, silver and copper, horses and mules, borax and salt. The monasteries had acquired great riches and their schools led a cultural revival, with skilled painters and incomparable scribes, poets and historians.

Gagik I, ruler of one of the major Armenian kingdoms, lived until 1020 when the country had reached the height of prosperity. In mid-century the Byzantines, in a last gasp, took over this territory until the Seljuq Turks conquered the entire area, along with the rest of the Middle East. The capital Ani fell in 1064 but many Armenians had already fled to the Taurus mountains and were by-passed by the Turks. After Ani fell, others moved to Cilicia, where they founded another kingdom called Lesser Armenia, an entity which lasted until the 14th century. While Armenia, proper, was divided, Georgia became unified and maintained independence until the 13th century. (Ref. 13)

1 [86] HANSEN, James, "Knights of Malta, mini-nation based on Chivalry", Smithsonian 12: 112-127, Jan. 1982.

2 [118] Fay, HOWARD, "Syria", National Geographic 157: 485-511, Apr. 1980.

3 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

4 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

5 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

6 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

7 [2] ABERCROMBIE, THOMAS J., "The Sweep of Islam.", Great Religions of the World, (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

8 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

9 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

10 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

11 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

12 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

13 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

1.  At the present there are still about 300,000 of these people in Syria, Lebanon and Israel, fighting Christians whenever they have the opportunity

2.  Avicenna's Persian name was Abu-ali al-Husayn ibn-Sina. (Ref. 10)

The Near East: A.D. 1101 to 1200

THE NEAR EAST

ARABIA AND JORDAN, MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS, & IRAQ AND SYRIA

In the north and east of this area the power of the Seljuqs waned as Sultan Sinjar died and the entire Near East became divided among warring kings, all Moslem. The western marches of the Sultanate of Hamadan were in the control of various emirs or atabegs (guardians for infant princes) and they were unable to prevent the founding of some Crusader states, such as Edessa and Jerusalem. In A.D. 1121 the Georgians from the Caucusus swept down as far as Tiflis. But a counter-blow by Zangi and his son Nureddin, establishing the Zangid Sultanate, soon unified Syria, with the absorption of Damascus and soon Egypt. (Ref. 1) The Crusaders kept on trying for territory, even after Saladin controlled the entire area. France's Philip captured Acre in 1191 and Richard of England negotiated with Saladin in 1192 and obtained a 3 year truce allowing the Christians a coastal strip between Joppa and Acre and access to Jerusalem. The Knights Templar and Hospitallers continued their mercy and military presence in that city. (Ref. 2)

IRAN: PERSIA

The century opened with the Seljuq Sultan of Hamadan controlling all of Persia except a small region south of the Caspian which was still ruled by the Assassins of Alamut. In the last half of the century, however, the sultanate was shrunk by inroads from the Arabian Peninsula of a new Abbasid Caliphate and from the west by the Zangid Sultanate which extended out from Syria. New emirates from Armenia and Azerbaijain on the western Caspian shore also appeared. (Ref. 3)

ASIA MINOR: ANATOLIA

TURKEY

The 1st Crusade left Anatolia in some confusion, with several small states, but although the remnant of the Byzantine Empire still held the coastal areas bordering the Aegean Sea (See map on page 575) the rest of Turkey became de-Hellenized and the Moslem culture predominated. Byzantine Emperor John II Comnenus did manage to exterminate the Patzinak Turks in the Balkans in 1122 but this was followed by a four year war with Venice. Peace with both Hungary and Venice occurred in 1126. (Ref. 4) The Sultanate of Nicaea, which had originally taken the major part of the Byzantine land, broke up with the Seljuqs holding the southwest half of Iconium and the Danishmandids inheriting the region northeast of that. The former soon broke up into still smaller emirates, however. (Ref. 5)

ARMENIA

Armenia proper was now ruled by Moslem Turks and Kurds but across the Tarsus Mountains in Cilicia, the Armenian people formed the country of Lesser Armenia, which now stood off all attacks and reached unparalleled prosperity.

1 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

2 [86] HANSEN, James, "Knights of Malta, mini-nation based on Chivalry", Smithsonian 12: 112-127, Jan. 1982.

3 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

4 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

5 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

The Near East: A.D. 1201 to 1300

THE NEAR EAST

If the reader is perusing this manuscript as a narrative and reading straight through, it is suggested at this point that he stop and turn now to CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA, this chapter, as the great Mongol invasions affected all parts of Eurasia and it will be important to have an understanding of the Mongol people, their organization and their homeland before attempting to interpret the remaining material in this 13th century.

ARABIA AND JORDAN

Except for the holy cities of Mecca and Medina, Arabia once again sank into oblivion and remained only on the fringe of world activity.

COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON

This area and particularly Jerusalem, was the scene of the Moslem-Christian battles incident to the Crusades. The Latin Kingdom of Jerusalem, which had been established in 1099, lasted less than a hundred years, but the Ayyubid Sultanate of Syria still allowed Christians to have that city and a small coastal corridor to prevent additional pin-pricking crusades. (Ref. 1) The Knights Templar and Hospitallers order of Italian Christian Knights continued to dominate the narrow coastal area until Acre finally fell to the Turks in 1291.

The Hospitallers then withdrew to Cyprus, taking sugar, which they had encountered in Syria, with them. (Ref. 2) In the meantime the Mamluk Turks from Egypt had defeated the Moslem forces from Syria in the great battle at Ain Jalut, near Nazareth, on September 3, 1260.

IRAQ AND SYRIA

The small Abbasid Caliphate, which had existed for about a century at the mouths of the Tigris and Euphrates was brutally crushed by the Mongols in 1258. The advancement of the Mongols into Iraq at that particular time can be traced to the actions of Louis IX of France, who had sent a Crusade to Egypt on the assumption that Eljigidei, in control of Persia, had turned Christian and that the French from Egypt and those Mongols from Persia could crush the Moslems between them. Unfortunately, the Mamluk Baibars forced the starving French army to surrender and Mangku, the Supreme Khan after 1251, ordered Hulegu, a grandson of Genghis, to advance through Syria to Egypt. Syria had refused to be governed by anyone not descended from Saladin and had crowned al-Nasir, King of Aleppo, as their independent sultan. But Hulegu began the bombardment of Baghdad on January 1, 1258, and by February 13th the city was sacked and the Moslem population massacred. Some Christian soldiers from Georgia, who had joined forces with Hulegu, took part in this with relish. The caliph and his sons were sewn up in carpets and trampled to death by Mongol horses. Finally the Mongol armies, themselves, were forced to abandon the city because of the stench of the corpses. It is of interest that Hulegu was a Buddhist, his favorite commander, Ked-Buka, was a Christian and so was his senior wife, Dokuz-Khatun, a Nestorian. (Ref. 3)

After Baghdad fell, Aleppo and Damascus sent word of surrender. It was at that time, however, that Mangku, the Supreme Khan, died of dysentery and Hulegu withdrew his army to Azerbaijan and the Syrian campaign was cancelled so that Islam was saved (A.D. 1259). Hulegu left for Mongolia, leaving Ked Buka in charge and it was the latter, with the remnants of the Mongol army that was defeated by the Mamluks at Ain Jalut, outside of Nazareth in 1260. The Mamluks were helped by a few Christians and a few tumen from the Golden Horde from Russia. But even with that defeat, Hulegu's soldiers stayed in Iraq and after his death in 1265 that area was ruled by his son, Abaka, who sent ambassadors to Europe several times to ask for a combined Christian-Mongol attack on Baibars, the Turk of Egypt. Finally Pope Gregory X replied that a campaign against the Moslems would be made within three years but it didn't materialize and in the meantime the Mongols lost control of Damascus. The last Christian garrison in Syria, at Crak des Cheoaliers, surrendered to Baibars in 1271 and the now militant Hospitallers moved to Cyprus and then to Rhodes. (Ref. 4, 5, 6)

After the sacking of Baghdad the entire Mesopotamian irrigation system was abandoned, never to be rebuilt and the productivity of the land shrank accordingly. In all fairness, however, it should be known that epicurean indulgence, physical and mental exhaustion, military incompetence and cowardice, religious sectarianism and obscurantism, political corruption and anarchy had all initiated a piece-meal collapse before the external attack of the Mongols. The raising and salination of the water table subsequent to over-irrigation may have done more to hasten Mesopotamia's decline than Hulegu's visitation. (Ref. 7)

The problem of the elevation of the fields above the canal levels as a result of centuries of silting was still another factor and this could be solved only by vast new canal construction on a scale and with a technical complexity which only a centralized administration could carry through. These things and not a change of climate turned western Asia from world leadership to destitution and from a hundred teeming and cultured cities in Syria, Iraq and Persia into the poverty, disease and stagnation situations of modern times – at least up to the late 20th century domination of Near East oil . In Toynbee's classification (Ref. 8) the Mongols, who came and went all within about 40 years, administered the coup de grace to the old Syriac Society. Former agricultural fields now again became grazing lands, all tending to restore a certain nomadic element in the Islamic culture. (Ref. 9)

Prior to 1295 the Mongols had favored Christianity over Islam, possibly for political reasons in an attempt to hold this minority group. After conversions of the Khan and his entourage to Islam, Christians were further subjected to massacres, forced mass conversions and various indignities, so that Christian communities in Iraq and Syria lost their importance. Only a few mountainous refuge areas remained solidly Christian after 1300. The Jews survived more successfully than the Christians.

After the battle of Ain Jalut, the Mamluks ruled Syria for almost 250 years. In spite of foreign domination and the decline in general, mentioned above, Syria still maintained some semblance of culture, with well maintained hospitals, including some for the insane and they treated all ophthalmological diseases with skill, including fine cataract operations. After this 13th century, however, Syria definitely waned.

IRAN: PERSIA

Early in the century the people of the western fragment of the Shahdom of Khwarizm were pushed into Persia by the Mongols, but shortly thereafter a young shah rallied them and seized Azerbaijan and Georgia. This new shahdom was short-lived as a new Mongol advance extinguished it in 1231. The Assassins of Alamut were annihilated in 1256. Al- though some say that 2/3rds of Iran's population was killed by the invading Mongols, still, Persia fared better that the other countries of the Near East. After Ogedei 's death, the Mongol Empire continued to expand in Persia through the campaign of Baiju and Hulegu, brother of Kublai, who founded a new Persian Il-Khan Dynasty in northwestern Persia, with a capital at Maragha. The greatest ruler of this dynasty was Ghazan Khan, scholar and administrator, whose reign gave great prosperity and culture. Chancellor Raslidu'd Din Fadu'llah, perhaps of Jewish parentage, was an administrator, scholar and physician, who established a great university city for the development of all the arts, crafts and sciences, bringing students and teachers from all over the world. Of the same era was Hafiz (meaning "remember"- given the name because he had memorized the entire Koran) – a fine poet, who was concerned with wine, women and song. Tabriz was a glorious city of 1,000,000 people at that time. In 1295 the Khan of Persia espoused the Moslem faith, after first flirting with Nestorian Christianity. It was in this century that there was the first mention of a Bakhatiyari tribe (probably Kurdish) in the Zagros mountains but it did not become a real force in Iranian history until the 18th century, when we shall meet them again. (Ref. 10, 11, 12, 13)

ASIA MINOR: ANATOLIA

TURKEY

Although Byzantine still dominated the immediate area of the Bosporus Strait as the century opened, the Seljuq Turks ruled most of the other regions know known as "Turkey". In addition to the small area about the straits, Byzantine controlled a small area of eastern Greece, southern Macedonia and a small area of coastal Anatolia. The latter soon went to the Venetians, however, when while carrying the 4th Crusaders, they took all the islands on the trade routes. The swordsmen of this 4th Crusade seized and ravaged Constantinople itself and then when the Mongols administered a crushing defeat on the Seljuq forces at Kose-dagh in 1243, there was very little central authority left. Then, for the first time, the Greeks had a majority in the shrunken empire. The little Kingdom of Nicaea eliminated the Latins from Asia about 1223 and then the Greeks teamed up with Venice's enemy, Genoa, to drive out the remaining westerners by 1261. An earthquake of 1268 which killed about 60,000 people in Cilicia added to the confusion. (Ref. 14, 15, 16)

NOTE: Insert Map 52. The Byzantine Empire 1265

It was into this shattered land of Anatolia that the beginnings of a new empire emerged. Although somewhat shrouded in legend it appears that about 1288 or 1290 Othman (or Osman) became the ruler of a small offshoot Turkish band from the Seljuqs from Khurasan, who had settled in a barren part of northwest Asia Minor. Far removed from the real Seljuq center of power, these Turks depended only on their stubborn dedication to Muslim causes and on their military prowess for survival. Under Othman and his son, the tribe prospered and gradually began to take territory away from both the Seljuqs, proper, and Byzantium. They were subsequently known either as Ottomans or Osmanlis.1

1 The Latins of the East (Romania) replaced the Greek Empire at Constantinople from 1204 to 1261.  (Ref. 17) After 1204 waves of Italian merchants arrived both in the city of Constantinople and on the shores of the Black Sea. Shopkeepers and notaries followed. (Ref. 18)

ARMENIA

The Armenian civilization continued chiefly in Cilicia, or Little Armenia. In 1247 the Sultan of Rum and the Christian king of Cilicia, Hayton I, became Mongol vassals. But the Egyptian Baibars started an attack in 1275, driving through Little Armenia and to Rum, there to defeat a Mongol army in the mountains, thus eliminating Mongol control. (Ref. 19)

1 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

2 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

3 [27] CHAMBERS, James, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

4 [27] CHAMBERS, James, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

5 [118] Fay, Howard, "Syria", National Geographic 157: 485-511, Apr. 1980.

6 [42] "CROSS AND CRESCENT, M.D. Medical Newsmagazine, Vol.3, No.3, March, 1959.

7 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

8 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

9 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

10 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

11 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

12 [70] GARTHWAITE, g.r., "The Bakhtiyari Tribe: Its Organization and Role in Iran". National Geographic Societv Research Reports Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 257-266. (National Geographic Society Publications, 1980).

13 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

14 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

15 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

16 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

17 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

18 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

19 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

The Near East: A.D. 1301 to 1400

THE NEAR EAST

ARABIA AND JORDAN, COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON, & IRAQ AND SYRIA

Although McNeill (Ref. 1) describes an homogeneous, organizational pattern and technique of trade which had been established all across the southern seas from the south China coast to the Mediterranean, the greater part of the Near East remained stagnant and unproductive. The decline of the irrigation works and the shift of the trade routes from the land to the sea had weakened the cities of Iraq and the centers of the Muslim society lay both farther west in Egypt and farther east in Persia. (Ref. 2) On the political side, the greatest episode of the era was Timur's conquest of Baghdad, in which his troops killed 90,000 people and erected 120 columns of their severed heads. (Ref. 3) More details of Timur's expeditions will follow in subsequent sections.

At Damascus, a fine physician, Ala'al-din ibn al-Nafis, expounded a theory of the pulmonary circulation of the blood 270 years before Servitus did-so in Europe.

IRAN: PERSIA

One of the most striking changes in the first half of the century in the Near East was the disappearance of the Khanate of Persia and its subject Seljuq Sultanate of Iconium and their replacement by a variety of petty states. In eastern Persia there were native provincial governments, while the diminished central power remained with the Mongol dynasty of the Jalayrids. Just north of the Persian Gulf was the Muzaffarid Emirate. (Ref. 4) Even so, the Muslim culture of the east was productive, with the art of the miniature and a new architectural style. The Persian language, revived in an Islamic form, was the medium of great poetry. (Ref. 5) As the century ended the conquests and raids of Timur resulted in his complete control of the country.

ASIA MINOR: ANATOLIA

TURKEY

The shrunken Byzantium was ruled by Michael IX and his father Andronicus as co-emperors, as the century opened. Antagonism with the Italians continued, so that in 1302 Andronicus hired Roger de Flor and his 6,000 Catalan mercenaries (The Catalan Company) from Barcelona, equipped with crossbows, to fight against those Italians who were in Constantinople. About 3,000 of the latter were killed and the Catalans then went on a rampage of their own through the Balkans. (Ref. 6)

As in Persia, throughout Anatolia there was a breakup of the previously ruling powers. The Seljuq Sultanate of Iconium, which had ruled the entire eastern portion of the peninsula under Persian suzerainty, gave way to a group of petty states. The Emirate of Karamanian, bordering on the Mediterranean corner, was at first the strongest but then all of the Byzantine Asia was conquered by the emir of Kastamuni, the six emirates of the southwest coast and finally the Ottoman sultanate on the northwest corner. (Ref. 7) The Ottoman capture of Bursa in 1326 was followed by the fall of the remaining Byzantine strongholds in the area so that by the middle of the century Byzantium existed essentially only on the European side of the Marmara Sea and a small portion of Greece. (Ref. 8)

NOTE: 53. The Byzantine and Ottoman Empires 1355

The Ottoman Turks continued to gain territory, crossing into Europe and gaining mastery of the Balkans as well as dominating the Anatolian princes. Their sultans, on assuming the throne, regularly practiced fratricide to remove potential claims to the crown. Later this was actually allowed by law, a practice they may have inherited from the Byzantines, themselves. Sir Mark Sykes, in The Caliphs' Last Heritage, stated:

"The relations between the Ottoman Sultans and the Emperors has been singular in the annals of Moslem and Christian states. The Turks had been involved in the family and dynastic quarrels of the Imperial City, were bound by ties of blood to the ruling families, frequently supplied troops for the defense of Constantinople, and on occasion hired parts of its garrison to assist them in various campaigns; the sons of the emperors and Byzantine statesmen even accompanied the Turkish forces in the field, yet the Ottomans never ceased to annex Imperial territories and cities both in Asia and Thrace."1

By the end of the century the Ottomans already had 12,000 Janissaries, chiefly from the Balkans. (See UPPER BALKANS, this chapter). It was at that time, too, that Timur invaded from the east and at Sivas, Turkey, he had 4,000 defenders buried alive, after a promise not to shed blood if they surrendered. (Ref. 10)

ARMENIA

We noted in the last chapter that the Armenian civilization remained chiefly in Cilicia, or Little Armenia, but even there it was under attack by the Egyptian forces and by 1375 even this small area was completely conquered and destroyed by the Mamluks. The few Armenians who were not slaughtered scattered throughout the Near East. To add further insult, in 1386 Timur seized the original, Greater Armenia and massacred most of the people there. (Ref. 11)

1 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [71] GEARY, DOROTHY, "Mighty Tamerlane became Master of Half the World", Smithsonian Sept. 1979, page 89.

4 [108] JORDON, ROBERT PAUL. "Sri Lanka", National Geographic 155: 123, Jan. 1979.

5 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

6 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

7 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

8 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

9 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

10 [71] GEARY, DOROTHY, "Mighty Tamerlane became Master of Half the World", Smithsonian Sept. 1979, page 89.

11 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

1.  As quoted by Wells, (Ref. 9), page 568

The Near East: A.D. 1401 to 1500

THE NEAR EAST

ARABIA AND JORDAN

In this period there were some independent nomad kingdoms along the northeastern periphery of the Arabian Peninsula on the Persian Gulf coast, but they were not important. The western, Red Sea coast was controlled by the Egyptian Mamluks. Coffee was first introduced as a beverage in Aden, in this century. (Ref. 1)

COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON

The entire Mediterranean coast was controlled by the Mamluk Sultanate of Egypt. (Ref. 2) Huge cannon, using balls of stone, helped the Turks batter down the walls of those Christian cities which had resisted them for 100 years. Slavery was prevalent in the entire area. (Ref. 3)

IRAQ AND SYRIA

This part of the Near East was becoming a back-water. At the opening of this century Iraq and Syria were part of the Timurid Emirate, but in 1408 Timur set up the separate Emirate of White Sheep Turks in this region and eastern Asia Minor, to counteract the Emirate of Black Sheep Turks, who had seized Persia. In 1410 the latter group took over the entire region, confronting the Timurids on a line running south of the Caspian. By 1467, however, the White Sheep group again conquered the entire area of Mesopotamia and Persia, pressing hard on the failing Asian Timurid Emirate of Herat. (Ref. 4)

IRAN: PERSIA

As the century began most of Persia was ruled by Shah Rukh, 4th son of Timur, with a reign of splendor and many successful campaigns against the Turkoman Dynasty of the Black Sheep to the northwest. The western part of Persia fell to the Black Sheep in 1408, however, and they dominated their rivals, the White Sheep Turks, who had been set up against them in Anatolia by Timur. Pushed on the west by the Ottoman Sultanate the people of the White Sheep re-grouped in 1467 and vanquished their "Black Sheep cousins" on the eastern border, taking essentially all of Persia and challenging the expiring Timurids in lower central Asia. (Ref. 5) Their leader was Uzun Hasan.

ASIA MINOR: ANATOLIA

TURKEY

Early on in the century Byzantine was confined to Constantinople across the straits, while the Ottomans held almost the entire peninsula. After their defeat at Ankara by Timur, however, the Ottoman Empire under Bayezid I, shrunk, as Timur simply set up several Anatolian emirs, establishing the Emirates of Kastamuni, Karaman and the White Sheep, among other lesser ones. (Ref. 6, 7) The sons of Bayezid I fought each other for a decade, so the reconstruction of the Ottoman state fell to Mehemmed I (1413-21) and his son Murad II (1421-51), culminating in the reign of Mehemmed II (1451-81). After capturing Constantinople in 1453 the Ottomans had established a true empire, contemporary with the Habsburg. The Turks used improved cannons, cast on the spot, in the capture of Constantinople, but the craftsmen who made them were Hungarian. Latin Christian gun-makers had achieved a technical lead over all others. (Ref. 8) The Ottoman was the last of the great universal empires of Islam, overlying the Abbasid and Seljuk, with some Mongol influence via the Ilkhanids of Persia. They saw themselves as Ghazis – fighters for Islam against polytheists. (Ref. 9) By the end of the century this sultanate had once again conquered almost the entire peninsula, touching the Kingdom of Georgia on the east bank of the Black Sea and confronting the Emirate of the White Sheep Turks on a line running almost south from there to the Mamluk territory on the eastern Mediterranean coast. At the same time they drove the Genoese out of the Black Sea, occupying their trading posts in the Crimea, particularly Kaffa (1479). (Ref. 10, 11)

The Ottoman armies were made up of three elements: Moslem cavalrymen, who lived on their estates in winter and joined the sultan for summer campaigns; slave families, which were actually a vast educational establishment for the conversion of Christian boys into champions of Islam; and finally Christian auxiliaries, many Rumanian, under their own princes. It is interesting that some feel that the capture of Constantinople was actually the downfall of the Ottomans, as witness this quotation from Sir Mark Sykes1:

"To the Turks the capture of Constantinople was a crowning mercy and yet a fatal blow. Constantinople had been the tutor and polisher of the Turks.---the markets died away, the culture and civilization fled, the complex finance faded from sight and the Turks had lost their governors and their support. On the other hand, the corruptions of Byzantine remained, the bureaucracy, the eunuches, the palace guards, the spies, the bribers, go-betweens,---all these the Ottomans took over and all these survived in luxuriant life. The Turks, in taking Stambul, let slip a treasure and gained a pestilence."

ARMENIA

Armenia had no independent existence at this time but some Armenians settled in the north of Syria around the mountains of Jabal Aqra (Roman-Mount Cassius) where some 2,000 still remain today. Others scattered to Turkey and other adjacent lands. (Ref. 13)

1 [211] TANNAHILL, Reay, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

2 [9] BARTHEL, THOMAS S., "The Talking Boards of Easter Island", Scientific American, 236:116-133, March, 1977.

3 [213] THOMAS, Hugh, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

4 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

5 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

6 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

7 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

8 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

9 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

10 [137] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

11 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

12 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

13 [118] Fay, Howard, "Syria", National Geographic 157: 485-511, Apr. 1980.

1.  As quoted by H. G. Wells (Ref. 12), page 570

The Near East: A.D. 1501 to 1600

THE NEAR EAST

ARABIA AND JORDAN & MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS OF ISRAEL AND LEBANON

Nominally all of this area went from Mamluk control to the Ottoman Turks between 1516 and 1517. Even North Yemen was occupied by the Turks from this century off and on until 1918, but they were able to exercise only nominal sovereignty over the many tribes. (Ref. 1) Portuguese attempts to get a monopoly on the spice trade by seizing Aden on the tip of the Arabian Peninsula and thus prevent the Red Sea-Cairo-Alexandria trade route, were unsuccessful. (Ref. 2)

IRAQ AND SYRIA

It was in Aleppo and Damascus that Selim I defeated the Mamluk troops allowing the Ottoman advance on the Mediterranean coast and into Egypt, so that all of that part of the Near East came under his control. (Ref. 3)

IRAN: PERSIA

As the century opened Persia was a mass of small kinglets, the Timurid Empire having collapsed. By 1502, however, Shah Ismail I united the country, founding the Shi'ite Safavid Dynasty, combining an audacity with a religious appeal to accomplish this feat. This Shi'ite (or Shiah) variation of Islam was not new, but never before had it been the fundamental focus for an entire nation. It has remained the state faith of Iran up to the present time, recognizing no rightful caliphs but Ali and his 12 lineal descendants, and in a sense, representing a split off the orthodox Moslem Sunnites somewhat like the split of the Protestants from the Catholic church in the Christian world. The Persian language became the basic tongue of this new Islamic society. The Safavid soldiers were fanatical in their religion, bursting out of a small territory south of the Caspian Sea and beginning their clash with the Ottoman Selim I by 1514. This pressure on the Turks' rear may have saved Christendom from further Turkish advances, but this violent split of the Moslem sects was one of the three most important setbacks to the Moslems, as a whole. Other factors were the Iberian Crusade against them and the administrative consolidation of Moscovy, which prevented the advance of the Moslem Khanates of the western steppe.

Safavid art in textiles, rugs and books was unparalleled, but the Long Wars against the Turks, extending from 1518 to 1590, weakened the administration which was only partially restored by the advent of Shah Abbas I the Great, a man of broad outlook and strong will, although personally exceptionally cruel. He moved the capital to Isfahan where he built many palaces, mosques, gardens and bridges, to the delight of its 600,000 people. He had 80,000 horses in his cavalry. This shah made peace with the Turks in 1590 in order to deal with the Uzbeks, who had been invading along the Iranian-Central Asian border in Khorasan for many years. Of incidental interest is the fact that about 1562 Anthony Jenkinson of the English Moscovy Company, reached Persia overland through Russia and opened commercial relations between East and West. (Ref. 4, 5, 6, 7)

ASIA MINOR

TURKEY

Selim I, the fanatic Sunnite Ottoman Turk leader, first slaughtered 40,000 of his own subjects who were Shi'ites, then attacked Persia -and conquered Mesopotamia9 along with Syria, Arabia and Egypt. By capturing the high priest of orthodox Mohammedism, the sultans, like Henry VIII, became masters of the church as well as the state. Under Suleiman I (1520-1566) the Ottoman Empire reached its greatest extent and started its long decline. With 25,000,000 people it had twice the population of any European nation except France. The Turks were dominant in their chiefly Moslem empire, but there were also millions of Christians, including Greeks, Serbs, Hungarians, Bulgars, Walalchians and Moldavians. This same area today contains 21 modern nations plus large areas of the United Soviet Socialist Republic's Ukraine, Crimea, Caucasus, Armenia and Georgia. All of those domains were allowed fairly independent rule, but were subject to Constantinople and had to pay annual tribute. The Stamboulyol was a carriage road from present day Istanbul to Belgrade via Sofia, an indication both of the new importance of carriages and the extent of European Islam. (Ref. 8) Suleiman, himself, was a man of gracious manners, temperate and either he or his vizier, Ibrahim Pasha, had sufficient administrative ability to make this reign equal to or greater than that of any ruler of his time. In the early part of his term his direct subjects numbered perhaps only 14,000,000, while Spain had 5,000,000 and England 2,500,000. Continuing wars on the European mainland with the Habsburgs and the wars against Shi'ite Persia debilitated all sides, but Sulei man persisted, taking the remainder of Hungary and actually advancing to the gates of Vienna. A Turkish fleet took Rhodes and was active along the Italian shores, only to be finally chased away by a Genoese fleet under Andrea Dorea. When the Hungarian campaign ended with Ferdinand of Hungary making his country an actual Turkish province in 1540, the Turks returned to Asia Minor and forged on eastward to the Persian border to take Tabriz. Later local rebellions in Hungary caused Suleiman to return there, where he died in 1566, in another siege, leaving his empire in dynastic and religious troubles. His successor, Selim II, was a drunkard. (Ref. 9, 10)

In 1571 the Christian world rejoiced prematurely at the victory of Lepanto, where an Ottoman fleet was defeated by ships of a new Holy League, composed primarily of Spain and Venice. Actually it was at least a century thereafter before any serious alteration in the political balance took place. The entire government administration, including the post of the grand vizier, was filled by a specially trained group of originally Christian boys who were brought up as Moslems and were, in essence, educated slaves. The famed infantry Janissaries were of the same origin. In 1585 the empire supposedly had 40,000 military horses in Asia and 100,000 in Europe. This Turkish cavalry, the Sipahis, long remained superior to anything in Europe, proper. After 1585, however, the empire did decline due to the degeneracy of the sultans, perhaps augmented by syphilis in the royal family and added to by the growth of corruption and harem influence, the emergence of governing cliques of Jews, Greeks and others and the inevitable decline of the Janissary corps. There was rising taxation and yet a decrease in the treasury. (Ref. 11) At its peak the Ottoman civilization had an agriculture and science as good as their contemporaries in the west; it was the merchants that were not as advanced. Constantinople, with a population of approximately 700,000, got sheep from the Balkans and grain from Egypt and the Black Sea, which had become the Ottoman's private property. Even so, it took harsh management by the sultan's government to prevent shortages and great famines. (Ref. 12)

The people of Asia Minor were gentle and generally kind, except in war, when they could be brutal. They had fine personal courage and stamina. While there was much bribery of officials, in general law and order was well maintained. Polygamy, concubinage and homosexuality were all common. Social life was unisexual, with the women remaining in the harems. Popular education was neglected but there were many excellent poets and artistic abilities were manifested in painted tiles ana rugs and the construction of mosques. Up through this century, the oldest son of the royal family, on inheriting the throne, would have all his brothers strangled to remove all threats to his position. In accord with this, at the end of the century Mehmert III strangled 19 brothers and 7 of his father's pregnant concubines, as he assumed the throne. Toynbee (Ref. 13) feels that the Ottomans supplied a Universal State for the Orthodox Christian Society, which they were unable to supply for themselves. The idea is at least unique. (Ref. 14, 15, 16)

The two major opponents of the Ottomans in the last of this 16th century were the Austrians and the Turcoman Confederation, remnants of the Uzbeks, in the region around Lake Van. Concerning the first, although the Turks won initial victories, they faced disciplined, infantry gunfire with new European equipment and in the end were defeated.

ARMENIA

Armenia did not exist, as such, at this time. Both the basic Armenian territory and lesser Armenia in Cilicia were all under Turkish control, with the Armenian people pretty well scattered. Along with Jews, the dispersed Armenians became the basic merchants throughout the Middle East. They eventually colonized-the whole of Persia, working out from their base in Jula, a vast suburb of Isfahan, where Shah Abbas the Great had initially confined them in this century. They were also active in Malta at this time. (Ref. 17)

1 [82] GROVE, NOEL, "North Yemen", National Geographic 156: 244, Aug. 1979.

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

4 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

5 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

6 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

7 [135] MAZOUR, ANATOLE G., Russia, Tsarist and Communist. (D. Van Nostrand Co., Inc. Princeton, New Jersey 1963).

8 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

9 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

10 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

11 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

12 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

13 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

14 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

15 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

16 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

17 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982)

The Near East: A.D. 1601 to 1700

THE NEAR EAST

THE ARABIAN PENINSULA, THE MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS, & IRAQ AND SYRIA

The Turkish Ottomans continued their rule over almost all of this area. Some Europeans came back from the East Indies to settle in Mocha and Jiddah on the Arabian Red Sea coast, but otherwise there was little change on the peninsula. Intermittent warfare was waged with the Safavid Dynasty of Persia, but trade across the region continued. There was tremendous profit in spices and war was not to interfere with that. 3,000 tons of spices bought in the East Indies for the equivalent of $227,603 could be sold for $1,972,920 at Aleppa, Syria. (Ref. 1)

IRAN

Rejuvenated under Shah Abbas I, the Safavid dynasty wrested Baghdad and the Armenian border provinces away from the Turks, and there were some periods of tranquility, with progress in the arts and crafts. Beautiful, strong horses were plentiful and some were moved in caravans of 1,000 at a time. They were reserved for warfare or treated as luxuries with harnesses of silver, gold, and precious stones. Rather than use them for communication, human runners called “chatirs” were utilized. These runners were specially trained for the job from childhood and they were often of the road for 30 to 40 hours at a time. (Ref. 2)

The Shia fanaticism faded somewhat, at least in the court, and a lasting peace was finally concluded with the Ottomans in 1639. When Abbas’ grandson Shah Safi came to the throne, however he began to distinguish himself with wholesale executions. It was the beginning of “harem rule” in Persia, initiating a period of rapid decline. The Turks re-won Baghdad and the Cossacks raided on the Caucasus front.

The customs and dress of the ordinary Persians changed little over the centuries. Braudel (Ref. 3) quotes Chardin, after living 10 years in Persia, in 1686:

“I have seen Tamerlane’s costume, which is kept in the treasury of Ispahan and it is cut exactly like the clothes worn here today, without any different—dress in the East is not subject to fashion…”1

The same might be said of their cities. In spite of some degree of culture manifested in advanced arts and crafts, the streets of Ispahan remained without any type of paving, dirty in the summer and muddy in winter. Dead animals, blood from butchered ones, and human excrement increased the filth. An Italian visitor at the end of the century wrote that the humblest house in Palermo was better than the best in Ispahan. (Ref. 5)

ASIA MINOR

TURKEY

Constantinople, with 700,000 people, was larger than any city in Europe and needed all the Balkan sheep, Egyptian rice, beans, and corn, Black Sea grain and wood, and Anatolian oxen, camels, and horses to support it. It required all empire manpower as well as Russian slaves brought in to the salve market of Besistan. (Ref. 6) The sultan himself had 5,000 servants. After Suleiman I (in the last century) the sultans did not marry, basically to keep official wives from meddling in the state and the sultan’s mother became the ruler of the harem. The harem women were technically slaves and as Moslem women could not be enslaved, all these women were foreigners – Russians, Circassians, Venetians, Greeks, and especially women from the Caucasus, where there were many blue-eyed beauties. Originally the eunuchs were white and they came also chiefly from the Caucasus, but at the beginning of this century blacks were used. Since castration was also against Moslem law, these black boys were castrated by Coptic Christians near Aswan as they were brought up from deeper Africa. In theory, these eunuchs, too, were slaves, but they often gained great power because of their proximity to the sultan. As weak, sexually depleted sultans appeared, the Grand Vizier and the Chief of the Black Eunuchs, the “Aga of the women” became the real power in the empire. (Ref. 7) At the beginning of the century the new Sultan Ahmed I refused to strangle his brothers, as had been the custom, and simply locked them up in “the cage”, cut off from the rest of the world. Thereafter, occasionally when a sultan died without male issue, one of the brothers would be brought out of the cage to the throne, knowing nothing. Then the grand vizier would rule.

After signing a peace treaty with Austria in 1606, the Turks fought with Persia and lost Azerbaijan and Georgia. There was a long war with Venice (1645-1660) occasioned by Turkish designs on Crete and again the Ottomans lost, perhaps because of outdated weaponry. A Portuguese ship which was attacked by a Turkish galley in 1603 reported that it was “covered with arrows, up to the topmast.”2 All through this century, the Ottomans competed with Venetians for the mercenary services of Christian infantrymen of the western Balkans. (Ref. 8) Only in cavalry did Turkey seem to have an advantage. The empire had 40,000 horses in Asia and 100,000 in Europe, while hostile Persia had about 80,000. (Ref. 9) It is probable that the loss of Ottoman manpower and money in their 16th century military excursions, plus the effect of inflation after 1584 and the continuing rising population with a shrinking economy, produced an internal crisis in the early decades of this 17th century. (Ref. 10)

With the empire near collapse, a temporary restoration of power was promoted by the Albanian grand vizier, Muhammad Korprulu, his son Ahmed, and his brother-in-law Kara Mustapha, covering the period from 1656 to 1683. During that interval, in response to a Hungarian appeal for aid against the Emperor Leopold, Kara Mustapha again took an army of over 200,000 to the walls of Vienna. When the attack finally failed due to a coalition of Bavarians, Saxons, and Poles, led by John III Sobieski, Kara was strangled on order of the sultan and after this the empire began again to disintegrate, as both Buda and Belgrade fell. Kara’s fate was typical of the tenuous power of the grand viziers in the last of the century. Between 1683 and 1701 some 12 of these came and went. (Ref. 12)

The Treaty of Carlowitz of 1699 by which most of Hungary was surrendered to Austria marked a turning point in the European-Islamic military balance. Other factors also aggravated the crisis in the Ottoman state. New sea routes to the East left the great Ottoman markets stranded in a backwater. (Ref. 13( New World silver swamped the Turkish economy, cutting the value of the standard Ottoman coin to 50% of its former value, precipitating uncontrollable inflation. The Janissaries, who had reached 51,647 in number in this century, were already deteriorating due to the admission of free Moslems to their ranks in the previous century and the carefully trained slave-militia was no more. (Ref. 14)

ARMENIA

Throughout all of the Ottoman activity the Anatolian peninsula was honeycombed with trade routes established by Armenian merchants working out of the original Julfa in what was formerly Armenia and from their transplanted New Julfa out of Ispahan, peopling the monsoon ships, commission agents with dealings in Turkey, Russia, Europe, and the Indian Ocean. From their exile center in New Julfa, some traveled to Patna, Nepal and even Lhasa, Tibet. In each city they could be received and assisted by fellow Armenian merchants. Europe, too, felt the impact of these men. In Moscow they handled raw silk from Persia, From permanent settlements there they traveled overland to Sweden, where they met countrymen coming up with other merchandise from Amsterdam. Poland, Germany, England, France, and Venice were all “invaded” by these businessmen. There was a little Armenian colony at Lwow in Poland, with its own printing plants. The master of regular, trading caravans from Poland to the Ottoman Empire was always an Armenian. (Ref. 15)

1 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

2 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

3 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

4 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

5 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

6 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

7 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

8 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

9 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

10 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

11 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

12 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

13 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

14 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

15 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

1.  As quoted by Braudel (Ref. 4), page 323, from Chardin, Voyage en Perse et aux Indes orientales, 1686, Vol. IV, page 1

2.  Quotation from Braudel (Ref. 11), page 293

The Near East: A.D. 1701 to 1800

THE NEAR EAST

ARABIA AND JORDAN

Differing in language and cultural background, the Arabs of the peninsula began to give the Turkish Ottoman rulers troubles. In the far south Abdul Wahhab (Muhammad ibn Abdulwahhab), a Moslem fundamentalist, called for the re-assertion of the original Moslem truths and soon joined forces with the emir, Muhammad ibn Saud, to conquer central Arabia as the Wahhabi Empire, a precursor of present day Saudi Arabia. (Ref. 1) This empire combined brigandage and pillage with preaching.

Until 1720 the English and Dutch East India Companies had to go to Mocha, Yemen, for coffee beans, but in that year the Dutch discovered that they could get coffee in Java and then Ceylon, while the English found it could be grown in the West Indies. (Ref. 2)

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS & IRAQ AND SYRIA

All these regions remained more or less docile under the Ottoman yoke.

IRAN (PERSIA)

Persia in this century was squeezed between an aggressive group of Afghans in the east, the Turkish Ottomans in the west and the Russians in the north. It is of interest that in spite of political diff iculties, trade apparently continued across the involved area. A document of 1708 says that camels carried loads of from 1,000 to 1,500 pounds between Tabriz and Istanbul. (Ref. 3) In 1722 the Afghan Mahmud defeated a central Persian army and made himself shah. He later went mad and instituted a reign of terror, massacring all Persian nobles and princes and many others. Russia and Turkey made an agreement to dismember Persia, but this plot was foiled by Nadir Kuli, another powerful chief of the Afshar tribe of Khorosan (part of Turkistan) by first def eating the Afghans that were in Persia and later defeating the Turks. In the end the Russians actually helped in this defeat of the Turks. In 1732 Abbas III, the last of the Safavid Dynasty, became the Persian Shah while still an infant, with Nadir still effectively in control. On the death of Abbas in 1736 Nadir became the shah, on the condition that the Persians renounce the Shi'a heresy. As a Turk by race, Nadir Shah was a Sunnite, but he was never able to make this orthodoxy acceptable to the people.

Forty thousand northern Persians died in an earthquake in 1755. Intermittent wars, rebellions and assassinations continued until the end of the century. Aga Mohammed founded the Kajar (Qajar) Dynasty, but probably because of his brutal, avarice nature, he was assassinated within three years. In 1800 the British East India Company concluded a political and commercial treaty in which the British agreed to supply arms and money in the event of an attack by Afghanistan or France. (Ref. 4, 5)

ASIA MINOR

TURKEY

In spite of their weaknesses, or perhaps because of them, in November of 1710 the Ottoman Empire declared war on Russia, marching north from their secondary capital of Adrianople in Serbia, to be joined at the mouth of the Danube by Tatar cavalry, making a total of 200,000 men. (Ref. 6) In this instance the Russians under Peter the Great were overwhelmed and the czar had to buy his way out by the Treaty of Pruth (1711), in which Russia again gave up Azov. But throughout this century Turkey fought on the defensive against Persia and the Balkan groups, as well as having further wars with Russia. Substantial defeats between 1714 and 1718 finally stimulated the Turks to attempt to train troops in the European fashion, but this only led to a successful mutiny by the Janissaries, in 1730. (Ref. 7) In the end Russia gained great territorial areas around the Black Sea and in the eastern Balkans and the Russians called Turkey the "sick man of Europe".

The Turks were at war for 41 of the 109 years between the siege of Vienna in 1683 and 1792, which was the end of the second Russo-Turkish war, involving Catherine 11 and the Treaty of Jassy. (Ref. 8) They progressively lost Hungary, the Banat (part of present Yugoslavia and Romania), Transylvania and Bukovina (west Ukraine and northeastern Romania), as well as the north shore of the Black Sea, including the Crimea. The real breakdown occurred in the 1760s when, because of Russian policies in Poland many Poles fled to Turkey, with the Russian troops right behind them. The Turkish Porte, backed by France, declared war, which became known as the First War of Catherine. The French involvement in the declining Ottoman Empire was imperialism disguised as friendship and Turkey became the first French protectorate. (Ref. 9) The Russian fleet in that war was officered by the British, who came from the Baltic to the Turkish coast, while the Russian infantry attacked by land. That war ended by the Treaty of Kuchuk Kainarji, only when Russia developed internal troubles with the revolt of Pugachev, of which we shall hear more later. But Russia obtained the right of free navigation in Turkish waters and many other concessions. The Second War of Catharine developed in 1787 as a result of Turkish intrigues with the Crimean Tatars.

As their military power declined the Ottomans had to rely more on conference and diplomacy to maintain their prestige and in this capacity the Phanariots rose to power. That was a Greek-Christian group, who had been living in a ghetto in a corner of Stamboul, where the Moslems had allowed a center of Orthodox Christianity to remain under the control of the patriarch. They became very powerful in the government and probably had visions of establishing a new Greek-Orthodox domain through the framework of the Ottoman Empire. Phanariot families controlled the Patriarchate of Constantinople and extended its jurisdiction over the formerly independent Serbian and Bulgarian churches. Istanbul had narrow, dirty streets and houses were usually of only one story, built of wood and bricks and were white-washed. Fire often did great damage. (Ref. 10)

ARMENIA

Although the geographical area of Armenia was still controlled by Ottomans and the Armenian people were dispersed widely, many of the Armenian merchants and financiers played important parts in Constantinople and other Turkish cities. Some Armenian merchants traveled as far as Sining on the Chinese frontier to trade silver for gold, a very profitable operation at that time. Even Lhasa in Tibet and any number of cities of India were common "ports of call" for these business men. (Ref. 11) From the old Armenian homeland, itself, cantaloupe was taken to Europe. (Ref. 12)

1 [6] AZZI, ROBERT, "Saudi Arabia: The Kingdom and its Power", National Geographic 158:286, Sept., 1980.

2 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

3 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

4 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

5 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

6 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

7 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

8 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

9 [74] GRAMONT, SANCHE DE, The French, Portrait of a People. (G.E. Putnam 's Sons~ New York, 1969).

10 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

11 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

12 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

The Near East: A.D. 1801 to 1900

THE NEAR EAST

The first cholera epidemic of the 1820s, coming out of India, went to Mesopotamia, Iran, Syria, Asia Minor and the Caspian shores. It was stopped only by a very severe winter in 1824. The next epidemic of the same disease occurred in the 1,830s and was established at Mecca by 1831. Thereafter epidemics of cholera always followed the Moslem pilgrimages to Mecca until 1912. There were approximately 40 such epidemics in the Near East. (Ref. 1)

ARABIA AND JORDAN

Nationalist opposition to Turkish rule was aroused by a revival of the Wahabi movement, which was a reform within Islam. Its cause was strengthened by the adherence of the founder of the present ruling f amily of Saudi Arabia, into whose hands much of Arabia fell. Expansion of this Saudi kingdom was temporarily halted by the Ottoman Empire, but just after the turn of the new century in 1,902, Abdulaziz captured Rijadh and reinstated the al Sauds to leadership, paving the way to unification.

Hejaz on the eastern shore of the Red Sea had Egyptian occupation from 1,811 to 1,840, then local rulers, the sharifs of Mecca, under Ottoman sovereignty until the next century. Bahrain, in the Persian Gulf, remained an independent sheikdom under the Al Khalifa family, but had British protection after 1,820. Aden, at the southwest tip of the peninsula, was annexed by British from India for use as a coaling station in 1,83~ and following this British influence in the area gradually increased. Kuwait, at the head of the Persian Gulf, was an autonomous sheikdom under the al Sabah family, with the Ottomans still claiming sovereignty until the British took it under formal protection after 1,899. Jordan remained passively under Turkish rule. (Ref. 2, 3)

MEDITERRANEAN COASTAL AREAS

A new colonization of the Palestine area from Europe began about 1,870. Although Lebanon was under Ottoman control, this area was permitted autonomy and powerful families rose periodically to rule. In one particular mountainous area lived the Druses, an off-brand Islamic sect who were fierce fighters and haters of Christians. In 1,841 and again in 1,860 they came down out of the mountains to massacre the Christian Maronites. Pressure from European powers had forced the Ottomans to grant still greater independence to "Great Lebanon", as it was then called. An American university was established in Beirut in 1,866. Printing had not attained significance in the Near East until this century, but now western books began to be translated into Turkish, Arabic and Persian.

IRAQ AND SYRIA

These two areas remained mainstays of the Ottoman Empire. Ibrahim Pasha, from Egypt, seized Syria from the Turks in 1,832 and 1,833, but later had to withdraw under European pressure. Some of the Druses also lived in Syria and although the massacres were in Lebanon they threw all Syria into an uproar.

IRAN: PERSIA

In Iran the Kajars (Qajars) continued as rulers throughout the century initiating a disastrous foreign and military policy, so that inroads were constantly made by western powers. Between 1,804 and 1,827 Russia defeated Iran in three wars, annexing Georgia and Azerbaijan. Iran's part of Afghanistan was also lost with the Treaty of Turkamanchai in 1,828 as Russia took over the entire foreign trade control and gradually thereafter gained control of the northern districts of Iran. The wild horsemen of Iran and Turkistan were no longer a match for armies equipped by European or even Chinese weapons. The British even fought a short Persian war in 1,856, but the Kajar Dynasty was not seriously challenged on that occasion.

Of political impact in this century were the three tribes of the Bakhtiyarl living in the central Zagros mountains and the adjacent northeast Khuzistan plain, in an area of approximately 20,000 square miles. This was and is a highly organized group, with leaders arranged in pyramidal f ashion through the khans and finally at the top, the Ilkhani. Nasir al-Din Shah of the central Persian government conferred the title of Ilkhani by imperial decree. The holder of that title benef ited greatly in wealth and prestige and in return saw that his people paid taxes and homage to the central government. But at the end of the century there was considerable squabbling and interchange of the position of Ilkhani between two families of the Bakhtiyarl. Finally it was agreedj with support of Nasir al-Din Shah and the British that both families should be honored, one with the Ilkhani and one with an assistant Ilkhani to be called the "ilbigi". After the turn of the century, in the Persian revolution, the Bakhtiyarl used force against the shah, himself, although they still also quarreled among themselves1 (Ref. 4, 5)

ASIA MINOR

TURKEY

The Turkish Empire was kept alive artificially during this century by Great Britain, France, Germany and Hungary as a bulwark against Russian advances to the straits. A series of weak sultans were kept on the throne, the last being Abdul Hamid II (1,876- 1,909). Russia gained more Turkish territory between 1,806 and 1,812. In 1,818 the Turks had to put down temporarily the Wahabi Empire in Arabia by an expedition from, and with the help of, Egypt and then fight a similar revolt in Syria. Greece declared its independence in 1,821 and won it; the Phanariots were overthrown and the Turks doubted the loyalty of all Greeks, thereafter. The Janissaries were abolished in 1,826 because they were beginning to control even the viziers and the sultans. Nicholas I of Russia gained Georgia and the principal mouth of the Danube in still another Turkish war, terminated in 1,829 by the Treaty of Adrianople. Related to this, at a second conference in London, Greece was formally given its independence. Reforms in government were initiated by Mahmud II and in 1,839 even Christians and Jews were granted formal equality with Muslims.

The Crimean War (1,854-56) was still another one fought by Turkey against Russia, but that time Turkey had western allies and Russia lost. Even so, in the Battle of Sinope in the Black Sea, new types of shells fired by the Russians completely destroyed the wooden fleet of the Turks, bringing two results - the realization by western powers that new armor was needed for warships and the bringing of Britain into the war to protect Constantinople. (Ref. 7) The campaign was a tragic one for the British, who lost ten times as many soldiers from dysentery as from Russian arms. It also showed up the deficiencies of traditional methods of supply, leading to a modernization of methods of management of armed forces. The Russians could not supply their forces adequately overland across the steppe, even though they had the largest land army in Europe. (Ref. 8) The Russians came back again in 1,877-78 in the Russo-Turkish War and this time the Turks were about to lose their entire empire. Actually the sultan had never really recovered from the Crimean War, because of the large public debt owed the Europeans for railroad construction, etc., and the formal guarantees of liberties forced by those allies. After that second war, the western allies met at the Congress of Berlin and forced Russia to give up much of its gains, but even then Turkey was left with only a portion of its former territory on the European side of the straits and much of that was still disputed by Russia. The bankruptcy of Turkey focused the need for revision of archaic and decadent institutions and led eventually to the revolution of the Young Turks in 1,908.

In this century Akif Pasha reformulated the Turkish language, developing a simpler vocabulary and style for Turkish prose and since then literary Turkish has been based on this work. (Ref. 9, 10, 11)

ARMENIA

Most of Armenia was still included as part of the Turkish Empire, but eastern Armenia, as we have seen, had been constantly disputed between Turkey and Persia for centuries. In 1,828 Russia acquired the region of present day Armenian Soviet Socialist Republic, from Persia. After the year 1,894, in the remainder of old Armenia, the Turk Abdul-Hamid II started a systematic plan for the extermination of the Armenian people.

1 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

2 [6] AZZI, ROBERT, "Saudi Arabia: The Kingdom and its Power", National Geographic 158:286, Sept., 1980.

3 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

4 [70] GARTHWAITE, G.R., "The Bakhtiyari Tribe: Its Organization and Role in Iran". National Geographic Societv Research Reports Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 257-266. (National Geographic Society Publications, 1980).

5 [132] MASON, RONAL J., "The Paleo-Indian Tradition in Eastern North America", Current Anthropology 3, No. 33: 227-252, 1962.

6 [70] GARTHWAITE, G.R., "The Bakhtiyari Tribe: Its Organization and Role in Iran". National Geographic Societv Research Reports Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 257-266. (National Geographic Society Publications, 1980).

7 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

8 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

9 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

10 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

11 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

1.  Much later in the 20th century, Mohammed Riza Shah's 2nd wife was a Bakhtiyari princess. (Ref. 6)

Geographical Presentation of The Pacific

The Pacific Ocean makes up one-half of the globe on which we live and if we exclude Australia, the total amount of land existing as islands in this massive amount of water is almost infinitesimal. Yet many of these tiny islands are of great interest because of the continuing controversies about the origin of their people and method of settlement. It has been impossible to show the entire Pacific on a diagrammatic map on the scale we have selected, so the large map on the second page ahead shows only essentially the south Pacific and omits the far eastern and western expanses, even then. The chief components of this geographical area will be outlined below.

AUSTRALIA AND THE PACIFIC ISLANDS

Because of the lack of space on the next page map, an additional, same scale drawing of Australia is shown below. After one records what little is known about the pre-history of this continent, as will be noted in the text, no more information is available until the 16th century C.E. when Europeans first visited the land.

The islands of the Pacific are usually divided into three groups. In the western side of the ocean, but north of the equator are the various groups of tiny islands, chiefly of coral origin, which are known collectively as Micronesia. Wake Island, the Marianas and the Caroline are examples of this group. Still in the western Pacific but south of the equator is Melanesia, so called because of the dark skins and Negroid features of the inhabitants. The Solomons, Hebrides and New Caledonia are examples of these basically volcanic islands. Finally, in the eastern half of the Pacific there is the so-called Polynesian triangle with the Hawaiian Islands at the apex, New Zealand in the southwest corner and Easter Island at the southeast point. One must realize that, excluding New Zealand, making any dot visible to the naked eye on any large scale map, makes the land far out of proportion. In correct perspective, they should be only microscopic points.

Image not Finished

 Map 1.1: Australia

Image not Finished

 Map 1.2: The Pacific

The Pacific: 5000 to 3000 B.C.

THE PACIFIC

About 4,000 B.C. seas rose to their present level and the dingo was introduced to Australia perhaps by boat. The Australian small tool tradition, in archaeological terms, appeared on that continent. Mankind was in the Soloman Islands in Melanesia by about 3,000 B.C. (Ref. 1)1

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

1 The arguments go on about the origin and route of settlement of the Polynesian islands. Sinoto (Ref.300) has recently excavated an ancient sailing canoe on Huahine in the Society Islands group, and reports that this dates to 3000 B.C. His conclusion that this indicates that ancient mariners sailed from Asia to these islands is difficult to verify from his paper. He says that linguists are able to trace language roots of early Polynesian sailors back to a tongue spoken in Southeast Asia 5,000 years ago and that this is strongly supported by archaeological evidence of west to east movement. The actual "evidence" is not detailed. There is little doubt but what the Polynesian ancestors came from Southeast Asia, but their route to the eastern Pacific and the time schedule is still debatable. There is more about this argument in the main outline in the 4th century C.E. and after.

The Pacific: 1000 to 700 B.C.

THE PACIFIC

As mentioned in the last chapter, Fell (Ref. 1) writes that western Pacific languages were greatly influenced by Libyan sailors as they helped the Egyptians mine gold in Sumatra. Fell actually used the term "Polynesian" when he probably should have used "Melanesian" or "Micronesian" where Neolithic cultures were known to have flourished at that time. Furthermore, it must be noted that this whole idea lacks confirmation by any other source material available to the author. While we are on controversial ground, it seems appropriate to introduce the theories of Thor Heyerdahl concerning the entire Pacific region. Heyerdahl is a bona fide professor of anthropology and biology with his own museum at Oslo, with some following on the continent, but whose work has not been whole-heartedly accepted in the United States. Whether this is the result of the frequent suspicion of conservative professionals in any field for those of their numbers who write for public consumption and profit, or not, remains to be determined. The facts remain that he has done several years research in the southern Pacific and presents an enormous amount of material that would be difficult to refute. We therefore present his ideas for serious consideration.

We must start with the realization that the Pacific Ocean covers one-half of the earth's surface and is, itself, a hemi-globe with only infinitesimal amounts of land scattered at great distances as islands across its vast expanse. If New Zealand is excluded, the combined surface areas of the Pacific islands would not cover an area half as large as New York State. Micronesia is that group of coral atolls barely rising above the ocean surface and in total surface area less than that of Long Island and which is located east of Asia and north of the equator but in an ocean area equating the total width of the Atlantic. South of Micronesia and the equator is Papua-Melanesia, a similarly wide water area beginning where the Indonesian archipelago ends and stretching 4,000 miles from western New Guinea to eastern Fiji. These are large, high islands of continental type, forming almost an uninterrupted bridge eastward, leaving only Fiji as an oceanic group distinct from the rest. East of both Micronesia and Melanesia, running both above and below the equator, lies Polynesia, a group of islands and atolls lying in a triangle with Hawaii at the north, New Zealand in the south and Easter Island in the east.

The settling of Papua-Melanesia by Stone Age people, travelling almost by foot over land bridges in prehistoric times (See The Pacific: Beginning to 8000 B.C.) has never been disputed. Except perhaps for Fiji, no navigational problems were encountered. The problem of the settlement of Micronesia is more complicated, although most scholars are agreed that the tribes there represent a mixture of unidentified people with later intruders from both Melanesian and Polynesian areas. Winds and ocean currents would favor overseas drifts from both of these areas.

The settling of Polynesia is still under controversy. The classical concept, still propounded in most histories, is that the Polynesian islands were uninhabited until fairly recent times (i.e. A.D. 600 to 1,000) when the people spread by outrigger canoes from Melanesia and Southeast Asia. But Heyerdahl and others have quite convincingly demonstrated two fallacies in this concept. First of all, there is now archeological evidence that the Polynesian islands were occupied long before the true Polynesians (as we known them today) ever appeared, and secondly it can be shown that it was impossible to sail or canoe eastward from Asia in the southern Pacific to the eastern Pacific until the time of very modern sailing ships. Even the great Spanish vessels of Mendana and others in the 16th century of the Christian Era could not sail directly east from Melanesia and Micronesia, because of the very strong westward currents. After arriving in the west Pacific they always re- turned home to Europe by going on west across the Indian Ocean and around the southern tip of Africa. The only possible sea route from Indonesia to America by primitive craft was north up along Japan on the Urdaneta Route to between the Aleutian islands and Hawaii to the coast of North America. All of Polynesia can be easily reached, on the other hand, from America, even by primitive rafts. This latter fact has been demonstrated by Heyerdahl with his Kon Tiki raft trip from Ecuador westward across the Pacific. The essence of Heyerdahl's theories is that the original people of the eastern Pacific islands came from the ancient civilizations of Ecuador, Peru and perhaps Mexico and were not the people we think of today as Polynesians. The latter came much later. The situation is best exemplified by studies of the people, archeology and history of Easter Island. An old tradition of that island insists that the island's earliest ancestors came from a vast desert land to the east and that the sailing time from the original home-land was sixty days. Some of the early people allegedly were of white skin and of these some had red hair, while others were dark-skinned with dark hair. Both of these types were described by early European visitors to the island, such as the Dutch Roggeveen, in 1722. We cannot here detail all the data which has been presented as evidence, but Heyerdahl is quite convincing in his theory that Easter Island and others of the Polynesian group were early populated by pre-Inca sailors from South America, particularly from the Tiahuanaco civilization which would have been the closest to Easter Island. It must be emphasized, however, that to make this assumption reasonable, one must also accept the idea that the Tiahuanaco civilization (and others in early America) might have been instigated by Mediterranean voyagers. Early grave and mummy studies in the Tiahuanaco area of the 19th century C.E. have confirmed that some were definitely different from typical Amerindians. Particularly it has been noted that the hair was not that of Amerindians, but fine in texture. In pre-Inca times, Peru probably had a mixed population and from there such a mixed group could easily have reached Polynesia in one or more migration waves.

This entire concept is strengthened by the writings of the eminent French archeologist, Frederic Andre Engel, who has worked for over twenty years in Peru and who says that the Galapagos group and Easter Island must have played a part in early South American history since pre-Columbian pottery has been found on the Galapagos and it is not difficult to compare the great statues of certain South American states and those of Easter Island and the polyhedral walls of Cuzco, Peru and those of the Marquesas islands of Polynesia. Others also write that permanent settlements were made between 1,000 and 500 B.C. in Polynesia, from whatever source. (Ref. 2, 3, 4)

1 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

2 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

3 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

4 [134] MAY, CHARLES Paul, Oceania: Polynesia, Melanesia, Micronesia. (Thomas Nelson, Inc., Nashville, Tenn. 1973).

The Pacific: 600 to 501 B.C.

THE PACIFIC

Most classical histories record that this and adjacent centuries saw continued spread of people from Indonesia through Melanesia and Micronesia eastward into Polynesia but as we have indicated in previous chapters this was probably impossible with the sea technology available at that time because of the strong westward ocean currents. Of interest in this regard is Braudel's (Ref. 1, page 201) statement that even in 1696 a galleon's trip from Manila to Acapulco took six or seven months and resulted in extreme difficulties in the feeding of the crew. Again, we should reiterate that the Polynesians are not genetically related to either Melanesians or Micronesians and their cultural habits and physical characteristics are entirely different. In contrast, it has been found that the Indians of the northwest American coast and coastal islands at the eastern end of the Japan current across the far northern Pacific used the same adzes that were used centuries before in the northern Philippines. Captain Cook found these also in Tahiti and other Polynesian islands, while others of the l9th century found that the adz-handle and the method of securing the blade to the wooden handle were exactly the same among the Polynesians as among the northwest American Indians. 20th century anthropologists have confirmed these observations and added many other similarities. The inference regarding the origin of the Polynesians is clear. The only contact that the true Polynesians had with the Micronesians was through the Fiji Islands on the border of the two groups of islands where it seems that the pig and the chicken spread from west to east, in a limited area. One must realize, however, that these true, present day Polynesians did not spread down the east Pacific from the North American coastal islands until a much later period than this 6th century B.C. and in the meantime other peoples did inhabit at least many of these islands. The source of these aborigines remains somewhat uncertain, although, as detailed elsewhere in this manuscript, it is possible that they came from Central and/or South America. (Ref. 2)

1 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

2 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

The Pacific: 300 to 201 B.C.

THE PACIFIC

We now come to a most interesting new concept concerning the early inhabitants of the Pacific, based on Fell's interpretation of the cave inscriptions of New Guinea mentioned just above. These inscriptions include star maps, navigation diagrams and even calculations attributed to Eratosthenes. Furthermore, in far flung Polynesian islands there are legends of a great sailor named Maui, who "fished up new lands from the sea". Heyerdahl, although making no mention of Fell's work, has attempted to show, and quite convincingly, that no direct eastward sailing from Indonesia and Melanesia was possible, but that people could reach the eastern Pacific islands by sailing up the Japanese current to or near the coast of North America and then back into the eastern Pacific via currents and winds that still prevail. Perhaps, then, both Fell's and Heyerdahl's theories are compatible in some degree. Fell claims to have found in southwestern North America Maui's charts of the Hawaiian Islands showing Gawi (Kaui), Uwahu (Oahu), Mawi Zara (Maui) and what he called the "Great Volcanic Island" (Hawaii). The relative positions of these islands are the same as those given on William Bligh's map of 1779, except that the relatively large size of Hawaii was not recognized by Maui, indicating that he probably only sighted it from a distance and did not really explore it. On Maui's chart the entire island group is called hawa and the islands are placed in correct relationship to the western coast of North America on some additional larger maps showing the entire continent.

Professor Raymond A. Dar, distinguished South African anthropologist, and a group from the University of Alabama led by Professor Albert E. Casey, have given some support to Fell's hypothesis in that they have found skull measurements of the ancient people of New Zealand (i.e. before the advent of true Polynesians) indicate links with both North Africans, Iberians and Zuni Arizona Indians, as well as some tribes in New England and Northeastern Canada. The inhabitants of New Zealand prior to the arrival of the Polynesians in a much later century, were the Morioris and they were driven to the Chatham Islands when the Maori arrived. These Chatham Islanders had Arabic-Semitic countenances, of ten with large, hooked noses and reddish hair. This information from Heyerdahl is certainly compatible with Fell's Libyan origin concept. Another hypothesis dealing with the possible American origin of the aborigines of the eastern Pacific islands will be given in the next chapter. (Ref. 1, 2)

1 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

2 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

The Pacific: 200 to 101 B.C.

THE PACIFIC

We have intimated previously that Polynesia appears to have been inhabited by some people prior to the true Polynesian migrations of later centuries. Whether these aboriginal dwellers came entirely from prehistoric America or from some other clime is not known with certainty. We are quite certain that Easter Island and perhaps adjacent South Pacific islands, such as the Marquesas, had immigrants from South America, but what about Hawaii? Recently on an helicopter trip to a remote, presently uninhabited part of Kuaui, the most northern of the chief Hawaiian Islands, we landed in what the pilot called the Valley of the Lost Tribe and he described an old Hawaiian legend that had this as the location of the last stand of the aboriginal people against the invading Polynesians. There were remnants of previous terracing in this valley. Whether these originals had come from the Americas or represented Libyans and others coming via the Japanese Current from Indonesia, a possibility suggested by the findings of Fell (See The Pacific: 300 to 201 B.C.), is not known. The later, true Polynesians did not have pottery, but many ancient sherds have been found on Hawaii, apparently left from an earlier people. Heyerdahl's arguments in favor of original settlement from South America, particularly Peru, are impressive. Of first importance is the flora. In Hawaii the husk tomato, Physalis peruviania, called "poha", is an American crop plant native from Mexico to Peru. Cotton, the sweet potato and Hibiscus of Hawaii all point to Peru. The white flowering Hawaiian Argemone is closely related to the Argemone grown in ancient Peru for narcotic and anesthetic properties and was similarly used in Hawaii. We must remember that humans brought almost all the plants to the volcanic and coral Pacific islands, as they were "born" completely bare and only a limited number of plants such as the screw pine, sandalwoods and possibly lauans and breadfruit could have arrived by sea or birds before the advent of man. (Ref. 1, 2) The question of how the sweet potato got to Hawaii and the Marquesas has been debated for a long time. It was once alleged to have been taken there by shipwrecked Spanish crews in 1528, but Dahlgreen of Sweden, after long study, says that there is absolutely no evidence that Hawaii was ever visited by the Spanish prior to Captain Cook's visitations in the l9th century. Some iron implements found by Cook on the islands are thought to be the result of driftage from Japan. The sweet potato is native to both South and Central America and old Hawaiian legends are suggestive of sea contact with America. Legends of the islands also relate that the sweet potato was dried and used for food on long voyages, apparently to other Pacific islands (the Marquesas?). (Ref. 207) There is also a remarkable similarity between the Hawaiian flat-iron type of grinder for poi and the Central American and Mexican corn grinders.

1 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

2 [134] MAY, CHARLES Paul, Oceania: Polynesia, Melanesia, Micronesia. (Thomas Nelson, Inc., Nashville, Tenn. 1973).

The Pacific: 100 B.C. to 0

THE PACIFIC

True Polynesians probably colonized the Hawaiin Islands less than 2,000 years ago but possibly in this first century before Christ. Similarly the Marquesas and Society Islands were possibly reached near the beginning of the Christian era but in the absence of more precise dating we shall postpone further discussion of this debatable issue until the 4th century. As indicated in previous chapters these islands were already inhabited either by an earlier wave across the northern Pacific from the New Guinea region or from America. Potsherds have been excavated in the Marquesas group and on islands near Fiji and they are of a South American not a Melanesian type. The cotton plant (the hybrid 26 chromosome type) from Mexico and Peru spread from the Galapagos Islands to Fiji but no farther.

Shards of pottery have been found on the Galapagos off the South American coast dating to 2,000 years ago, but whether this means a permanent settlement or merely that some ships had taken temporary refuge there is unknown. (Ref. 1, 2)

1 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

2 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

The Pacific: A.D. 301 to 400

THE PACIFIC

Classical histories relate that while Lapita pottery was disappearing in Melanesia, prehistoric Samoans ventured eastward in canoes to settle the Marquesas and from this point, in the next 450 years, the Polynesians took their plants, animals, adzes, fishing gear and ornaments all over the Polynesian world. This traditional view is probably no longer tenable. Except for root vestiges in about 1% of the total vocabulary there are no traces of Polynesian language ties to any region in the west Pacific and by blood typing studies it is apparent that the true Polynesians are related to the aboriginal peoples of America, not to the Melanesians. (Ref. 1) We have chosen this module to discuss the probable migration of the Northwest American Kwakiutl - Haida - Salish people to Hawaii, although the time-frame has not been definitely established and it might have occurred anytime in the early Christian era up to the classical date of A.D. 750, which has been accepted by many for the time of the settlement of Hawaii. As stated on pages 269 and 270, the Canadian coastal Indians and the Polynesians all seem identical physically, and neither of these groups have any relationship to the inhabitants of present day Southeast Asia and/or Indonesia. Genetically blood group B has a maximum occurrence in Indonesia, Melanesia and Micronesia but it is totally absent among pure-blooded Polynesians and North American Indians. The blood sub-groups of the Polynesians also follow those of the aboriginal Americans. These studies have been repeated by several investigators and confirmed by an international work group in 1972.

Superficially the guttural present day languages of the Northwest Indians do not resemble the softer speech of Polynesia, but some linguists have confirmed a relationship of the latter with the Haida language of the central northwest Canadian coast. The houses, mats, fish-hooks, stone adzes, poi pounders, warclubs and in some instances the totem poles are identical, within narrow variations, in the two groups. The legends of these people give further clues. A legendary hero from whose brother the chiefs of the Kwakiutl got their divine descent was called "Kan-e-a-ke-luh"1. Similar pronunciations are used by adjacent tribes, always with the beginning "Kan-e". The legend continues with the story of Kaneakeluh marrying a "woman of the sea" and the two disappearing, leaving the sun to represent them. Tribal memories of Hawaii describe the discovery of their islands by a wandering chief who came from a vast island or mainland in the north called the "lost home of Kane". Kane was the chief Hawaiian god and considered the direct ancestor of the ruling families. While the Kwakiutl claimed descent from the younger brother of Kane. It is felt that the newly arriving Polynesians on Hawaii tended to absorb the belief s and customs of the former inhabitants, rather than exterminating them and that the mixture of the races began at that time. (Ref. 2)1

It has been estimated that in this century stone-masons were at work making giant statutes in the mid-south Pacific on Easter Island. Thor Heyerdahl believe that there is archeological and ethnological evidence that these people had migrated by rafts from a pre-Incan civilization in Peru. We hasten to say that only a few others accept any of this theory, although blood factors in South America and on Easter Island suggest that the people on the island resemble the Americans more than either of these groups resemble Asian Mongoloids and that they have probably received genes from both the East and the West.

Recent archeological excavations and carbon-dating on that island by Heyerdahl and his associates have established three cultural periods with the first, or Early Period, dating from before A.D. 380 to about A.D. 1100. By island tradition the people of this period arrived from the east under King Hotu Matua, after a sixty-day journey on the sea. These "long-ears" people had raised moai or statues and made their homes from stone, although wood was plentiful on the island at that time. They also built totora reed boats identical with those of inland Tiahuanaco waterways and the desert coast region of Peru. What happened to this early culture by about 1100 is unknown, but the subsequent history of this island will be taken up again, then, in a later module.

1 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

2 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

3 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

4 [300] SINSTO, YOSIHIKO H., "The Huahine Excavation: Discovery of an Ancient Polynesian Canoe", Archaeology 36, No.2: 10-15, Mar./Apr. 1983.

5 [309] THE MAKING OF AMERICA: HAWAII, Cartographic Division of National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., Nov. 1983.

1.  Phonetical spelling, as given by Heyerdahl, (Ref. 3), page 177, quoting G.M. Dawson, who lived among these people in the 1880s.

2 Sinoto (Ref.4) says that most authorities deny these theories of Thor Heyerdahl's, which have been put forward in the text. He insists that Polynesia was settled from the west, but he does not seem to consider the possible Japanese current - Canadian Islands - Hawaii at all, and he does not mention anything about blood types, which would seem to prove that the Polynesians did not come through the western Pacific islands. Sinoto gives the route at a much earlier period east from Tonga to Samoa to the Marquesas and shortly thereafter to the Society Islands. As late as November, 1983, the National Geographic Society apparently still subscribes to the idea that the Hawaiian Islands were settled by travelers in double canoes going 2,000 miles northeast from the Marquesas. (Ref.5)

The Pacific: A.D. 701 to 800

THE PACIFIC

At this time and in adjacent centuries, the Pacific Ocean witnessed one of the most remarkable human dispersals of all history. Remote coral atolls and isolated volcanic cones, often separated by hundred of miles of open sea, became sites of human habitation. This occurred by virtue of the Polynesian sea voyages over long distances with their efficient outrigger canoes. Most of the migrations appear to have taken place between A.D. 600 and 1,000. We have previously noted that the spread now appears to have taken place from Hawaii southward, rather than the reverse. Even McNeill (Ref. 1) notes that occasional accidental contact with the Americas and the Asian mainland occurred. The erratic and complex distribution of cultivated plants and domestic animals among the Pacific Islands indicates the range and variety of contacts long before the Europeans arrived in the area. Legend has it that exploring Polynesians even reached the Antarctic ice pack in A.D. 750. Even so, throughout all this period, there was little or no change in Australia, with the aboriginal people existing apparently without significant change, century after century. (Ref. 2, 3)

1McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

2McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

3 [76] GRATTAN, C. HARTLEY, The Southwest Pacific to 1900. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1963).

The Pacific: A.D. 801 to 900

THE PACIFIC

The groups of islands called the Southern Cooks and New Zealand were occupied by Polynesians between 750 and 850. In New Zealand the new arrivals had either lost their Marquesan fauna and flora or those could not withstand the new climate, as only the dog and the native rat survived. Taro, yam and sweet potatoes grew on the northern coastal areas only.

There is little doubt but what all the Pacific island groups were already inhabited when the Polynesians arrived. Early European voyagers were emphatic in stating that they had seen three, clearly distinct people, intermixed. The dominant type had fair to light, copper-colored skin, black hair, almost European features with a slight Mongoloid stamp, ability to grow mustaches and tall stature, usually six feet in height. This is the common norm of the New Zealand Maori, as well as the Hawaiians and the island tribes of the Northwest American coast, as we have previously described. The second type showed some Melanesian affinities, with dark skin, flat, broad noses, thick lips, frizzy hair and shorter stature. They were considered by the islanders to be descendants of the legendary Menehune or Manahune. The third type had unusually fair skin, reddish or brown hair and prominent nose, suggestive of Jewish or Arabic faces. This last type was particularly present in the original inhabitants of New Zealand - the Morioris, who took refuge in the Chatham Islands in this or the preceding century, when the true Polynesian Maori arrived. It is felt that all these three types of people dispersed through the Pacific at different times, possibly by different routes and certainly from different cultures. (Ref. 1) A study of skeletons from the Polynesian Islands, apparently taken from the Museum of Natural History, and published by Sullivan in 1924 (Ref. 2) showed a mixture of four different and distinct racial elements. Two of these were classed as Caucasian types, one as Negroid or Melanesian and the fourth as Negroid with added Mongoloid characteristics. Obviously very little conclusion could be drawn from these studies, except that through the centuries many different people have arrived on these Pacific islands.

1 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

2 [208] SULLIVAN, LOUIS R., "Race Types in Polynesia", American Anthropologist Vol. XXVI, No. 1, 1924.

The Pacific: A.D. 1001 to 1100

THE PACIFIC

In Australia the aborigines still had no settled communities, were sparsely distributed and lived a hunting and gathering life. Although no special information is available about this particular century, it is assumed that the Australoid peoples of Melanesia and Micronesia continued to multiply and spread, with a primitive culture.

The Maoris of New Zealand now had a classical Polynesian society and their legends related to an ancestral arrival from Hawaiki (also called "Hawai'i") and this same concept is widespread in central and southern Polynesia. The names of various chiefs of early Hawaii are duplicated, or nearly so, in the Maori memories. The similarities of Maori physiques and customs to Northwest American Indian groups are amazing. They both used a specialized elbow adze and their large, ocean going canoes were identical, including such details as rudder, row locks, pegs in joining planks and absence of keel. Both used sewing for adding elevated bow and stern pieces and occasionally for adding side planks. At times the double canoe was used by both, the paddles were similar and the method of propulsion by the paddlers exactly the same. Both peoples used three special types of fish-hooks and a grooved tapa or bark-beater of wood or whalebone for manufacturing paper cloth. Neither group had knowledge of the loom until Europeans arrived, but the women made dresses from plants or the inner bark of trees after beating. Captain Jacobsen, who visited the American Northwest coast in the last century, wrote: "Their articles of clothing look almost entirely like those of the New Zealand Maori, in form as well as in fabric and manufacturing method. The similarity is so great that some of the blankets from the two regions, when hung up beside each other, can hardly be distinguished."1 As with the Hawaiians, the Maori houses were also essentially the same as the Kwatiutl-Haida-Savish Indians and their war clubs were identical. (Ref. 1) See also the next module.

1 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

2 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

1.  As quoted by Heyerdahl (Ref. 2, page 171).

The Pacific: A.D. 1101 to 1200

THE PACIFIC

Most of the western Pacific, including Australia, apparently remained much as in previous centuries. On the island of Ponape, formerly called Ascension Island, in Micronesia, there are ancient stone ruins at Nonmatol consisting of walls of great rocks carved into log shapes. These high blocks of basalt had been moved long distances and the work may have some relation to that on Easter Island. Radio-carbon dating shows that the area was occupied as recently as A.D. 1200 but the original inhabitants may have been there centuries earlier. (Ref. 1) (Also see The Pacific: 400 to 301 B.C.)

In the eastern Pacific at Easter Island, it appears that the earliest known platforms (Ahu) known to have been altars for classic giant statues (Moai), were built about A.D 1110 to 1205, although statues of the same type may have been constructed earlier.

The year A.D. 1100 begins the 580 years of the Middle Period of Easter Island history and was initiated with a new invasion of "Short-ear" people, who probably also came from Peru. They introduced the bird-man cult which dominated religious activities throughout this period. In this same era more than 600 giant statues were sculptured from the now naked crater walls of Rano Raraku. Some of these statues reached 46 feet in height and weighed 40 tons.

In the last chapter we discussed the probable migration of Hawaiian Polynesians to the south Pacific. In this same vein, legend has it that in this 12th century a notable Hawaiian chief named Olopana and his wife Lu'ukia left their islands to seek a new home in the south. With the sound changes which distinguish the Maori variety of the Polynesian language from the Hawaiian, these names become Koropanga and Rukutia and, as such, these names occur in Maori legend as having come from Hawaiki. This would tend to give further credence to the concept that Hawaii was the gateway of the present Polynesian population of the eastern Pacific Islands. Samoa, the western corner of Polynesia, became a contact point, acquiring certain Melanesian assets from Fiji. The original occupants of these eastern islands were not carpenters and did not excel in woodcarving art like the historically known Maori-Polynesians and their northern neighbors and probable relatives along the Northwest American coast, but were, rather, expert stone masons like the inhabitants of the barren landscapes of the Andes. (Ref. 2)

1 [134] MAY, CHARLES Paul, Oceania: Polynesia, Melanesia, Micronesia. (Thomas Nelson, Inc., Nashville, Tenn. 1973).

2 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

The Pacific: A.D. 1501 to 1600

THE PACIFIC

Both New Zealand and Australia still remained essentially untouched since prehistoric days. Sailing with the westward Pacific current from Mexico, Alvaro de Saavedra reached the eastern Caroline Islands in Micronesia in January, 1528. Subsequently the Spanish introduced cattle, goats, corn and coffee to those small islands, but with these products went foreign diseases of influenza, measles and perhaps others, which killed thousands of island people. (Ref. 1)

The Spaniards had no sooner crossed the isthmus of Panama and reached the coast of Peru by water than the Inca historians recounted that inhabited islands were to be found some 2 months sailing distance westward in the South Pacific and gave correct sailing directions to some of these, including Easter Island. It was from these reports that Spanish caravels soon set out on two separate voyages which led to the European discovery of the Solomons in Melanesia in 1567 and the Marquesas of Polynesia in 1595. The latter voyage has an interesting story. Alvaro de Mendana was the Peruvian Viceroy's nephew and had been ordered by King Philip II of Spain to leave Callao harbor, Peru with 150 men to convert the Pacific islanders to Christianity. The presence of the islands were known chiefly through Sarmiento de Gamboa, who eventually was a famous chronicler of the Incas and he had learned from them of the inhabited islands far out in the Pacific. Among his writings is the story of a voyage of Tupac Inca, grandfather of the Inca brother kings that the Spaniards encountered. Tupac allegedly had sailed west with an immense number of balsa barges and 20,000 men, returning almost a year later, with much booty and "black people". Such balsa rafts have been found in various parts of the Pacific. The memory of King Tupac Inca is preserved in the traditions of Mangareve Island and even as late as 1825 a Captain Beechey visited that island and drew a picture of 13 Mangarevans sailing a log raft 40 to 50 feet long. The balsa rafts, like reed boats, were "wash-through" craft which could never be filled with water. At any rate, with de Gamboa as navigator, Mendana sailed west to land without difficulty in the Marquesas. (Ref. 2)

None of the European ships mentioned above or the ones that followed for 200 years were ever able to come back east across the Pacific the way they had gone because of the tremendous westward running currents in the equatorial and southern latitudes of that ocean. Those early trans-Pacific ships usually returned to Spain through the Indian Ocean and around the tip of Africa. Incidentally it was Zacatula, using this same westward ocean flow, called the Saavedia current, who sailed straight across to Mindanao in the Philippines in 1527. Braudel (Ref. 3) tells us that in 1590 a Portuguese merchant from Macao, Joao da Gama, crossed the Pacific and landed at Acapulco, but he says nothing about his route and we must assume that the skipper may well have gone north along the Japanese coast to near the Aleutians and then down the American coast. There is no other way for any kind of early vessel. Malay canoes and proas or Chinese and Japanese junks, whether guided or lost in drift, can be readily brought to British Columbia on the Japanese current and if drifting on from there, in another few weeks, will find themselves in Hawaii. (Ref. 4) It was sometime in this or the next century that prolonged strife began on Easter Island and some 300 finished moai (giant statues) were overturned. We shall seek the possible meaning of this in the next module. (Ref. 5)

1 [134] MAY, CHARLES Paul, Oceania: Polynesia, Melanesia, Micronesia. (Thomas Nelson, Inc., Nashville, Tenn. 1973).

2 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

3 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

4 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

4 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

The Pacific: A.D. 1601 to 1700

THE PACIFIC

Pedro Fernandes de Queireos, the Portuguese pilot who continued command of Mendana's expedition into the far Pacific in the previous century, set out again from Peru in 1605 with settlers to establish another colony in the Solomons. He went too far south, passing by Tuamotu and the Society Islands and finally set his settlers ashore in the New Hebrides in Melanesia in 1606. A little later he, himself, mysteriously sailed away again. (Ref. 1)

Luis Vaez de Torres sailed along the southern coast of New Guinea and through what is now called the Torres Strait in about 1606, but thereafter Spain made no more exploratory trips for almost 2 centuries. At the same time, however, the Dutchman Willem Jansz, sailing out of the great base in Java, had discovered Australia, although he thought it to be a southern extension of New Guinea. The climax of Dutch exploration came under Governor-General Van Dieman and his captain, Abel Janszoon Tasman after 1636. They sailed the northwest coast of Australia, discovered and named New Zealand (1642), found the Tonga and Fiji Islands and discovered the south coast of Van Dieman's Island in 1644. (Ref. 2) By the early 1640s the Dutch knew something of the west coast of Australia, which they called New Holland, although they were not sure that it was a continent. (Ref. 3) It has been estimated that the aborigine population of Australia at that time was about 300,000. (Ref. 4)

Jesuit missionaries were sent to Micronesia by Mariana of Austria, Spain's King Philip IV's widow, in 1667 and they renamed Magellan's Ladrones the "Marianas" in the Queen's honor. Meanwhile, in the Carolines, where Spanish sailors had first landed, disease continued to rampage and where 20,000 to 30,000 people had previously lived peacefully, by the end of this century only a few thousand remained. (Ref. 5)

On Easter Island a catastrophe struck in 1680 and all work in the stone quarries, along the roads and on the Ahu was suddenly stopped, never to be resumed. Thousands of obsidian spear heads have been found and the Ahu images were overthrown and masonry walls and old reed houses were torn down or burned and a major population group was nearly annihilated. The victors, who remained, were Polynesians, but they may have arrived quietly some 200 years earlier. (Ref. 6)

1 [134] May, CHARLES Paul, Oceania: Polynesia, Melanesia, Micronesia. (Thomas Nelson, Inc., Nashville, Tenn. 1973).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [76] GRATTAN, C. HARTLEY, The Southwest Pacific to 1900. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1963).

4 [222] TRAGER, James, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

5 [134] May, CHARLES Paul, Oceania: Polynesia, Melanesia, Micronesia. (Thomas Nelson, Inc., Nashville, Tenn. 1973).

6 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

The Pacific: A.D. 1701 to 1800

THE PACIFIC

We have discussed in earlier modules the great difficulties in direct west to east crossings of the Pacific in primitive vessels. Even in 1707 to 1711 Monsieur de Frondad, while sailing without particular difficulty from Port Louis, France down around the tip of South America, up the west coast to Huacho and then across the Pacific to China, then took 6 months to come back across the Pacific to Cape St. Lucas. Ocean currents and winds are not conducive to such trips. European voyages in the Pacific were originally searches for a habitable, southern continent or for a usable northern strait to the orient, both imaginary. But they did reveal an insular New Zealand and a habitable eastern Australia, many attractive islands and a valuable shale industry. (Ref. 1) When the Dutchmen Jacob Roggeveen stumbled on Easter Island in 1722, there were probably 3,000 or 4,000 people on the island, representing a mixed group with some fair-skinned and some dark-skinned, who lit fires before some enormous statues standing in a row. The statues, even then, were old and eroded. The people appeared to be living in near anarchy amid the wreckage of a once high culture and cannibalism was common. Roggeveen, however, was given great quantities of sweet potatoes, which they called by the Peruvian name "Kumara". (Ref. 2, 3) When the Spaniards finally arrived on that island in 1770 they found it to be at exactly the direction and distance f rom Ecuador that had been detailed to their earlier comrades by the Incas some two centuries before. The Spaniards' description of Easter Island included the presence of plantains, chili peppers, sweet potatoes and fowls. The plants were all those known in pre-European Peru and had been present in pre-Inca burials. Of perhaps more importance, they found totora reeds in large bogs of old crater lakes and from these the islanders built houses and boats, furniture, baskets, fish-nets, etc.

These reeds also had been grown in irrigated fields on the coast of Peru and similarly used. Easter Island tradition insists that an early ancestor, Ure1, brought with him the first totora root stocks and planted them in Rano Kao Lake. Captain Cook also visited Easter Island in the late 1770s and the disastrous Hotu-iti war, which finally annihilated most of the people there, must have occurred about 1772 to 1774, just before Cook's arrival. Only a few poor islanders were left and Cook's Tahitian interpreter could understand only a few of their words. (Ref. 4)

In a sense, the first British Empire collapsed in 1783 when the 13 American colonies broke free, but then the second British Empire involved the British dominance of the South Pacific. In this 18th century Oceania belonged to the British and the French. This began before with the voyages of William Dampier, who had twice visited the Indian Ocean coast of New Holland (Australia) between 1681 and 1711. Captain John Byron (grandfather of the poet) took possession of the Falklands in 1765 and Samuel Wallis and Philip Carteret followed with exploration of Tahiti, Pitcairn, New Britain, Philippines, Celebes, etc.

Captain James Cook left England on the first of his three Pacific voyages in 1768, supposedly on a scientific mission at the instance of the Royal Society. Cook circumnavigated New Zealand and came upon the eastern shore of mainland New Holland in April, 1770 and at extreme peril spent 4 months exploring the seaboard inside the Great Barrier Reef. He called this land "New South Wales". Almost simultaneously with Cook's first Pacific trip, Captain Louis Antoine de Bougainville (for whom the flower is named) took possession of the Society Islands of Polynesia for France. He was one of the few explorers who was good to the natives, gaining their conf idence. He introduced turkeys to the islands and may have tried to grow wheat. De Bougainville then sailed on west to the Samoas, New Hebrides and the Solomons. (Ref. 6) When the Europeans arrived in Australia there were some 300,000 aborigines living in about 500 tribal territories. One of their food delicacies was the bogang moth. On New Zealand there were between 100,000 and 250,000 Maoris living a hunting-farming life style. (Ref. 7)1

Cook's second voyage starting in 1773 took him twice deep into the Antarctic Ocean and to many new islands, including the New Hebrides, where he first saw the Melanesians, realizing that they were much different from the Polynesians seen on the other islands. By using citrus fruits, Cook had prevented all scurvy on this trip. His third Pacific trip was to find the much desired Northwest Passage to China through North America, - seeking it from the Pacific side. It was in 1778 on that trip that he discovered the Hawaiian Islands, where he was originally mistaken for a white, fair-haired ancestor god, Rono (Lono), but in 1779, when they found he was not, they killed him. In Hawaiian folklore, the blond god Lono was associated with navigation in boats made of reeds and wickerwork. Throughout Polynesia, Cook was deluged with sweet potatoes and he found various gourds used as water vessels and utensils. (Ref. 9) It should be noted that he originally named the Hawaiian group "The Sandwich Islands" after John Montague, the 4th Earl of Sandwich. (Ref. 10)2

In 1787 the British government decided to send a penal colony (not a settlement colony) to Botany Bay in Australia. The exact number of convicts sent is still in some dispute, but it approximated 700 plus, of which about 150 were women. Actually they skipped Botany Bay and settled in the great harbor area to be named Sydney, after a Lord of that name, and Captain Arthur Phillip set up an autocratic government. (Ref. 13)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

3 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

4 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

5 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

6 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

7 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

8 [302] WARNER, OLIVER (with DR. J.C. BEAGLEHOLE), Captain Cook and the South Pacific. (Cassell, London. American Heritage Publ. Co., Inc., New York, 1963).

9 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

10 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

11 [302] WARNER, OLIVER (with DR. J.C. BEAGLEHOLE), Captain Cook and the South Pacific. (Cassell, London. American Heritage Publ. Co., Inc., New York, 1963).

12 [309] THE MAKING OF AMERICA:HAWAII, Cartographic Division of National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., Nov. 1983.

13 [76] GRATTAN, C. HARTLEY, The Southwest Pacific to 1900. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1963).

1.  "Oro" is the name of an old, important tribe of the Lake Titicaca area in Peru-Bolivia, which based its economy on the totora reeds. (Ref. 5)

1 Captain Cook's first trip was in the 106 foot bark "Endeavour". He actually had two goals, the first being the scientific one to observe the "transit of Venus" in 1769 so that this could be compared with two other places of observation around the globe. Because of a cloud zone around Venus, however, the observation was to no avail. His second goal was given to him sealed and was opened only after completion of the first. It was to sail south to find "the southern continent", theorized to have to be present by geographer Dalrymple, who felt that New Zealand was only a northern peninsula of that hypothetical large continent. On this trip Cook proved that New Zealand consisted of two major islands. The Maori were initially unfriendly, but they could converse with a Tahitian accompanying Cook. Some of the Maori canoes would hold 100 warriors. On the Australian coast the aborigines paid little attention to the white men and just wanted to be left alone. On a stop at Batavia many men were lost from malaria and dysentery although they had been healthy when they arrived in Asia. (Ref.8)

2 Cook's 2nd Pacific voyage (from west to east) was really another search for the "southern continent". He used Harrison's chronometer, a "never-failing guide". On his flagship Cook made the men keep to a strict dietary regime and he had no scurvy, but Lt. Tobias Furneaux, commanding a second ship, did not carry out the dietary orders and his men developed scurvy. In 1,774 when Furneaux was awaiting Cook in Queen Charlotte Sound, New Zealand, he sent 11 men ashore to get some vegetables and they did not return. A rescue party found the remains of a cannibalistic feast! It is of interest that on Cook's third voyage he left Plymouth, England just 8 days after the signing of the Declaration of Independence in the United States, but Ben Franklin saw to it that no U.S. ships were to bother this scientific expedition. On Cook's return, coming north from the tip of Africa, he stayed clear of Europe because of danger from French ships and went up around north of Great Britain and then down to Whitby on the east coast.  Cook described Polynesian canoes 60 to 80 feet long, some even up to 100 feet and carrying 60 people with pigs, dogs and fresh vegetables or 100 warriors. He found Polynesians almost all over (Society Islands, Hawaii, etc.) were incorrigible thieves. His biographer, Warner (Ref.11) thought the Polynesians might have gone through Micronesia on their eastward migration but certainly not Melanesia.  By 1,778 there were perhaps 300,000 Polynesians in Hawaii in warring and feudal-like farming chiefdoms. By 1,795 all islands but Kauai were consolidated in a single kingdom under King Kamehameha. (Ref.12)

The Pacific: A.D. 1801 to 1900

THE PACIFIC

AUSTRALIA

Although the first penal colonists, including 700 convicts and 324 officials and family members had landed in Botany Bay in 1,788, the population of Australia did not pass 50,000 until 1,830 and the 1,000,000 mark was not reached until the late 1,850s.

As the century opened England was so busy with Napoleon that there was little concern for Australia and it was not until about 1,820 to 1,825 that even reasonable information was available in England about the New South Wales colony. Overall, by mid-century 160, 800 convicts had been sent, including many Irishmen. Few free settlers could be tempted to arrive and by the middle 1820s there were not more than 2,000.

It was in 1,801 that Captain Mac Arthur brought 12 ewes and a ram of the Merinos Spanish-origin sheep from South Africa, where they had been introduced from Spain a generation before. But wool was not exported to Britain until 1,806 and did not become a really significant market factor until the middle 1,820s, chiefly as the result then of the prodding of Governor Lachlan Macquarie, successor to the famous William Bligh of "Bounty" fame. The subsequent need for new grassland resulted in the successful crossing of the Blue Mountains and as the economy improved, a scattering of free settlements were started around the coast. Then the inland exploration of Australia was dominated by the problem of the rivers, because away from them there was usually great drought. (Ref. 1, 2)

Insert Map: Some Significant Explorations of Australia, and notes.

Multiple attempts were made by the British to settle the northern tip of Australia, chiefly to harass the Dutch in the adjacent islands and to make contact with the Malayans and Indonesians, who had been in communication with the Australian aborigines for centuries, but by mid-century all colonies had failed. In the south wheat began to be of commercial importance by 1,843, when a mechanical harvester called a "stripper" became available. Problems of land acquisition and ownership as well as the problem of labor supply continued for decades. Even up to 1850 free labor lived under the shadow of convict competition. At mid-century one still spoke of the "Australian Colonies", four in number, and initial proposals of federation got little response. In 1,863, however, the political geography was fixed in the present day pattern, although the Commonwealth did not materialize until 1,901. Up until then, the people thought of themselves, not as Australians, but as Victorians or Queenslanders, etc., as the case might be. Gold in significant quantity was discovered in New South Wales and multiple areas of Victoria in the 1,850s, leading to massive immigration from Europe, America and China, so that Australia's population almost tripled from 1,850 to 1,860, reaching 1,146,000 people. Melbourne grew fiercely as the seat of government of the gold fields of Victoria and the presence of thousands of "diggers" in those fields resulted in a lasting nickname for any of Australia's residents. But even then, wool-growing remained the premier industry.

Development increased in the 1,870s with a land boom in the 1,880s, followed by a financial panic in the early 1,890s. Recovery occurred rapidly, with associated great political, social and cultural changes. Agriculture and especially sheep raising remained the mainstay of the economy. Sheep diseases, the carnivorous sheep-eating dingo and the pasture destroying kangaroos and imported rabbits were fought constantly. In Queensland in 1,887 to 1,889 some 3,700,000 and 60,500 dingoes were killed, but the rabbits remained uncontrolled. Wheat acreage was gradually increased during the century, with South Australia alone reaching over 1 1/2 million acres by 1,891. Cane sugar became an important crop in Queensland by the end of the century. Less in true importance to the economy, but high in emotional value was mining - not only of the gold, but also of copper, a silver-lead-zinc complex, tin and coal. The leading manufactured products were boots, shoes and clothing.

Attempts to nationalize Australia and its various colonies surf aced at intervals after about 1,850 and culminated in 1,891 in a constitutional convention held in Sydney. In spite of much work, ratification by most of the colonies did not follow and it was not until September 17, 1,900 that Queen Victoria was finally able to sign a Proclamation to the effect that on and after the 1st day of January, 1,901 the people of New South Wales, Victoria, South Australia, Queensland, Tasmania and Eastern Australia should be united in a federal commonwealth under the name of the Commonwealth of Australia.

Australia's remoteness from the rest of the Caucasian world lessened with the development of steam-driven ships and undersea cables. In 1,881 60% of the shipping tonnage arriving in Australian ports was sail, but by 1,900 only 17% remained. The appearance of refrigerated ships in the 1,880s allowed shipment of frozen meat through the tropics to the London market and many farmers made fortunes. Urbanization progressed with Sydney reaching a population of 487,900 in 1,901 and Melbourne attaining 494,129 in the same year. Immigration supplied over 25% of the increase in population in the last half of the century, with people from the British Isles leading the way. Next in number were Germans, with Italians a distant third. In the gold rush days, however, as we noted above, thousands of Asiatics, chiefly Chinese, entered the area. Then other, chiefly Pacific Islanders called the "Kanakas", were deliberately imported as laborers, first in the pastoral industries and then in sugar manufacture. The colony of Victoria legislated restriction on Chinese entry as early as 1,855. Led by Sir Henry Parks, Victoria, South Australia and Queensland all joined in passing fairly uniform legislation to stem the influx. Western Australia followed in 1,886 and Tasmania in 1,887. By 1,901 the Chinese population had shrunk to 32,000 from a high of about 50,000 in the 1,870s. Although it was agreed in the 1,880s that Kanaka importation should also stop by 1,890, a depression in that year changed the outlook and the restriction was not imposed.

In 1,803 Great Britain took possession of the island of Tasmania and in the following year established a penal colony there. At that time there were approximately 7,000 natives, but they had been completely exterminated by 1,888. Originally part of New South Wales, Tasmania became a separate colony in 1,825, but did not receive its present name until 1,853. (Ref. 3, 4)1

MELANESIA

Insert Map: Micronesia, Melanesia and Polynesia

The people of the Solomon Islands are generally darker and shorter than even those of Fiji, New Caledonia or the New Hebrides, with many of the interior tribesmen being very black. Pygmies are present in the southern islands. European domination of the Pacific islands did not occur rapidly. New Caledonia, rich in minerals, became French in 1,853 and by 1,900 there were 23,500 whites in that group, by far the largest Caucasian population in any South Seas island chain. After 1,887 New Hebrides was controlled by a joint naval commission of British and French officers. (Ref. 6, 7)

New Guinea (Papua) is the world's largest island, excepting Greenland. It was so named because of coastal similarity to Guinea in Africa and consists largely of tropical jungle in which head-hunting and cannibalism have been practiced in some remote areas perhaps right up to the current writing. The west half of the island was annexed by the Dutch in 1,828 and in 1,884 the British announced a protectorate over the southeast coast and adjacent islands, while the Germans claimed the northeast portion. Thus it remained for the remainder of the century. In Fiji, bordering Melanesia and Polynesia, Europeans came at the opening of the century looking for sandalwood, but their diseases almost destroyed the native Fijians, who were of Melanesian origin. European guns intensified the tribal wars and after many chiefs joined in a request, the British annexed the islands in 1,874. Cannibalism flourished in those islands until the 20th century. Small, hot peppers and other vegetables were served with human meat to give it better flavor. After the British took over they hired natives to work in the cane fields, but at poor wages and only a few would work. As a result the British began to import East Indian laborers and today there are more of the latter in Fiji than natives and that brings up many problems. (Ref. 8, 9, 10)

Since whaling vessels stayed at sea until their barrels were filled with oil, the voyages sometimes took 2 or 3 years and only the dregs and troublemakers of the sailing men's world could be talked into signing up for such long voyages. As a result the Pacific islanders saw some mighty rough and dishonest American and British sailors. They brought in rum, started fights, stole women and anything else available. Some jumped ship to become pirates on their own, the most famous being "Bully" Hayes, who also was one of the originators of "blackbirding". Ship captains would "rent" natives to entrepreneurs to be used as laborers or miners (in South America) with the theory being that af ter a certain period the "blackbird" would be released to return home. Few ever did. The men of Melanesia suffered most of this blackbirding and wherever they were taken, living condition were very bad and 10% up to 75% of them died of disease. In the late 1,870s the people of New Caledonia rebelled against that and started to slaughter- any foreigner, savagely. That got the attention of European governments so that they finally forced an end to that traffic in island people.

MICRONESIA

The Japanese, feeling population pressure, began to more south in the Pacific, forcing the Chinese out of Okinawa and other Rykyu islands by 1,875. They had already laid claim to the Bonins in 1,861 and made them a part of their empire in 1,876. They then soon took the three volcano islands of which Iwo Jima is one, and after the turn of the century they moved still further south into the true area of Micronesia. Copra and dried fish were about the only products of these tiny islands.

POLYNESIA

In this 19th century Americans, Russians and Germans joined the Spanish, French and English in Oceania. In the first 50 years, European attention was given chiefly to the eastern islands, all of which, except Fiji, were already inhabited by true Polynesian peoples. The great explorers included the Frenchmen Dumont d'Urville (1,826-1,840), who also explored the Antarctica, the British Captain Frederick Beechey (1,825-1,828), Captain James Cook and above all the American Charles Wilkes, U.S.M. (1,838-1,842). Wilkes had 5 ships at his disposal and his explorations were extensive, from Hawaii to Antartica and the scientific publications arising from the expeditions are voluminous. In the east Pacific as well as the west, white men brought much grief to the islands, including disease and guns for more deadly warfare than had previously been possible between tribes. Dysentery and childhood diseases, along with firearms, started the process of island depopulation. Whalers and missionaries, each in their own very opposite ways, had tremendous effects on the island natives. (Ref. 11)

In the last module we described the visits of Captain Cook to the Hawaiian Islands. In an effort to secure an agricultural base for Alaska, Georg Schaeffer, a Bavarian in the Russian Service, established forts at two places on Kuaui in 1,816, but was soon run out by Yankee traders. Later in the century the Hawaian Islands functioned under theirown government, first as a constitutional monarchy and then in 1,893, after the deposition of Queen Liliuo Kalani, under a republic with Sanford B. Dole as president. In 1,900 the islands became a United States territory with Dole as governor. (Ref. 12)

The Marquesas and Tahiti reluctantly became French protectorates in 1,842. At that time the population of the Marquesas was about 20,000, but-European diseases decimated the people, as elsewhere in the Pacific, and today in the 20th century there are only about 3,000 people, with 4 of the islands having no inhabitants at all. The people of those islands used knotted strings to help them memorize lists of their ancestors names, much the same as the Aztecs did. (Ref. 13)

At the southwest corner of the great Polynesian triangle lies New Zealand, the only island group lying entirely within the temperate zone. Although discovered by Captain Cook in 1,769 it had only temporary, various European settlements in the next half century. By 1,840 the fierce, native Maori had already declined from a previous high population of perhaps 200,000 down to about 100,000 in the North Island, probably chiefly from inter- tribal wars. The South Island probably never had more than 15,000. The Maori were cannibals, but ate only their enemies, and initially, at least, they did not consider the whites in general as enemies. Their priests used notched sticks to help them remember endless chanted verses. They all suffered from the white man's diseases, including venereal ones, changes in diet and clothing and the use of guns on themselves. But they were happy to get iron, the pig and the potato. Soon after 1,840 there were already 19 Church of England missions and 2 Catholic ones, with both trying to keep the Maori tribes from warring on each other, although the church groups had conflicts themselves.

The British influence on the islands actually began in 1,833 with the appointment of James Busby as a resident agent. In 1,835 he signed the Treaty of Waitangi with Maori chieftains, forming an infant state of mixed whites and Maoris, under the parent protection of the King of England. Legally this appeared to be only a statement of intent to form a biracial society, with equal rights for both, but it survived only as an ideal. In spite of land wars which raged from time to time, New Zealand became a Crown Colony in 1,842, with Captain William Hobson as the first governor. A constitution of 1,852 set up a pseudo-federal system with 6 provinces, each with legislatures and central governments, but the Maori were denied franchise because they were not land-owners individually, as the Europeans were, but communally. Although not represented, they were still heavily taxed and Hobson and his successors had great difficulties pleasing both the Maori chieftains and the white settlers. Great government deficits augmented the problems.

The principal promoter of systematic settlement, the New Zealand Company, was motivated by land hunger at the expense of the "naked savages" and the racial situation rapidly deteriorated to the Maori-pakeha2 Wars of the 1,860s. These Maori Wars, lasting from March 1,860 to February 1,872, were not in any way a general native uprising. They were loosely linked bush skirmishes in various parts of the North Island. The total losses were probably not more than 700 whites and "loyal" Maoris on one side and 2,000 Polynesians on the other side. The wars simulated the smaller Indian wars of the eastern American forests. They finally ran themselves down and stopped, without any formal declaration of peace. The Maoris tried to withdraw then from the pakeha world. The whites were then able to exploit the North Island, with a boom developing in the 1,879s. Maoris were employed as laborers on public works and as shearers and station hands. In 1,867 some natives got the vote and elected 4 members to the House of Representatives.

Running parallel with the wars during the 1,860s was the story of gold on the South Island, beyond the reaches of the battles. Thus, both population and economy rose faster on the South Island, due not only to gold, but also to vast increases in cattle, sheep and crop acreage. Full exploitation of the potential products of both islands was delayed because of the absence of technology such as refrigeration, however, and a depression developed in the 1880s. Along with this, but unrelated, by the middle 1,880s it appeared that the Maoris might die out, as their number rapidly declined. By 1,896 there were only 42,000 left. New Zealand reached political stability under the leadership of a liberal prime minister, Richard John Seddon (1,893-1,906) and the help of rising prices and the export of meat, cheese and butter facilitated by refrigerated shipping. The British initially offered a market for wool and gold. Many experiments in socialism were undertaken in this country and it remains basically socialistic, yet without complete government control, today. (Ref. 14, 15, 16)

It was noted previously that when the Maoris arrived in New Zealand they found a previous people, the Morioris3, which they drove out to the Chatham Islands, some 400 miles away. In the 1,830s some Maoris apparently followed them there and largely exterminated them, with the help of a disreputable white. These Chatham Islands served as a place of confinement of Te Kooti and other Maori rebels during the wars of the 1,860s and were later incorporated into the pastoral economy of New Zealand.

At the risk of overemphasizing the importance of one small island, further information on the far southeastern Polynesian Easter Island may be of some interest. To date we have noted:

Probable original settlement by people from the South American mainland
Late arrival of true Polynesians
The loss of Polynesian culture, in the main, in favor of the earlier traditions

 Between 1,859 and 1,862 Peruvian slavers took some 1,000 Eastern islanders to Peru to dig guano. A handful of those later returned to the island, but brought small-pox with them and that disease further decimated the already depleted island. By 1,877 there were only 111 natives left. (Ref. 18)

In 1,862 a French missionary, F. Eugene Eyraud, visited Easter Island and found some strange boards and sticks with carved symbols in some of the huts and the local people had no idea of their meaning or significance. Some were salvaged and eventually ended up in various museums across the world. In 1,958 Thomas Barthel (Ref. 19) got reproductions of those from Honolulu, Vienna, Santiago de Chile, Leningrad, Washington D.C. and London, finally accumulating some 12,000 signs or ideograms to analyze. The signs were 1/3 to 1/2 inches long and were elegantly made. Previously a French bishop had found a man on Tahiti, who allegedly was originally an Easter islander and he had "read" four of the tablets containing the signs, by chanting a song in Polynesian for each. The chants were recorded by the bishop, but translated into French they seemed meaningless and the notes were almost lost. Barthel decided that the Tahitian, Metoro Tauara, was too uneducated to have completely translated the ancient script and proceeded to develop a translation of his own. He reported that 120 basic elements were combined to make 1,000 compound signs as ideograms and that it was not a phonetic system. Furthermore, he decided that the writing was chiefly religious ritual, without mention of historical events. He says that the islanders had another writing called the "Kau Script" which recorded their annals, but that has disappeared. Since the board writings had a special symbol for the breadfruit tree and other plants which never grew on Easter Island and since Pitcairn Island to the west was mentioned, Barthel felt that these things refuted Heyerdahl's theory of settlement from the eastern mainland. But those talking boards are not dated and whereas Heyerdahl's South American migrations theoretically occurred many centuries ago, it does not seem that Barthel's conclusions are necessarily valid. Ocean trips between Polynesian islands certainly occurred after the time of the early Polynesian migrations, if not before and such have no bearing on very early trips west from Peru or Ecuador. (Ref. 20)

Please permit one more argument from Heyerdahl. (Ref. 21) In 1,864 before the local language had been recorded, a missionary with a group of Mangarevans came to Easter Island via Tahiti and the Tahitian language was introduced, so that subsequently there was a mixture of languages, if there had not been before. The Tahitians who arrived at that time were Christians and therefore did not bring the classical Polynesian deities of Tu, Tane, Tangaroa, Tiki and Maui. Some of those names persisted although they were not worshiped or venerated. The Easter Island gods were Makemake and Haua and symbols related to the former were closely associated with sun-measuring devices and other trappings of solar worship, all unknown in other Polynesian areas. Conversely, the complex bird cult and ritual of Easter Island has no counterpart in the rest of Polynesia, but the bird-man cult was present at Tiahuanaco, Bolivia and in the Chimu culture of north Peru, so that an American origin for those Easter Island practices is suggested.

1 [76] GRATTAN, C. HARTLEY, The Southwest Pacific to 1900. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1963).

2 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

3 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

4 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

5 [312] PATTERSON, CAROLYN BENNETT, "A Walk and Ride on the Wild Side", National Geographic 163, No. 5: 676-693, May 1983.

6 [76] GRATTAN, C. HARTLEY, The Southwest Pacific to 1900. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1963).

7 [134] MAY, CHARLES Paul, Oceania: Polynesia, Melanesia, Micronesia. (Thomas Nelson, Inc., Nashville, Tenn. 1973).

8 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

9 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

10 [134] MAY, CHARLES Paul, Oceania: Polynesia, Melanesia, Micronesia. (Thomas Nelson, Inc., Nashville, Tenn. 1973).

11 [134] MAY, CHARLES Paul, Oceania: Polynesia, Melanesia, Micronesia. (Thomas Nelson, Inc., Nashville, Tenn. 1973).

12 [199] STARR, S. FREDERICK, "Why did Russia let Seward's folly go on the cheap?" Smithsonian, Dec. 1979, page 129.

13 [9] BARTHEL, THOMAS S., "The Talking Boards of Easter Island", Scientific American, 236:116-133, March, 1977.

14 [76] GRATTAN, C. HARTLEY, The Southwest Pacific to 1900. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1963).

15 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

16 [9] BARTHEL, THOMAS S., "The Talking Boards of Easter Island", Scientific American, 236:116-133, March, 1977.

17 [76] GRATTAN, C. HARTLEY, The Southwest Pacific to 1900. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1963).

18 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

19 [9] BARTHEL, THOMAS S., "The Talking Boards of Easter Island", Scientific American, 236:116-133, March, 1977.

20 [9] BARTHEL, THOMAS S., "The Talking Boards of Easter Island", Scientific American, 236:116-133, March, 1977.

21 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

1. NOTES: In Tasmania the first Europeans (except a few shipwrecked sailors) were prisoners transported there in 1821. They worked under the lash, cutting 2,000 year-old Huon pines for ship building.  In the 1850s whalers came to Port Davey. The whites raped the aboriginal women and stole their children. Their men were relentlessly tracked down and killed for sport in parties like fox-hunters. The last pure-blood aboriginal died in 1876. (Ref. 5)

2.  "Pakeha" was the Maori word for "white settlers".

3.  Grattan (Ref. 17) describes the Morioris as "Polynesians", but this may be incorrect. Please see The Pacific: A.D. 801 to 900.

BIBLIOGRAPHY

References

1. ABBOTT, SHIRLEY, The National Museum of American History, (Harry N. Abrahams, Inc. New York, 1981).

2. ABERCROMBIE, THOMAS J., "The Sweep of Islam.", Great Religions of the World, (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

3. ALLISON, MARVIN J., "Studies of Pre-Columbian American Diseases 1971-1976, National Geographic Research Reports. Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 1-11 (National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., 1980).

4. ANGELL, J. LAWRENCE, "Osteoarthritis in Prehistoric Turkey and Medieval Byzantium", Henry Ford Hospital Journal 27: 38, 1979.

5. ATIL, ESIN, "As bodyguards or rulers, Mamluks made a golden age.", Smithsonian 12: No. 4, pp.108-1131, July, 1981.

6. AZZI, ROBERT, "Saudi Arabia: The Kingdom and its Power", National Geographic 158:286, Sept., 1980.

7. BALFOUR, MICHAEL, Stonehenge and its Mysteries, (Charles Scribners Sons, N.Y., 1980).

8. BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

9. BARTHEL, THOMAS S., "The Talking Boards of Easter Island", Scientific American, 236:116-133, March, 1977.

10. BELCHER, TAYLOR AND EDIE, "Great Golden Art of the Ancient Peruvian Artisans", Smithsonian 8:841, Dec. 1977.

11. BELL, I. WILEY, "Admiral Yi and the Turtle Boats", American History Illustrated X11:44-48, June, 1977 .

12. BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

13. BERGER, TENY, "Tulipomania was no Dutch treat to gambling burghers", Smithsonian 8:70-77, April, 1977.

14. BIEL, JORG, "Treasure from a Celtic Tomb", National Geographic 157:428, March 1980.

15. BOOKS AND MEDICINE, (Editors), M.D. Medical News Magazine, Vol. 3, No. 8, Aug. 1959.

16. BOYD, WM. C., "Genetics and the Human Race", Science 140:1057-1064, June 7, 1963.

17. BREFFNY, BRIAN DE, (Editor), The Irish World, (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. N.Y., 1977).

18. BRITISH MUSEUM, (Personal notes, 1978).

19. BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

20. BRODIE, FAWN M., Thomas Jefferson, An Intimate History", (W.W. Norton & Co., Inc., New York).

21. BRONOWSKI, J., The Ascent of Man. (Little, Brown & Co. Boston, Toronto, 1973).

22. CANBY, Thomas Y., "The Search for the First Americans", National Geographic Vol.155 No. 3, page 330, Sept. 1979.

23. CASTELOT, ANDRE, King of Rome, (Translated from French by Robert Baldick), (Harper and Bros. Publishers, New York, 1960).

24. CERRUTE, JAMES, "Belgium, One Nation Divisible", National Geographic 155:314, March, 1979.

25. CHAKRAVARTY, AMIYA, "Hinduism". Great Religions of the World, (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

26. CHAN, WING-TSIT, "The Orderly Realm of Chinese Sages". Great Religions of the World. (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

27. CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

28. CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

29. CHURCHILL, WINSTON, A History of the English Speaking Peoples. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1956). Volume I - The Birth of Britain.

30. CHURCHILL, WINSTON, Ibid., Volume II - The New World.

31. CHURCHILL, WINSTON, Ibid., Volume III - The Age of Revolution.

32. CHURCHILL, WINSTON, Ibid., Volume IV - The Great Democracies.

33. CLARK, KENNETH, Civilization. (Harper & Row, New York & Evanston, 1969).

34. CLARK, SIDNEY, All the Best in Scandinavia. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1968).

35. COBB, CHARLES E.,JR., "After Rhodesia, a Nation named Zimbabwe", National Geographic 160: 616-651, Nov. 1981).

36. COE, MICHAEL D. "Archeological Linkage with North & South America at La Victoria, Guatemala", American Anthropologist 62: 363-393, 1960.

37. COLLINS, LARRY and LAPRERRE, DOMINIQUE, Freedom at Midnight. (Simon & Schuster, New York, 1975).

38. COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

39. COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

40. COSTAIN, THOMAS B., The Three Edwards. (Doubleday & Co., Inc., Garden City, New York, 1958).

41. COTTERELL, ARTHUR, The Minoan World. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, N.Y., 1980).

42. "CROSS AND CRESCENT, M.D. Medical Newsmagazine, Vol.3, No.3, March, 1959.

43. CUNLIFFE, BARRY, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

44. DALES, GEORGE F., "Strange Relics of the Crumbling, Still-puzzling Indus Culture", Smithsonian 89:56-65, July, 1977.

45. DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

46. DURANT, WILL, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

47. DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part II - The Life of Greece. (1939).

48. DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

49. DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part IV - The Age of Faith. (1950).

50. DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part V - The Renaissance. (1953).

51. DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part VI - The Reformation. (1957).

52. DURANT, WILL and ARIEL, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part VII - The Age of Reason Begins. (1961).

53. DURANT, WILL and ARIEL, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

54. DURANT, WILL and ARIEL, Ibid., Part IX - The Age of Voltaire. (1965).

55. DURANT, WILL and ARIEL, Ibid. Part XI - The Age of Napoleon. (1975).

56. DYSON, FREEMAN, Disturbing the Universe. (Harper and Row, N.Y., 1979).

57. EASTON, STEWART C. The Heritage of the Past. (Alternate Edition). (Rinehart & Co., Inc. New York, 1957.

58. EDWARDS, MIKE, "Tunisia: Sea, Sand, Success", National Geographic 157: 184, Feb. 1980.

59. EL-BAZ, FAROUK, "Desert Builders Knew a Good Thing when they saw it", Smithsonian April, 1981, pages 116-121.

60. ELIOT, JOHN L., "Treasures of Dresden", National Geographic 154: No. 5, Page 702, Nov. 1978.

61. ENCYLOPEDIA BRITANNICA, (Encyclopedia Britannica, Inc., Wm. Benton, Publ.).

62. ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

63. FALCONER, THOMAS, Discovery of the Mississippi. (London, 1844 - as reprinted by Shoal Creek Publishers, Inc. Austin, Texas, 1975).

64. FARB, PETER, Man's Rise to Civilization. (E.P. Dutton & Co., New York, 1968).

65. FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

66. FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

67. FITZHUGH, WM. W., "Excavations at Rattlers Bight - A Late Maritime Archaic Settlement and Cemetery in Hamilton Inlet, Labrador." National Geographic Research Reports Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 287-304. (Publishers National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., 1980).

68. GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

69. GARRETT, W.E., "China's Beauty Spot", National Geographic 156: 536, Oct. 1979.

70. GARTHWAITE, G.R., "The Bakhtiyari Tribe: Its Organization and Role in Iran". National Geographic Societv Research Reports Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 257-266. (National Geographic Society Publications, 1980).

71. GEARY, DOROTHY, "Mighty Tamerlane became Master of Half the World", Smithsonian Sept. 1979, page 89.

72. GIBBONS, BOYD, "The Bulgarians", National Geographic 158: 91, July, 1980.

73. GORE, RICK, "Journey to China's Far West", National Geographic 157: 292, March 1980.

74. GRAMONT, SANCHE DE, The French, Portrait of a People. (G.E. Putnam 's Sons~ New York, 1969).

75. GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

76. GRATTAN, C. HARTLEY, The Southwest Pacific to 1900. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1963).

77. "GREEK MEDICINE", (Epic of Medicine Series, M.D. Newsmagazine, Vol. 3, No. 9, Sept. 1959).

78. GREEMAN, E.F. Discussion of paper of Ronal J. Mason, Current Anthropology, Vol. 3, No. 3, pp. 252-254, 1962.

79. GREEN, MAUREEN, "A tough people in a tough time, the Vikings also had a gentler side", Smithsonian, Sept., 1980, page 60.

80. GROVE, DAVID C., "Olmec Origins and Transpacific Diffusion: Reply to Meggers", American Anthropology 78: 634-637, 1976.

81. GROVE, DAVID C., "Archeological Investigations at Chalcatzingo, 1972, 1973." National Geographic Reports Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 287-304, (National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., 1980.

82. GROVE, NOEL, "North Yemen", National Geographic 156: 244, Aug. 1979.

83. HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

84. HAMBLIN, DORA JANE, "Carthage must be destroyed' It was but now it is reappearing", Smithsonian 9: 442, Feb. 1979.

85. HAMMOND, NORMAN, "The Earliest Maya", Scientific American 236: 116-133, Mar. 1977.

86. HANSEN, JAMES, "Knights of Malta, mini-nation based on Chivalry", Smithsonian 12: 112-127, Jan. 1982.

87. HAWKES, JACQUETTA, The World of the Past. (Two volumes). (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1927.

88. HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

89. HEARN, MAXWELL, "An Ancient Chinese Army rises from Underground Sentinel duty", Smithsonian, Nov. 1979, page 39.

90. HEIZER, Robert F., "Source of the Colossi of Memnon of the Theben Plain, Egypt, National Geographic Society Research Reports Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 287-304. (National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., 1980).

91. HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

92. HERODOTUS, The Persian Wars. (Translated by George Rawlinson). (Random House, Inc., 1942).

93. HESS, BILL, "The White Mountain Apache: Seeking the Best of Two Worlds", National Geographic 157: 218, Feb. 1980.

94. HEYERDAHL, THOR, "Tigris sails into the Past, National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

95. HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

96. HEYERDAHL, THOR, Aku-Aku, The secret of Easter Island. (Chicago, 1958).

97. HISTORICAL ATLAS OF THE WORLD. Barnes and Noble Books. (Harper & Row, New York et al, 1972).

98. HOPKINS, TOM, South Africa. (Time, Inc. New York, 1964).

99. HOYLE, FRED, On Stonehenge. (W. F. Freemon & Co., San Francisco, 1977).

100. HSU, KENNETH J., "When the Black Sea was Drained," Scientific American, 238: 53-63, May, 1978.

101. HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

102. HUME, IVOR NOEL, "First look at a Lost Virginia Settlement," National Geographic. June, 1979, page 735.

103. HUME, IVOR NOEL, "New Clues to an Old Mystery", National Geographic 161: 53-77, Jan. 1982.

104. HUNT, CARLA, "Berber Brides' Fair", National Geographic 157: 119, Jan. 1980.

105. HYMAN, RANDALL, - "Fiery Images of Continental Drift", Smithsonian 12: 52-63, Jan. 1982.

106. JONES, ROBERT A., "State's Past Being Sacrificed in Rush to Future", Los Angeles Times, Oct. 1975.

107. JORDON, ROBERT PAUL, "The Proud Armenians", National Geographic 153: 846, June 1978.

108. JORDON, ROBERT PAUL. "Sri Lanka", National Geographic 155: 123, Jan. 1979.

109. JUDGE, JOSEPH, "Minoans and Mycenaens: Greece's Brilliant Bronze Age", National Geographic 153: 142, Feb. 1978.

110. JUDGE, JOSEPH, The Travail of Ireland", National Geographic 1159: 432-441, Apr. 1981.

111. KEDDI, NIKKI R., Roots of Revolution. (Yale University Press, 1981).

112. KEITH, DONALD H., "A 14th Century Cargo Makes Port at Last", National Geographic 156: 231, Aug. 1979.

113. KIM, H. EDWARDS, "Seoul: Korean Showcase", National Geographic 156: 770, Dec. 1979.

114. KITAGAWA, JOSEPH M., "The Eightfold Path to Nirvana", Great Religions of the World. (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

115. KUH, MICHAEL, "Saffron Roles in Gilded Thailand", Great Religions of the World. (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

116. LAMB HAROLD, Genghis Khan. (Robert M. McBride & Co., New York 1927).

117. LA FAY, HOWARD, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

118. FAY, HOWARD, "Syria", National Geographic 157: 485-511, Apr. 1980.

119. LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

120.  LAURING, PALLE, A History of Denmark. (Host & Son, Copenhagen 1960).

121.  LEONARDO DA VINCI. (Reynal & Co. New York, 1956).

122.  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

123.  LIBRARY OF CONGRESS, "Documents Illustrative of the Formation of the Union of the American States, Government Printing Office, Washington D.C. 1927.

124.  LOW, D.M. (Editor). Abridgement of The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire, by EDWARD GIBBON. (Harcourt, Brace & Co., New York 1960).

125.  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

126.  MACARTNEY, C.S., Hungary. A Short History. (Aldine Publishing Co., Chicago 1962).

127. MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

128. MAREK, GEORGE R., The Eagles Die. (Harper & Row, New York, 1974).

129. MARINATOS, SPYRIDON, "Thera, Key to the Riddle of Minos", National Geographic 141: No. 5, page 702, May, 1972.

130. MARSHACK, ALEXANDER, The Roots of Civilization. (McGraw-Hill Book Co., 1972).

131. MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

132. MASON, RONAL J., "The Paleo-Indian Tradition in Eastern North America", Current Anthropology 3, No. 33: 227-252, 1962.

133. MATTINGLY, GARRETT, The Armada. (The Riverside Press, Cambridge: Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston 1959).

134. MAY, CHARLES Paul, Oceania: Polynesia, Melanesia, Micronesia. (Thomas Nelson, Inc., Nashville, Tenn. 1973).

135. MAZOUR, ANATOLE G., Russia, Tsarist and Communist. (D. Van Nostrand Co., Inc. Princeton, New Jersey 1963).

136. McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

137. McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

138. McDOWELL, BART, "The Aztecs", National Geographic 158: Dec. 1980.

139. McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

140. McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

141. MEGGERS, BETTY J., "The Transpacific Origin of Meso American Civilization: A Preliminary Review of the Evidence and its theoretical Implications", American Anthropologist 77: 1-271, 1975.

142. MEGGERS, BETTY J., "Yes if by Land, No if by Sea: The Double Standard in Interpreting Cultural Similarities", American Anthropologist 78: 637, 1976.

143. MENOZZIL, P., PIAZZA, L. AND CAVELLI-SFORZA, L., "Synthetic Maps of Human Gene Frequencies in Europeans", Science 201: 789-7921, Sept. 1978.

144. MICHAUD, ROLAND AND SABRINA, "Afghanistan: A Record of a Timeless Culture now threatened with change", Smithsonian, Nov. 1980, page 48.

145. MIDDLETON, DREW, "History Supports Poland", Syndicated column in Dallas Morning New, Jan. 25, 1982.

146. MILTON, RENE, "Teotihuacán", Scientific American, June 1967, page 38.

147. MITFORD, NANCY, The Sun King. (Harper & Row, New York, 1966).

148. MOCTEZUMA, EDUARDO MATOS, "New Finds in the Great Temple", National Geographic 158: Dec. 1980.

149. MOLINA MONTEZ, Augusto F., "The Building of Tenochtitlan", National Geographic 158: Dec. 1980.

150. MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, Admiral of the Ocean Sea. A Life of ChristopherColumbus. (Little, Brown & Co., Boston 1942).

151. MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

152. MUCKROSS ABBEY, Killarney, Ireland. Personal material obtained 1978.

153. NANCE, JOHN, The Gentle Tasaday. (Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, Inc., New York 1975.

154. NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Africa: Its Political Development", Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, Washington, D.C., Feb. 1980.

155. NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Archeological Map of Middle America, Ibid. Oct. 1968.

156. NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, Atlas of the World. 5th Edition. (National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., 1981.

157. NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Demons and Lamas in the High Himalayas", Great Religions of the World, National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition.

158. NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Early Civilizations in the Middle East. Map from Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., Sept. 1978.

159. OETTINGER, MARION JR. AND PARSONS, PATRICIA AMANDA, "The Tlapanec Indians of Tlacoapa, Guerro, Mexico", National Geo~raphic Research Reports, 12: 517-528, 1971. (Published by the National Geographic Society, Washington D.C. 1980.

160. OXENSTIERNA, ERIC, "The Vikings", Scientific American, May 1967.

161. OZGUC, TAHSIN, "Ancient Ararat", Scientific American, Mar. 1967, page 44.

162. PAGE, JAMES K., JR., "Phenomena, Comment and Notes, Smithsonian 8: 15-16. Summer, 1976.

163. PAGELS, ELAINE, The Gnostic Gospels. (Random House, New York 1979).

164. PAINTIN, ELAINE, "Radio-carbon Dating and the Archeologist", Pamphlet published by the Trustees of the British Museum, 1977).

165. PALMER, ROSE A., The North American Indians. (Vol. IV Smithsonian Instruction Series, The Series Publishers, Inc., New York 1949).

166. PARKES, HENRY BAMFORD, A History of Mexico. (Houghton Miff lin Co., Boston. The Riverside Press, Cambridge).

167. PARSON, JAMES J. AND DENEVEN, WILLIAM M., "Pre-Columbian Ridged Fields", Scientific American July, 1967, page 93.

168. PEI, MARIO. The Story of Language. (Revised Edition). (J.P. Lippincott Co., Philadelphia & New York 1962.

169. POLLITZER, WILLIAM S., "Blood Groups and Anthropology", Critical Reviews in Clinical Laboratory Sciences Vol. I: 193, 1970.

170. PREBBEL, JOHN, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

171. PRIDEAUX, TOM, "Rich & Rugged Thracian life seen in a Glittering Show", Smithsonian 8: 42-51, June 1977.

172. PUTMAN, JOHN J., "Down the Teeming Ganges, Holy River of India, Great Religions of the World. (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

173. RAMSEY L.G.G., The Complete Encyclopedia of Antiques. (Hawthorn Books, Inc., New York, 1962).

174. RANG, MERCER, Anthology of Orthopedics. (Chas. Livingtone, Edinburgh, London & New York, 1966).

175. READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

176. READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

177. REINHARDT. KURT F., Germany: 2000 Years. (Frederick ~ngar Publishing Co., New York, 1960).

178. RENFREW, COLIN, "Ancient Europe is Older than we Thought", National Geographic 152: 615, Nov. 1977.

179. RENFREW, COLIN, "Ancient Bulgaria's Golden Treasures", National Geographic 158: 112, July, 1980.

180. RICE, DAVID TALBOT, (Editor), The Dawn of European Civilization. (McGraw-Hill Book Co., Inc., New York 1965).

181. RICKETT, RICHARD, A Brief Survey of Austrian History. (Georg Prachner Verlag, Wien, Third Edition, 1970).

182. RIPLEY, S. DILLON, "Tibet: the high & fragile land behind the ranges", Smithsonian Jan. 1981, pp. 97-105.

183. ROCKEFELLER (NELSON) COLLECTION. (The Nelson Rockefeller Collection, Inc., New York, 1978).

184. RODES, JOHN E., Germany: A History. (Holt, Rinehart & Wilson, New York 1964).

185. ROMAN MEDICINE, in Epic of Medicine Series, M.D. Medical Newsmagazine, 3: No. 8, Aug. 1959.

186. SAKELLARAKIS, YANNIS AND SAPOUNA-SAKELLARAKI, EFI, "Drama of Death in a Minoan Temple", National Geographic 159: 205-222, Feb. 1981.

187. SANTA CATALINA ISLAND, Pamphlet by Santa Catalina Island Co., Avalon, Calif.

188. SAVILLE, CURTIS & KATHLEEN, "They row, row, row their boat across the Atlantic Ocean", Smithsonian, Oct. 1981, pp. 192-215.

189. SCHLEDERMANN, PETER, "Eskimo and Viking Finds in the High Arctic", National Geographic 159: 575-602, May 1981.

190. SCHOMP, GERALD, "St. Brendan's Fantastic Voyage", American History Illustrated XII: 22-27, Apr. 1977.

191. SCHWARTZ, GEORGE AND BISHOP, PHILIP W., Moments of Discovery. Vol. I - The Origins of Science. (Basic Books, Inc., New York 1958).

192. SCHWARTZ, GEORGE AND BISHOP, PHILIP W., Ibid. Volume II - The Development of Modern Science.

193. SCIENTIFIC AMERICAN, "Science and the Citizen" section, 238: 92-96, May 1978.

194. SEVERY, MERLE, "The Celts", National Geographic 151: 582-634, May 1977.

195. SMITH, GARY AND LONG, MICHAEL E., "Utah's Rock Art: Wilderness Louvre", National Geographic 157: 971, Jan. 1980.

196. SMITH, RHEA MARSH, Spain, A Modern History. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

197. SOUTHGATE, M. THERESE, "Explanation of Cover - Rhyton with Kneeling Bull", Journal of the American Medical Association 239: vol. 1, page 4.

198. (The) SPANISH WEST, by Editors of Time-life Books. (Time-Life Books, New York, 1976).

199. STARR, S. FREDERICK, "Why did Russia let Seward's folly go on the cheap?" Smithsonian, Dec. 1979, page 129.

200. STATLER, OLIVER, "Pilgrims' Path in Buddhist Japan", Great Religions of the World. (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

201. STATLER, OLIVER, " Zen's Disciplined Way to Sudden Light", Great Religions of the World. (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

202. STEIN, JESS, (Editor-in-chief), The Random House Dictionary of the English Language. (Random House, New York, 1966).

203. STEPHENS, JOHN L., Incidents of Travel in Central America, Chiapas and Yucatan. (Dover Publ., Inc., New York, 1969 - Re-publication of original published in 1841 by Harper and Brothers).

204. STEPHENS, JOHN L., Incidents of Travel in Yucatan, Volume I. (Dover Publ., Inc. New York, 1963 - unabridged re-publication of 1843 work by Harper & Bros.).

205. STEPHENS, JOHN L., Ibid. Volume II.

206. STILLMAN EDMUND AND EDITORS OF LIFE, The Balkans. (Time, Inc., New York, 1964).

207. STOKES, JOHN F.D., "Spaniards & the Sweet Potato in Hawaii & Hawaiian American Contacts", American Anthropologist 34: 594, 1932.

208. SULLIVAN, LOUIS R., "Race Types in Polynesia", American Anthropologist Vol. XXVI, No. 1, 1924.

209. SWANSON, EARL H; BRAY, WARWICK; FARRINGTON, IAN, The New World. (E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc., New York, 1975).

210. TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

211. TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

212. TANNER, OGDEN, The Canadians. (Time-Life Books Inc., Alexandria, Va. 1977).

213. THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

214. THOMSON, DANIEL, "The Ebb & Flow of Infection", Journal of the American Medical Assoc. 235: Vol. 3, page 269, Jan 19, 1976).

215. THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

216. THUCYDIDES, The Peloponnesian War. (Translated by John H. Finley, Jr.). (Random House, Inc., New York 1951).

217. de TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

218. de TOCQUEVILLE, ALEX15, Ibid. Volume II. (Original publication in 1840).

219. TOPPING, AUDREY, "China's Incredible Find", National Geographic 153: 440, Apr. 1978.

220. TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

221. TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., Change and Habit. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1966).

222. TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

223. UNDERWOOD, E. THURSTON, "The Mimbrenos: Masters of the Pottery Art", Southwest Heritage 6: 15-161, Summer, 1976.

224. VAN ANDEL, TJEERD, Tales of an Old Ocean. (The Portable Stanford, Stanford Alumni Assoc., Stanford, Calif. 1977).

225. VESILIND, PRIT J. "Return to Estonia", National Geographic 157: 485-511, Apr. 1980.

226. WAECHTER, JOHN, Prehistoric Man. (Octopus Books Limited, London and Mandarin Publishers Limited, Hong Kong, 1977).

227. WALDREN, WM. H., "Investigation of Cave Deposits of Quarternary and Holocene Origin: The Muleta Expedition", National Geographic Society Research Reports, Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 731-745. (National Geographic Society, Washington D.C. 1980).

228. WARD, FRED, "In Long-Forbidden Tibet", National Geographic 157: 218, Feb. 1980.

229. WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

230.

231. WENTE, EDWARD F., "Tutankhamun and his World", Treasures of Tutankhamun. (The Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1976).

232. WERNICK, ROBERT, "M. de Tallyrand, a controversial Prince of Politics", Smithsonian Nov. 1981, pp. 74-83.

233. WHEAT, JOE BEN, "A Paleo-Indian Bison Kill", Scientific American, Jan. 1967, page 44.

234. WHEELER, KEITH, The Alaskans. (Time-Life Books, Alexandria, Va. 1977).

235. WICHITA FALLS TIMES, Wichita Falls, Texas, Apr. 29, 1977.

236. WILKERSON, JEFFREY K. "Man's Eighty Centuries in Veracruz", National Geographic 158: 202, Aug. 1980.

237. WILSON, DAVID, The Vikings and their Origins. (Thames and Hudson, London, 1970).

238. WOOLLEY, SIR LEONARD, Excavations at Ur. (Barnes & Noble, Inc., New York and Ernest Benn Limited, London, 1955).

239. WORLEY, IAN A., "Ancient Environments & Age of Non-glaciated Terrain in Southeastern Alaska", National Geographic Research Reports, Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 731-732. (Publ. National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., 1980).

240. WORLD BOOK ENCYLOPEDIA. (Field Enterprises, Inc., Chicago 1950).

241. ZIMMERMAN, LARRY J. AND WHITTEN, RICHARD G., "Prehistoric bones tell a grim tale of Indian vs. Indian", Smithsonian, Sept. 1980, page 100.

242. PEFFER, NATHANIAL, The Far East. (Univ. of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1958).

243. EL-BAZ, FAROUK, "Egypt's desert of Promise", National Geographic 161: 190-221, Feb. 1982.

244. MALONEY, STEPHANIE J., "The Medieval Fortress of Mietlica in Poland", Archeology 35: 26-32, Mar./Apr. 1982.

245. DETHLEFSEN, EDWIN, ET AL, "Archeology on St. Eustatius: The Pompeii of the New World", Archeology 35: 8-15, Mar./Apr. 1982.

246. BIANCHI, ROBERT S., "Egyptian Mummies: Myth and Reality", Archeology 35: 18-25, Mar./Apr. 1982.

247. WINN, MICHAEL, "Following the trail of Marco Polo across the roof of Central Asia", Smithsonian 13: No. 1, pp. 46-55, Apr. 1982.

248. CHELMINSKI, RUDOLF, "The plot to murder Napoleon:, Smithsonian 13: No. 1, pp. 76-87, Apr. 1982.

249. FINLEY, M.I., Ancient Slavery & Modern Ideology. (The Viking Press, New York, 1980).

250. GILLINGHAM, JOHN, The Wars of the Roses. (Louisiana State University, 1981).

251. BEDAUX, ROGIER M.A., "Rediscoverring the Tellem of Mali", Archeology 35: No. 3, pp. 28-34, May/June 1982.

252. FLEMING, STUART, "Chaco Canyon: Mystery of the Pueblos", Archaeology 35: No. 3 37-38, May/June 1982.

253. BECKER, MARSHALL J., "Search for the Lenape Indians", Archeology 35: No. 3, 10-19, May/June, 1982.

254. CAPUTO, ROBERT, "Sudan: Arab-African Giant", National Geographic 161: 346-379, Mar. 1982.

255. ARCHEOLOGY OF SOUTH AMERICA, Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, March 1982.

256. INDIANS OF SOUTH AMERICA, Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, March 1982.

257. LEVY, JANET E., The Bronze Age Hoards of Denmark", Archeology 35: No. 1, pp. 37-45, Jan/Feb. 1982.

258. SEARS, W.H., "Food Production & Village Life in Prehistoric Southeastern United States", Archaeology 24: 322-329, Oct. 1971.

259. MAC NEISH, RICHARD STOCKTON, "Food Production & Village Life Developed in the Tehuacan Valley, Mexico", Archaeology 24: 307-315, Oct. 1971.

260. BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

261. PULESTON, DENNIS E. AND PULESTON, OLGA STAVRAKIS, "An Ecological Approach to the Origins of Maya Civilizations", Archaeology 24: 330-3371, Oct. 1971.

262. WARNER, ROBERT, "Thailand hosts a birthday party", Smithsonian, Vol. 13, No. 3: 34-45, June, 1982.

263. HAMMOND, NORMAN, "Unearthing the Oldest Known Maya", National Geographic 162: 126- 140, July 1982.

264. FREIDEL, DAVID; ROBERTSON, ROBIN; AND CLIFF, MAYNARD B., "The Maya City of Cerros", Archaeology Vol. 355, No. 4: 12-211, July/Aug. 1982.

265. SNARSKIS, MICHAEL J., "The Pre-Columbian Art of Costa Rica", Archaeology Vol. 35, No 1: 54-581, Jan./Feb. 1982.

266. de SAPIR, OLGA LINARES AND RANERE, ANTHONY J., "Human Adaptation to the Tropical Forests of Western Panama", Archaeology 24: 346-355, Oct. 1971.

267. WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

268. McINTOSH, SUSAN & RODERICK, "Finding West Africa's Oldest City", National Geographic 162: 396-417, Sept. 1982.

269. McQUIRE, RANDALL AND SCHIFFER, MICHAEL B., "On the Threshold of Civilization: The Hohokam of Arizona", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 22-29, Sept./Oct. 1982.

270. BUTZER, KARL W., "Empires, Capitals and Landscapes of Ancient Ethiopia", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 30-37, Sept./Oct. 1982.

271. ANDERSON, ROBERT D., "Qasr Ibrim: Watchdog of the Nile", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 58-60, Sept./Oct. 1982.

272. TONG, ENZHENG; LENG, JIAN AND WANGDUI, SUOLANG, "Unraveling Tibetan Prehistory at Karuo", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 62, Sept./Oct. 1982.

273. ANAWALT, PATRICIA R. "Understanding Aztec Human Sacrifice", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 38-45, Sept./Oct. 1982.

274. BENCHLEY, PETER, "The Bahamas", National Geographic 162: 365-395, Sept. 1982.

275. FISHER, ROBERT E., "The Stone Temples of Kashmir", Archaeology 35, No. 4: 47-53, July/ Aug. 1982.

276. EVERINGHAM, JOHN, "Thailand's Working Royalty", National Geographic 162:468-498, Oct. 1892.

277. CANBY, THOMAS Y, "The Anasazi: Riddles in the Ruins", National Geographic 162: 562-592, Nov. 1982.

278. MOZAI, TORAO, "The Lost Fleet of Kublai Khan", National Geographic 162: 635-649, Nov. 1982.

279. McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

280. BUTTERFIELD, FOX, China. Alive in the Bitter Sea. (Times Books).

281. GORE, RICK, "The Mediterranean: Sea of Man's Fate", National Geographic 162: 694-737, Dec. 1982.

282. PEKARIK, ANDREW J., "The Cave Temples of Dunbruang", Archaeology 36, Vol. 1: 20-27, Jan./Feb. 1983.

283. NATIONS, HAMES D. AND CLARK, JOHN E., "The Bows and Arrows of the Lacandon Maya", Archaeology 36, Vol. I: 36-43, Jan./Feb. 1983.

284. HATCH, JAMES W. AND GEIDEL, RICHARD A., "Tracing Status and Diet in Prehistoric Tennessee", Archaeology 36, Vol. I: 56-59, Jan./Feb. 1983.

285. KERSHAW, NORMA, "Journey to the Caves of China", Archaeology 36, Vol. I: 66-69, Jan./Feb. 1983.

286. MORTON, W. BROWN, III, "Indonesia Rescues Ancient Borobudur", National Geographic 163: 126-142, Jan. 1983.

287. "NAPOLEON'S DEATH: ARSENIC & OLD WALLPAPER", Currents section, page 6, Science 83, Jan./Feb. 1983.

288. "PEOPLES OF THE ARCTIC", Cartographic Division, National Geographic, Feb. 1983.

289. TUCKER, WILLIAM, "Thrifty Diabetes", Science 83, Apr. 1983, pp. 92-93.

290. CASEY, HARRY, "Desert Intaglios", Science 83, Apr. 1983, pp. 50-54.

291. RIDLEY, JASPER, Statesman & Saint. (The Viking Press, New York, 1982).

292. BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

293. EDMUNDS, R. DAVID, The Shawnee Prophet. (University of Nebraska Press, Lincoln and London, 1938).

294. CAPPS, BENJAMIN, The Great Chiefs. (Time-Life Books, New York, 1975).

295. VAN BEEK, GUS W. "Digging up Tell Jemmeh", Archaeology 36, Vol. 1: 12-19, Jan./Feb. 1983.

296. WHITE, JOYCE C. "Ban Chiang: Discovery of a Lost Bronze Age", Archaeology 36, No.1:52-55, Jan./Feb. 1983.

297. PFEIFFER, JOHN, "At Ban Chiang a lost civilization comes to light", Smithsonian, Jan. 1933, pp. 98-107.

298. HANNERS, DAVID, "Archaeological find alters conceptions of early Indian life", Dallas Morning News, Feb. 20, 1983, pp. 1 & 2 AA.

299. ANATI, EMMANUEL, "Saving the World's Rock Art", Archaeology 36, No.2: 24-30, Mar./Apr. 1983.

300. SINSTO, YOSIHIKO H., "The Huahine Excavation: Discovery of an Ancient Polynesian Canoe", Archaeology 36, No.2: 10-15, Mar./Apr. 1983.

301. SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

302. WARNER, OLIVER (with DR. J.C. BEAGLEHOLE), Captain Cook and the South Pacific. (Cassell, London. American Heritage Publ. Co., Inc., New York, 1963).

303. BONNET, CHARLES, "Kerma: An African Kingdom of 2nd and 3rd Millennia, B.C., Archaeology 36, No.6: 38-45, Nov./Dec. 1983.

304. HESTER, THOMAS R.; SHAFER, HARRY J., ET AL, "Colhas's Stone Tool Industry", Archaeology 36, No.6: 46-52, Nov./Dec. 1983.

305. FOCKLER, SHIRLEY, "Kyongju", Travel Holiday, Sept. 1981, page 41.

306. KAO, JEFFREY AND ZUOSHENG, YANG, "On Jade Suits & Han Archeology", Archaeology 36, No.6: 30-37, Nov./Dec. 1983.

307. FLEMING, STUART, "Gallic Water Power: The mills of Barbegal", Archaeology 36, No.6: 68, Nov./Dec. 1983.

308. EDWARDS, MIKE, "Honduras: The Eye of the Storm", National Geographic 164: No.5: 608-637, Nov. 1983.

309. THE MAKING OF AMERICA: HAWAII, Cartographic Division of National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., Nov. 1983.

310. MORGAN LAEL, "Alaska's Far Out Islands: The Aleutians", National Geographic 164, No. 3: 336-363, Sept. 1983.

311. CAPUTO, ROBERT, "Ethiopia: Revolution in an Ancient Empire", National Geographic 163, No. 5: 614- 644, May 1983.

312. PATTERSON, CAROLYN BENNETT, "A Walk and Ride on the Wild Side", National Geographic 163, No. 5: 676-693, May 1983.

313. RIPINSKY, MICHAEL, "Camel Ancestry and Domestication in Egypt & the Sahara", Archaeology 36, No. 3: 21-27, May/June, 1983.

314. SANGRAW, CLARENCE, "Treasures from Shanghai", Archaeology 361, No.3: 60-63, May/June, 1983.

315. HAMBLIN, DORA JANE, "Treasures of the Sands", Smithsonian, Sept. 1983, pp. 43-53.

316. HOFFMAN, MICHAEL ALLEN, "Where Nations Began", Science 83, Oct. 1983, pp.42-51.

317. MOORE, R.I., (Editor), The Hamlyn Historical Atlas. (Hamlyn, London, N.Y., Sydney, Toronto, 1981).

318. PRIESTLEY, J.B., Literature & Western Man. (Harper & Bros., New York, 1960).

319. WILSON, EDMUND, The Dead Sea Scrolls. (Oxford University Press, New York, 1969).

320. SELTMAN, CHARLES, Women in Antiquity. (Cambridge University).

321. SWAIN, JOSEPH WARD, The Ancient World, Vol. II. (Harper & Bros., New York, 1950).

322. FOSDICK, HARRY EMERSON, Riverside Sermons. (Harper & Bros., New York, 1958).